<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></title>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//"/>
  <updated>2013-10-06T13:15:19+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://nsewell.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Common Cognitive Mistakes and How to Prevent Them]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/06/cognitive-mistakes/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-06T12:00:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/06/cognitive-mistakes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good post on the <a href="http://blog.bufferapp.com/thinking-mistakes-8-common-mistakes-in-how-we-think-and-how-to-avoid-them">Buffer blog on cognitive errors</a>. There&#8217;s good discussion of Dan Ariely&#8217;s work on anchoring and pricing, as well as this classic about the conjuction fallacy:</p>

<blockquote><p>In 1983 Kahneman and Tversky tested how illogical human thinking is by describing the following imaginary person:</p>

<blockquote><p>Linda is thirty-one years old, single, outspoken, and very bright. She majored in philosophy. As a student, she was deeply concerned with issues of discrimination and social justice, and also participated in antinuclear demonstrations.</p></blockquote>

<p>The researchers asked people to read this description, and then asked them to answer this question:</p>

<p>Which alternative is more probable?</p>

<ol>
<li>Linda is a bank teller.</li>
<li>Linda is a bank teller and is active in the feminist movement.
Here’s where it can get a bit tricky to understand (at least, it did for me!)—If answer #2 is true, #1 is also true. This means that #2 cannot be the answer to the question of probability.</li>
</ol>


<p>Unfortunately, few of us realize this, because we’re so overcome by the more detailed description of #2. Plus, as the earlier quote pointed out, stereotypes are so deeply ingrained in our minds that subconsciously apply them to others.</p>

<p>Roughly 85% of people chose option #2 as the answer. A simple choice of words can change everything.</p></blockquote>

<p>Adding more detail or extra assumptions can make an event seem more plausible, even though the event necessarily becomes less probable. Kahneman and Tversky tried <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/ji/conjunction_fallacy/">another experiment on probabilities</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Consider a regular six-sided die with four green faces and two red faces.  The die will be rolled 20 times and the sequences of greens (G) and reds (R) will be recorded.  You are asked to select one sequence, from a set of three, and you will win $25 if the sequence you chose appears on successive rolls of the die.  Please check the sequence of greens and reds on which you prefer to bet.</p>

<ol>
<li>RGRRR</li>
<li>GRGRRR</li>
<li>GRRRRR</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>65% of respondents chose option 2 as the most likely bet, as it matches the colours of the 6 sides, even though the shorter sequence 1 requires less correct rolls to complete.</p>

<p>Another example of the conjunction fallacy</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>&#8220;A complete suspension of diplomatic relations between the USA and the Soviet Union, sometime in 1983.&#8221;</li>
<li>&#8220;A Russian invasion of Poland, and a complete suspension of diplomatic relations between the USA and the Soviet Union, sometime in 1983.&#8221;</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Most respondents rate 2 as more likely than 1, even though 2 would necessarily entail 1, and it would be possible to have a complete suspension of diplomatic relations between the USA and USSR without invasion of any country, let alone Poland specifically.</p>

<p>If you have the time, consider how you&#8217;d approach a problem like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Hall_problem">Monty Hall problem</a> or this classic problem on breast cancer screening:</p>

<blockquote><p>1% of women at age forty who participate in routine screening have breast cancer.  80% of women with breast cancer will get positive mammographies.  9.6% of women without breast cancer will also get positive mammographies.  A woman in this age group had a positive mammography in a routine screening.  What is the probability that she actually has breast cancer?</p></blockquote>

<p>While most doctors give the intuitive answer of 80%, working though with Baysean logic gives the answer of 7.8%. Yudowsky has a <a href="http://yudkowsky.net/rational/bayes">long explanation</a> of the answer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[depression-kevin-breel]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/06/depression-kevin-breel/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-06T11:25:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/06/depression-kevin-breel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Kevin Breel&#8217;s impassioned talk at TEDxKids on depression and the need for honesty has been going around on social media. Depression is a taboo topic, but it&#8217;s important for everyone like myself who don&#8217;t suffer from clinical depression that the stigmatising of mental health issues can be more of a challenge for sufferers than their disease.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('VYs05qPycYQ');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VYs05qPycYQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('VYs05qPycYQ-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VYs05qPycYQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VYs05qPycYQ" id="VYs05qPycYQ" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VYs05qPycYQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VYs05qPycYQ" id="VYs05qPycYQ-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">(FIXED AUDIO) Kevin Breel: Confessions of a Depressed Comic at TEDxKids@Ambleside</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Kevin Breel is a 19 year old writer, comedian, and mental health activist. http://www.kevinbreel.com/

As a rising young stand up comedian in Canada, Kevin is also extremely involved in mental health work; actively speaking at schools and organizations.

His activist work has garnered international media attention and has impacted the lives of thousands of young people in North America.

For more: http://www.kevinbreel.com/

In this emotional talk, Kevin Breel speaks from the heart about his story with depression, how it&#8217;s impacted his life, and why he is ultimately grateful for it.

 
*** PLEASE NOTE:  this talk was originally uploaded on June 17, 2013 with an audio problem that prevented the sound from being audible on certain devices and web browsers.  This version of the talk is a re-upload with re-compressed and re-formatted sound that is compatible with any and all browser or device.  We apologize for any inconvenience.  


In the spirit of ideas worth spreading, TEDx is a program of local, self-organized events that bring people together to share a TED-like experience. At a TEDx event, TEDTalks video and live speakers combine to spark deep discussion and connection in a small group. These local, self-organized events are branded TEDx, where x = independently organized TED event. The TED Conference provides general guidance for the TEDx program, but individual TEDx events are self-organized.* (*Subject to certain rules and regulations)</div>
</div>


<p>Imgur had a <a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/UqbD7">good series of comics communicating the same timely message</a>. Allie has brought <a href="http://hyperboleandahalf.blogspot.com.au/">Hyperbole and a Half</a> back from hiatus.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Katy Perry - By the Grace of God]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/02/perry-grace-of-god/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T23:48:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/02/perry-grace-of-god</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Katy Perry</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Popular Science and I Turn Off Comments]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/26/comments-suck/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T03:18:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/26/comments-suck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Popular Science recently announced that they are shutting down the comments for new articles, as they can skew the readers into <a href="http://www.popsci.com/science/article/2013-09/why-were-shutting-our-comments">distrusting the expertise of scientists</a>. Recent studies have found that incivility in the comment section can alter the perception of the credibility of the articles they accompany. In one study, readers of a fake blog post on nanotechnology were asked to evaluate it&#8217;s impact, with <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/03/opinion/sunday/this-story-stinks.html?_r=0">one group exposed to vituperative comments</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> Uncivil comments not only polarized readers, but they often changed a participant&#8217;s interpretation of the news story itself.<br/>
 In the civil group, those who initially did or did not support the technology — whom we identified with preliminary survey questions — continued to feel the same way after reading the comments. Those exposed to rude comments, however, ended up with a much more polarized understanding of the risks connected with the technology.<br/>
 Simply including an ad hominem attack in a reader comment was enough to make study participants think the downside of the reported technology was greater than they&#8217;d previously thought.</p></blockquote>

<p>In a world where more and more discussion of contemporary issues happens online, this does not bode well for the public understanding of the importance of science, alread <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/22/opinion/welcome-to-the-age-of-denial.html">at all time lows</a>. As people search out information about health online, &#8220;Dr Google&#8221; can mislead patients and present <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/bigideas/stories/2011/04/28/3202794.htm">debunked information wrongly suggesting that vaccines don&#8217;t work</a>. A decentralised media landscape should have the ability to route around authoritarian regimes that try to censor it, but what happens when it undermines the structures that support the public respect of useful institutions?</p>

<p>Carl Sagan fundamentaly believed that the populace deserved to be educated about science, so that political or religious charlatans wouldn&#8217;t lure them into the next deception. Noting that either the people control the government or the government controls the people, he fiercely advocated that the science of evolution be taught in public schools so that the people could choose to understand science for themselves:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('U8HEwO-2L4w');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/U8HEwO-2L4w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('U8HEwO-2L4w-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/U8HEwO-2L4w/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U8HEwO-2L4w" id="U8HEwO-2L4w" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/U8HEwO-2L4w/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U8HEwO-2L4w" id="U8HEwO-2L4w-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Carl Sagan&#8217;s last interview with Charlie Rose (Full Interview)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Last interview with Charlie Rose</div>
</div>


<p>Benkler, in his 2006 book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wealth_of_Networks">The Wealth of Networks</a> portended a networked society enriched by freely available peer-produced cultural works in a shared online commons like wikipedia. The utipian visions of such an information ecosystem, however, have to be reconciled with the reality that most people are unaware of their own cognitive biases, and are increasingly polarised on science and other issues in the management of polities. Without educating people on cognative biases and getting them to understand the world as it is, not as they want it to be, then potentially a decentrilised internet will simply fracture people into tribal teams who all see things the same way. Unfortunately, some content algorithms are set up to give users content <a href="http://www.thefilterbubble.com/ted-talk">similar to what they&#8217;ve already seen</a> potentially limiting their exposure to information that contradicts their beliefs. Similarly, asking a search engine to find information on &#8220;global warming <em>science</em>&#8221; or &#8220;global warming <em>conspiracy</em>&#8221; may find different sets of sites, without the questioner perceiving any bias in their own question, and assuming that the results they see are representitive of the information as a whole.</p>

<p>In conclusion to all of this, the reason I don&#8217;t have comments is that like Popular Science, I don&#8217;t think they&#8217;re particularly helpful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sexual Politics in Rome]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/22/sexual-politics/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T14:27:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/22/sexual-politics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pope Francis has recently made international headlines by suggesting <a href="www.americamagazine.org/pope-interview">that the Catholic Church is too focused on gays and abortion</a>. This follows from his earlier comments that <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/pope-francis-assures-atheists-you-dont-have-to-believe-in-god-to-go-to-heaven-8810062.html">atheists who follow their conscience might be able to go to heaven</a> and that he isn&#8217;t in a position to judge <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/world/pope-on-gay-priests-who-am-i-to-judge-20130730-2qvh9.html">celibate gay Catholics</a>. This is a major turnaround from the culture war style dealings with the public the church pushed under Benedict, culminating in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhattan_Declaration:_A_Call_of_Christian_Conscience">Manhattan Declaration</a>&#8217;s popularity.</p>

<p>Most of the current culture war issues revolve around <a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/category/topics/feminism">gender politics</a>, and these disputes likely go back to the start of the church. This history channel documentary presents expert opinions on New Testament apocrypha, including the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acts_of_Paul_and_Thecla">Acts of Paul and Thecla</a></p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('4uZ7usrRiEc');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/4uZ7usrRiEc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('4uZ7usrRiEc-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/4uZ7usrRiEc/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uZ7usrRiEc" id="4uZ7usrRiEc" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/4uZ7usrRiEc/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uZ7usrRiEc" id="4uZ7usrRiEc-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Banned From The Bible - Secrets Of The Apostles</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Travel back to the blistering sands of the Holy Land, into the onion-domed chapels of Eastern Orthodox churches and onto the pages of the Koran. Unearth the trail of chapters that were left out of the ultimate version of the Scriptures. Included in the Koran is &#8220;The Life of Adam and Eve,&#8221; a detailed account of the creation story written before Jesus was born. The incestuous account of &#8220;The Book of Jubilees&#8221; was included in the Orthodox Old Testament and the Dead Sea Scrolls. &#8220;The Book of Enoch,&#8221; an ancient bestseller, relates the story of the man said in Genesis to have walked with God and been assumed directly into heaven. This fascinating collection offers a fresh perspective on the figures at the foundation of faith.</div>
</div>


<p>Thecla, as <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/religion/maps/primary/thecla.html">the story goes</a>, was a student of Paul&#8217;s that loved his preaching on asceticism and celibacy. After telling her fiance that she was no longer interested in marrying him, he became furious and sought out Paul to demand he stop teaching that virgins should remain chaste. He raised a multitude of angry husbands who were furious their wives stopped wanting sex, and brought Paul and Thecla to the governor, who condemned Paul to flogging and and Thecla to burning at the stake as a warning against their teachings. While Thecla was being brought to her pyre, she looked around for Paul, and saw in the crowd a vision of Jesus who ascended to heaven. Fixing her gaze on heaven as the pyre was lit, a miraculous hailstorm extinguished the flames, saving her. I find it interesting that while this story is entirely fictional, it has a number of similarities to the death of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_arc">Joan of Arc</a>.</p>

<p>Paul, it is said, then allowed Thecla to travel with him throughout the land, so long as she didn&#8217;t let her looks tempt the people. In Antioch, an magistrate called Alexander was taken with her, and grabbed her and kissed her as his way of proposition. Vowed to chastity, Thecla responded by knocking the crown off his head and ripping his cloak open so as to humiliate him in front of the people he ruled. Ashamed, Alexander took her to the governor who ordered her be thrown to the lions. Alexander had support from the men of the town, but the women of the town felt sympathy for the virgin and felt the punishment unjust. Before being cast into the amphitheatre to confront her fate, Thecla cried out in faith to her god to protect her innocence, and a she-lion fiercer than all the beasts fell down before her. The she-lion then killed the beasts that attacked Thecla, including male lions and a she-bear. This is probably a reference to Elisha&#8217;s she-bears, and Daniel&#8217;s lions.</p>

<div class="figure"><a href="http://dashinvaine.deviantart.com/art/Thecla-in-the-Arena-373006770"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/thecla-lions.jpg" link="http://dashinvaine.deviantart.com/art/Thecla-in-the-Arena-373006770" title="Thecla and the lions by Gordon Napier" ><p>Thecla and the lions by Gordon Napier</span></a></div>


<p>Next Thecla decided to baptise herself in a pool of sharks. Upon baptising herself in the name of Jesus, the sharks were struck with fire and lightning, and she was protected with a ring of fire. The women threw ointments into the field to knock out the other animals, so Alexander brought in his strongest bulls to have Thecla tied to. So the governor&#8217;s men tied a rope around Thecla&#8217;s waist to bulls that became enraged when hit by a hot poker in the nads. But the divine fire around Thecla burned off the rope fastened to the members of the bulls. When a powerful widow and relative of Caesar collapsed with worry for Thecla, the governor put an end to her trials fearing for his reputation, and officially pardoned Thecla. Thecla proclaimed the message of Christianity, converting many young men and women, and dressed as a man, led her new followers to find Paul who had run off amongst the commotion.</p>

<p>Thecla then went about the land preaching and performing miraculous healings, and set up a monastery where a large number of young women pledged their chastity. Tales of her miracles caused the sick in adjacent countries to travel to her for healing, making the local physicians furious at the competition, so they plotted to kill her. They decided that the virgin priestess must be raped to lose her powers, so conspired to pay local youths to assault her. They announced to her their intent to lie with her, before she cried out to heaven to save her chastity, and she ran into a miraculous fissure in a rock that closed up behind her, saving her one last time.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s a lot of things in this story that the early church fathers would have found objectionable, including the claim that Paul preached asceticism. But one of the most interesting things is how virginity went against the culture of the time. The story has Paul preaching that married couples should stay chaste, and while some <a href="http://blackamericaweb.com/129296/christian-couple-maintains-abstinence-two-years-after-marriage/">loopy couples today manage this for two whole years</a> most of the church&#8217;s preaching has changed to pro-natalist ideas. Interestingly, this may only have come after Paul and Jesus, as both believed that an apocalypse was coming in their lifetime, and children were unnecessary. Bart Ehrman has argued in <em>Forged</em> that 1 Thessalonians and parts of 1 Corinthians are a forgery of Pauline writings. This would actually fit with an asceticist Paul being watered down by later authors wanting to focus on childbearing, and making Christianity compatible with the Roman society of the time.</p>

<p>Justin Martyr, facing Roman persecution, presented his argument that Christianity was less of a threat to Roman order than atheistic philosophers like Socrates. The earlier church would have faced similar persecution, and had the similar desire to make Christianity seem compatible with the Roman culture of the time. In Book 1 of Politics Aristotle writes that the hierarchy of the state should be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Household_code">matched by the &#8220;building block&#8221; of the family</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Seeing then that the state is made up of households, before speaking of the state we must speak of the management of the household. The parts of the household are the persons who compose it, and a complete household consists of slaves and freemen. Now we should begin by examining everything in its least elements; and the first and least parts of a family are master and slave, husband and wife, father and children. We have therefore to consider what each of these three relations is and ought to be:—I mean the relation of master and servant, of husband and wife, and thirdly of parent and child.</p></blockquote>

<p>Plato advocates husbands ruling over their wives, <a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Politics_(Jowett)/Book_I#Different_kinds_of_rule_within_the_household:_.281.29_rule_of_master_over_slaves.3B_.282.29_of_father_over_children.3B_.283.29_of_husband_over_wife.">criticising Socrates for advocating for equality between the sexes</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>A husband and father rules over wife and children, both free, but the rule differs, the rule over his children being a royal, over his wife a constitutional rule. For although there may be exceptions to the order of nature, the male is by nature fitter for command than the female, just as the elder and full-grown is superior to the younger and more immature&#8230; moral virtue belongs to all of them; but the temperance of a man and of a woman, or the courage and justice of a man and of a woman, are not, as Socrates maintained, the same; the courage of a man is shown in commanding, of a woman in obeying</p></blockquote>

<p>Philo of Alexandria similarly reflected on the society of his time by documenting the importance of men controlling their families:</p>

<blockquote><p>if you ask any one of them about their national laws or customs, they can all tell you at once, without any difficulty; and the husband appears to be a master, endowed with sufficient authority to explain these laws to his wife, a father to teach them to his children, and a master to his servants.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Many Christian writers would have wanted to make Christianity compatible with these household codes, and the similar decrees that women submit to their husbands, save themselves in childbirth, and never preach (in Colossians, Ephesians, 1 Timothy, Titus and 1 Peter) may be a response to the Roman culture of the time. It may also be a way on clamping down on radical women&#8217;s movement of virgins that would have sprung up in the wake of texts like the Acts of Paul and Thecla, pushing for women to gain power over the men by denying their husbands sex - the one area in which they wielded considerable power. Even in times when women have jobs and education, there is widespread anxiety over the <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2012/06/27/the-ugly-side-of-modesty/">&#8220;sexualisation&#8221; of girls</a>, as though female sexuality is some dangerous, destabilising force.</p>

<p>All non-apocalyptic religions emphasise marriage, childbearing and family. Studies have found that when people are in a room with highly attractive people, they are <a href="http://www.psychologytoday.com/collections/201107/will-atheism-replace-religion/religious-piety-mating-strategy">more drawn to religious ideas that emphasise monogamy</a>. In nearly every religion, teachings can be conveniently cherry picked to conform to the type of <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/camelswithhammers/2013/06/fck-me-in-the-ass-because-i-love-jesus/">reproductive strategy that the adherent wants to achieve</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Politics Wrecks Your Brain]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/20/politics-wrecks-your-brain/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T12:13:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/20/politics-wrecks-your-brain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="figure"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/michaelkeen/3892771349/"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/confused-monkey.jpg" link="http://www.flickr.com/photos/michaelkeen/3892771349/" title="Confused Monkey" ><p>Confused Monkey</span></a></div>


<p>Everyone knows the old rule of avoiding bringing up religion and politics in polite company to keep discussions civil. Political disagreements often become pointed and vituperative because people who are otherwise open to new ideas can become defensive when their political views are questioned. While most people believe that others will see things their way if they simply <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_deficit_model">had the right information</a>, the reality is that people presented with new information will typically interpret in light of what they already know. A new study from Yale shows just how bad the problem can be, with people <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2013/09/new-study-politics-makes-you-innumerate">letting their political views get in the way of thinking clearly</a>.</p>

<p>Dan Kahan presented students with a simple number problem, asking them to determine whether a certain intervention improves or worsens a problem. Respondents were presented with one version asking about skin rashes (a neutral problem) and another version asking them about gun control and crime (a deeply polarising ongoing political argument). The respondents were presented with the following table and asked whether the intervention worked:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Kahan1.png"></p>

<p>Figuring out whether the cream works requires computing two ratios, and comparing whether the intervention worked better in the experimental group than the control group. In the experimental group, there is a 3:1 ratio of improvement to worsening, leading to the intuitive answer that the intervention works. But the correct answer is only found when that ratio is compared to the 5:1 improvement in the control group. As I&#8217;ve already written about, people can <a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/12/are-you-a-racist/">make errors in basic maths problems by settling for the intuitive answer</a>, rather than double checking their work to find the correct one.</p>

<p>On average only 41% of respondents got the answer about skin care right, with more numerate respondents getting the answer right more of the time. Unfortunately, with the question on gun control, highly numerate Democrats and Republicans tended to get the answer right when the intuitive answer didn&#8217;t align with their political philosophy, but were unlikely to get the answer right when the intuitive answer agreed with their political philosophy. Kahan&#8217;s data suggests that people with high scientific literacy and numeracy are still likely to misinterpret scientific findings if they agree or disagree with their political biases. Earlier work found that people with a high level of scientific literacy, on average, are <a href="http://www.nature.com/nclimate/journal/v2/n10/full/nclimate1547.html">more sceptical of climate change</a>, with views more politically polarised the more knowledgeable the individuals are.</p>

<p>When people are presented with information on the risks and opportunities of nanotechnology, those who oppose nuclear power usually oppose nanotechnology, and vice versa, as people interpret new information in line with their pre-existing beliefs. Philosophers and moral leaders have for millennia used parables and metaphors to present new ideas to students, getting them to reason about thought experiments outside of their intuitions about their current situation.</p>

<p>David Hume described reason as the &#8220;slave of the passions&#8221;, and Jonathan Haidt describes human cognition as an emotional elephant with a rational rider. We think with emotions <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dual_process_theory#Dual-process_accounts_of_reasoning">faster than we consciously reason with logic</a>. More often than not, the reasons we give for thinking one way or another are post-hoc rationalisations for intuitive emotional judgements. Haidt has suggested that many people see themselves in a tribe, with their own interests in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Realistic_conflict_theory">opposition to the other team&#8217;s</a>. People who support certain causes can see their identity as part of a group that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_cognition">believes in similar causes</a>.</p>

<p>So while many people view the divisiveness of political discourse as the fault of the current media landscape, the reality is that these kinds of debates have been going on for all of history. In Emperor Justinius&#8217;s Byzantium in 532, political factions took sides on chariot racing in the Hippodrome. Two major factions existed, the Blues and Greens racing teams, with the Blues receiving support from the Emperor and his faction, and the Greens a more popular team. Consider the historian Procopius&#8217;s view on the <a href="http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/procop-wars1.asp">politics of Byzantium in 532</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>In every city the population has been divided for a long time past into the Blue and the Green factions; but within comparatively recent times it has come about that, for the sake of these names and the seats which the rival factions occupy in watching the games, they spend their money and abandon their bodies to the most cruel tortures, and even do not think it unworthy to die a most shameful death. And they fight against their opponents knowing not for what end they imperil themselves, but knowing well that, even if they overcome their enemy the fight, the conclusion of the matter for them will be to be carried off straight away to the prison, and finally, after suffering extreme torture, to be destroyed. So there grows up in them against their fellow men a hostility which has no cause, and at no time does it cease or disappear, for it gives place neither to the ties of marriage nor of relationship nor of friendship, and the case is the same even though those who differ with respect to these colours be brothers or any other kin</p></blockquote>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Ben-Hur.jpg" title="Chariot Racing, from Ben Hur" ></p>

<p>The horse races could kill and maim participants, and some of the supporters, in their colours would smuggle weapons into the stadium (that seated 150,000) to start fights with the supporters of the other team. These fights broke out not just because of the sport, but because the tribal identity of the sports teams lead their supporters to fight over political issues, and theological debates coming from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalcedonian_Christianity">Fourth Ecumenical council</a>. This culminated in a riot that Procopius estimated <a href="http://blogs.smithsonianmag.com/history/2012/03/blue-versus-green-rocking-the-byzantine-empire/">killed up to 30,000</a></p>

<p>Eliazar Yudkowsky has reflected on just how meaningless and pointless these tribal conflicts can be. In a <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/gt/a_fable_of_science_and_politics/">thought experiment I love</a>, he presents a politicised version of Plato&#8217;s cave, inviting reflection on a future society living underground with no vision of the sky. They have only scraps of human history describing a &#8220;cerulean&#8221; sky, and factions of Blues and Greens have fought violently for years over the interpretation of the colour of the sky. After growing exhausted with the constant conflicts over the issue, an uneasy truce develops. People continue to be entrenched into the &#8220;Blue&#8221; or &#8220;Green&#8221; way of thinking about political and cultural issues like taxation, based on battle lines drawn from the original debate.</p>

<p>I highly recommend reading Yudkowsky&#8217;s post in full to understand the power of the metaphor. Briefly, he presents different people reaching the surface and seeing the sky for the first time. For some Blues, the confirmation of a blue sky encourages them to want to break the truce and fight out the issue. For some Greens, the disconfirmation of everything they&#8217;ve lived for crushes them, and they must confront the cruel truth that while the reviled Blues are right. For the professor who&#8217;s always emphasised that both positions could be right, the single colour of the sky is too much of a risk to the harmony of society to embrace. For one Green, the admission that she was wrong for most of her life will hurt her family and leave her with few friends, but her committment to intellectual integrity requires her to announce her changed belief. The final traveller, seeing only the beauty and wonder of the sky, marvels at the new environment and decides to go exploring.</p>

<p>Knowing that political differences arise from the way that people deal with information, rather than a lack of information, leads me to belive that the last traveller probably has the best response. Sometimes you&#8217;ll find new information that other people wouldn&#8217;t accept, and it&#8217;s better just to explore the world without them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kevin Rudd on Biblical Slavery]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/03/rudd-slavery/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-03T21:32:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/09/03/rudd-slavery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>KRudd has received strong support on social media for <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-09-02/rudd-appears-on-q-and-a/4930540">his views on same sex marriage</a>:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('CdU3ooAZSH8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CdU3ooAZSH8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('CdU3ooAZSH8-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CdU3ooAZSH8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CdU3ooAZSH8" id="CdU3ooAZSH8" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CdU3ooAZSH8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CdU3ooAZSH8" id="CdU3ooAZSH8-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Rudd launches passionate gay marriage defence</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Kevin Rudd rebukes a questioner on ABC Television&#8217;s Q&A program on the issue of whether he should have changed stance on gay marriage. Story: http://bit.ly/15upc7Z</div>
</div>


<p>Rudd further defended the views</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('q4ax30bbRHk');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/q4ax30bbRHk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('q4ax30bbRHk-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/q4ax30bbRHk/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q4ax30bbRHk" id="q4ax30bbRHk" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/q4ax30bbRHk/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q4ax30bbRHk" id="q4ax30bbRHk-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Prime Minister Kevin Rudd on the Bible, same sex marriage, slavery, discrimination</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >The day after PM Kevin Rudd&#8217;s comments on Q&A to a Christian pastor, about same sex marriage and saying that the Bible sees slavery as &#8216;a natural condition&#8217;.

12:30pm, 3 September 2013, Tasmania-

Reporter: Just on your exchange last night with a Christian pastor about same-sex marriage, are you concerned your position on marriage equality risks alienating the Christian vote?

Kevin Rudd: You know something? This is a really interesting example of a question, because it&#8217;s about political perceptions of a given action. I&#8217;m concerned about what we do. I&#8217;m actually concerned about answering directly a question about what we do about all those Australians who are in same-sex relationships, who are asking for a basic exercise of human decency which is called &#8216;marriage equality&#8217;. And so, if it offends some people, so be it. But my job is to say what I am standing up for, what we would do if we are re-elected, and how we would go about doing it. And I&#8217;ve done that. And in my response to that fellow last night, when people start hurling Biblical quotes at me &#8211; I know a bit about my New Testament as well. And as I said last night, if you&#8217;re going to be a serious Biblicist about these questions, we&#8217;d still be supporting slavery in the 21st century, and by the way, to all of you who are women, it says in the New Testament according to St Paul that wives should be submissive to their husbands. So just bear all that in mind, cause it&#8217;s in the Bible. In fact, if we took it that seriously, you know what? We may as well repeal, also, the Sex Discrimination Act because that creates a different set of circumstances. Let&#8217;s get real about this. The core principles are those I outlined last night. And what happens with any civilised country is over time, they apply them to different sets of circumstances. And we did that in the 19th century with slavery, we did that in the 20th century &#8211; far too late &#8211; in terms of the rights of women. 21st century &#8211; we should look at the rights of same-sex couples. These are questions of principle. And therefore they should be addressed firmly as such. And as to their political consequences, that&#8217;s a matter for others. I&#8217;m there to argue a proposition and my reasons for it. I think I did it fairly clearly last night.</div>
</div>


<p>The religious community, of course, is furious that their authority to oppose legislation the <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-08-29/vote-compass-gay-marriage-euthanasia-abortion/4918494">majority of Australians want</a> is questioned by the issue of the relevance of the bible to contemporary society. Sandy Grant has trotted out the tired evangelical claim that the <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-09-03/grant-how-could-a-christian-pm-call-the-bible-pro-slavery/4932422">bible doesn&#8217;t endorse slavery</a> even though it&#8217;s been interpreted that way for most of human history. Grant claims &#8220;Even a cursory reading of the Bible would tell you it never says slavery is a &#8220;natural condition&#8221;. Never. Not once.&#8221; Of course, the Curse of Caanan, commonly called the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curse_of_Ham">Curse of Ham</a> in Genesis 9 says that some races deserve to be the &#8220;least of the slaves&#8221; to the others:</p>

<blockquote><p> Noah, a man of the soil, began to plant a vineyard. <em>21</em> When he drank some of the wine, he got drunk and uncovered himself inside his tent. <em>22</em> Ham, the father of Canaan, saw his father&#8217;s nakedness and told his two brothers who were outside. <em>23</em> Shem and Japheth took the garment and placed it on their shoulders. Then they walked in backwards and covered up their father&#8217;s nakedness. Their faces were turned the other way so they did not see their father&#8217;s nakedness.</p>

<p> 24 When Noah awoke from his drunken stupor he learned what his youngest son had done to him. 25 So he said,</p>

<p> &#8220;Cursed be Canaan!<br/>
 The <strong>lowest of slaves</strong><br/>
 he will be to his brothers.&#8221; <br/>
 26 He also said,</p>

<p> &#8220;Worthy of praise is the LORD, the God of Shem! <br/>
 May Canaan be the slave of Shem!<br/>
 27 May God enlarge Japheth&#8217;s territory and numbers!<br/>
 May he live in the tents of Shem <br/>
 and may Canaan be his slave!&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>And so because Ham didn&#8217;t cover up his father&#8217;s nakedness, instead left his father&#8217;s tent to tell his brothers and laugh at his father (and possibly bring out Noah&#8217;s garment to show his brothers, before they honourably bring back &#8220;the garment&#8221;) all of Ham&#8217;s descendants are cursed to be the lowest of slaves (<strong>עֶבֶד עֲבָדִים eved avadim</strong>). The curse is pronounced on Canaan, not Ham.</p>

<p>While Genesis 9 only mentiones the Canaanites (Phoenecia/Palestine) as the people group under the curse of slavery from Ham, Genesis 10:6 also mentions the Cush (Nubia/Ethiopia), Mizraim (Egypt) and Put (Libya). Traditional Christian understanding asserts that Japheth went on to father the people group that became Western Europeans and Caucasians. Biblical literallists have used this understanding of Genesis for generations to support the idea that black people were under a curse from God to serve the white people as slaves. Unfortunately the idea humans come from Noah&#8217;s family <a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/texas-public-school-course-teaches-racial-origins-traced-noah">still being taught by creationists in Texan public schools</a>.</p>

<p>Grant admits that the bible regulates slavery, but notes &#8220;it is true that the Bible also honestly records, and sometimes regulates, the practice of slavery. It is naïve in the extreme - just a poor reading strategy - to assume an endorsement&#8230; because it is regulated.&#8221; Of course, with modern apologetics, Grant can construct all kinds of fancy arguments about how &#8220;recording&#8221; and &#8220;regulating&#8221; slavery is not an endorsement, but that was never the way that <a href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/lib-edu/education/psd/nation/halifax.htm">slave owners saw things in 1785</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>An Attempt carried on by the Enemies of our Country, Tools of the British Administration, and supported by a Number of deluded Men among us, to <strong>wrest from us our Slaves</strong> by an act of the Legislature for a general Emancipation of them&#8230; But is unsupported by the Word of God, and will be ruinous to Individuals and to the Public.</p>

<p>It is unsupported by the Word of God. Under the Old Testament Dispensation, Slavery was permitted by the Deity himself. Thus it is recorded, in Levit. Chap. 25. Ver. 44, 45, 46. &#8216;Both they Bond-men, and Bond-maids, which thou shalt have, shall be of the Heathen that are round about you; of them shall ye buy Bond-men and Bond-maids. Moreover, of the Children of the Strangers, that do sojourn among you of them shall ye buy, and of their Families that are with you, which they beget in your Land, and they shall be your Possession, and ye shall take them, as an Inheritance for your Children after you, to inherit them for a Possession; they shall be your Bond-men forever.&#8217; This <strong>Permission to possess and inherit Bond Servants</strong>, we have Reason to conclude, was continued through all the Revolutions of the Jewish Government, down to the Advent of our Lord. And we do not find, that either he or his Apostles abridged it. On the Contrary, the Freedom which the Followers of Jesus were taught to expect, was a Freedom from the Bondage of Sin and Satan, and from the Dominion of their Lusts and Passions; but as to their outward Condition, whatever that was, wether Bond or Free, when they embraced Christianity, it was to remain the same afterwards. This Saint Paul hath expressly told us 1 Cor. Chap. 7. Ver. 20th. where he is speaking directly to this very Point; &#8216;Let every Man abide in the same Calling, wherein he is called&#8217;; and at Ver. 24. &#8216;Let every Man wherein he is called therein abide with God.&#8217; Thus it is evident the above Attempt is unsupported by the Divine Word.</p></blockquote>

<p>Critically, Grant implies that there is such a clear difference between endoresment and regulation that it would be obvious to an informed reader which is which. In reality, proslavery apologists like James Henley Thornwell would simply present the <a href="http://rachelheldevans.com/blog/is-abolition-biblical">&#8220;plain reading&#8221; of scripture</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;On the eve of the Civil War, interpretations of the Bible that made the most sense to the broadest public were those that incorporated the defining experiences of America into the hermeneutics used for interpreting what the infallible text actually meant. In this effort, those who like James Henley Thornwell defended the legitimacy of slavery in the Bible had the easiest task. The procedure, which by 1860 had been repeated countless times, was uncomplicated. First, open the Scriptures and read, at say Leviticus 25:45, or, even better, at 1 Corinthians 7:20-21. Second, decide for yourself what these passages mean. Don’t wait for a bishop or a king or a president or a meddling Yankee to tell you what the passage means, but decide for yourself. Third, if anyone tries to convince  you that you are not interpreting such passages in the natural, commonsensical, ordinary meaning of the words, look hard at what such a one believes with respect to other biblical doctrines. If you find in what he or she says about such doctrines the least hint of unorthodoxy, as inevitably you will, then you may rest assured that you are being asked to give up not only the plain meaning of Scripture, but also the entire trust in the Bible that made the country into such a great Christian civilization.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>By defending what he claimed was the &#8220;plain&#8221; reading of scripture, Thornwell could then oppose supporters of abolitionism by accusing them of attacking Christianity. In a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Henley_Thornwell">speech, he stated</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The parties in this conflict are not merely abolitionists and slaveholders—they are atheists, socialists, communists, red republicans, jacobins, on one side, and the friends of order and regulated freedom on the other. In one word, the world is the battleground—Christianity and Atheism the combatants; and the progress of humanity at stake</p></blockquote>

<p>Grant states that &#8220;Any material regulating the practice of slavery needs to be read alongside the extensive material which shows the Bible ultimately opposes slavery.&#8221; By that maxim, any material that appears to offer exculpatory evidence must also be read alongside other material that refutes it. For instance, Grant claims that Yahweh&#8217;s freeing of the Israelite people from captivity proves that he doesn&#8217;t like slavery:</p>

<blockquote><p>It involves God&#8217;s rescue of his people out of slavery! Slavery is presented as unequivocally unpleasant and cruel. Refer Exodus 2:23-25:</p>

<p>During that long period, the king of Egypt died. The Israelites groaned in their slavery and cried out, and their cry for help because of their slavery went up to God. God heard their groaning and he remembered his covenant with Abraham, with Isaac and with Jacob. So God looked on the Israelites and was concerned about them. (NIV84)</p></blockquote>

<p>What Grant conveniently ignores is that during the Exodus, the Israelite people had already been given the dominion over other races back in Genesis 17: 12-13, with Abraham owning Hagar, a slave girl from Egypt. The narrative has the Israelites escaping from Egypt and immediately being given permission to give passover to their own slaves, in Exodus 12: (ESV)</p>

<blockquote><p>43 And the Lord said to Moses and Aaron, “This is the statute of the Passover: no foreigner shall eat of it, 44 but every slave that is bought for money may eat of it after you have circumcised him.</p></blockquote>

<p>Yahweh goes on in Exodus 20 to give clear commands</p>

<ul>
<li>You shall not murder.</li>
<li>You shall not commit adultery.</li>
<li>You shall not steal.</li>
<li>You shall not give false testimony against your neighbor.</li>
</ul>


<p>But the final commandment is &#8220;You shall not covet your neighbor&#8217;s house. You shall not covet your neighbor&#8217;s wife, nor his male servant, nor his female servant, nor his ox, nor his donkey, nor anything that belongs to your neighbor.&#8221; If god wanted to lay down a clear, unequivocal law against keeping slaves, he could easily do so like with murder, adultery, stealing and lying. Instead he categorises humans as property, like wives treated as chattel.</p>

<p>Grant claims that 1 Timothy 1 opposes the slave trade, but neglects to mention that the first slave ship to bring Africans to America was called &#8221;<a href="http://graceinafrica.com/the-good-ship-jesus/">The Good Ship Jesus</a>&#8221;:</p>

<blockquote><p>A deeply religious gentleman, Hawkins insisted that his crew “serve God daily” and “love another” as he sailed his ship for Africa.  In a short time he had gathered up over 300 Africans “partly by sword and partly by other means.”  The other means included promising them free land and riches in the new world.</p></blockquote>

<p>If Yahweh wanted to give a clear prohibition he could do that.
Grant notes that Ephesians 6 &#8220;counter-culturally warns masters never to mistreat their slaves.&#8221; Of course, he fails to note that by a similar standard, 1 Corinthians 6:16-18 counter-culturally condemns prostitution clearly and unequivocally with no concession to the economic and cultural situation of the time, when to Corinthianise meant to fornicate.</p>

<p>Grant claims that &#8220;Paul encourages the emancipation of a runaway slave, Onesimus, in his letter to the wronged-master, Philemon.&#8221; He doesn&#8217;t note that the slave was sent back, and the note encouraged the slavemaster to seek dues from Paul. But Paul asserts the right for slavemasters to have their human propertyreturned, while he only argues for the emancipation of one slave, and the way in which future slavemasters would interpret how to deal with runaway slaves is left up to the circumstances.</p>

<p>Many other articles counter the idea that the <a href="http://www.skepticink.com/reasonablyfaithless/2013/02/07/slavery-bible-style/">bible is overwhelmingly against slavery</a>, or that Christians thoughout history have been <a href="http://debunkingchristianity.blogspot.com.au/2010/07/slave-to-incompetence-truth-behind.html">overwhelmingly on the side of abolitionism</a>.</p>

<p>Justin Welby, on launching a campaign to <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2013/07/05/homophobic-bullying-campaign-coe_n_3551701.html">stamp out anti-gay bullying in Anglican schools</a> noted &#8220;The majority of the population rightly detests homophobic behaviour or anything that looks like it and sometimes they look at us and see what they don&#8217;t like.&#8221; He followed up talking about his vote against marriage equality in the UK parliament, <a href="http://www.secularism.org.uk/blog/2013/08/on-homophobia-and-racism">noting</a></p>

<blockquote><p>We have seen changes in the idea about sexuality, sexual behaviour. We have to face the fact that the vast majority of people under 35 not only think that what we&#8217;re saying is incomprehensible but also think that we&#8217;re plain wrong and wicked and equate it to racism and other forms of gross and atrocious injustice. We have to be real about that.</p></blockquote>

<p>The question evangelicals now need to answer is, how would you like to be remembered by your kids? As someone who changed with the times, or someone who kept holding onto views that became increasingly despised?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Miley Cyrus, How Far You've Come]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/08/27/miley-cyrus/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-27T21:19:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/08/27/miley-cyrus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>http://www.sineadoconnor.com/2013/10/open-letter-to-miley-cyrus/</p>

<p>http://amandapalmer.net/blog/20131003/</p>

<p>When Destiny Hope Cyrus rose to fame after being cast in Disney&#8217;s Hannah Montanna, many were enamoured with the country singer&#8217;s daughter from the buckle of the bible belt. To add to her family friendly charm, she described her Christian faith as &#8221;<a href="http://www.parade.com/celebrity/2010/03/miley-cyrus.html">very important</a>&#8221; and wrote about keeping the faith in <em>The Climb</em>. Some even saw her as part of a new movement of conservative Christian public figures that would bring the US <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20130703010527/http://conservapedia.com/Essay:The_Coming_Fifth_Great_Awakening_in_America">back to social conservatism in a new great awakening</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/cyrus-c.png" alt="Conservapedia praises Cyrus's Christianity" /></p>

<p>Cyrus in 2007 described her stardom as being &#8221;<a href="http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/life/television/news/2007-01-10-miley-cyrus_x.htm">God&#8217;s will</a>&#8221;, promising that she wouldn&#8217;t start going crazy under the spotlight.</p>

<blockquote><p>In a pop culture filled with young hot starlets gone wild, isn&#8217;t Billy Ray worried that pretty Miley will soon start doing nutty Britney Spears-eque things, like not wearing underpants?</p>

<p>&#8220;She&#8217;s never wore underwear,&#8221; Billy Ray says without missing a beat.</p>

<p>&#8220;Dad!&#8221; Miley says.</p></blockquote>

<p>Miley went on to present an increasingly edgy image, with most media outlets <a href="http://www.theonion.com/articles/let-me-explain-why-miley-cyrus-vma-performance-was,33632/">disproportionately covering her antics instead of actual news</a>. This is the <a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/Qy8xE">latest controvertial act</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/cyrus.gif" alt="Cyrus VMA performance" /></p>

<p>Why would she do such a thing? Probably because Professor Lawrence Krauss has addled her brain:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/cyrus-1.png" alt="Cyrus tweeting a beautiful quote from Lawrence Krauss" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Voltaire Dumping on Leibniz]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/08/15/voltaire-dumping-leibniz/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-15T12:54:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/08/15/voltaire-dumping-leibniz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/krauss-craig.jpg" alt="William Lane Craig and Lawrence Krauss at Sydney Town Hall" />
Earlier this week William Lane Craig and Lawrence Krauss discussed cosmologogy and arguments for and against the existence of God. Professor Krauss concluded his opening remarks warning the audience against following the logic of syllogisms like this one:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>All mammals exhibit homosexual behaviour</li>
<li>William Lane Craig is a mammal</li>
<li>Therefore, William Lane Craig exhibits homosexual behaviour</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Krauss briefly noted that the 2003 paper by Arvind Borde, Alan Guth, and Alexander Vilenkin (BGV hypothesis) that the universe has a beginning has issues.
Craig has previously tried to use the BGV hypothesis to suggest that the universe must have a beginning, and therefore a creator.
But as Vilenkin has pointed out <a href="https://debunkingwlc.wordpress.com/2010/07/14/borde-guth-vilenkin/">in his book</a> it would be &#8220;far too simplistic&#8221; to use his work to prove the existence of God (on the same page Dr Craig quotes from to support his argument). Further, Vilenkin mentioned in <a href="http://arizonaatheist.blogspot.com.au/2010/05/william-lane-craigs-arguments-for-god.html">an email</a> &#8220;the expansion of the universe must have had a beginning. You can evade the theorem by postulating that the universe was contracting prior to some time.&#8221; Craig has also relied on trying to say that because some collections cannot be infinite, <a href="http://www.skepticink.com/reasonablyfaithless/2013/03/25/infinity-minus-infinity/">no collections can be infinite, and past time cannot be infinite</a>.</p>

<p>Krauss went on to criticise the second premise of Craig&#8217;s version of Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz&#8217;s cosmological argument, before Dr Craig went on to present it as &#8220;logically airtight.&#8221; The first premise is Leibniz&#8217;s Principle of Sufficient Reason, which is applied to the universe:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>Anything that exists has an explanation of its existence, either in the necessity of its own nature or in an external cause</li>
<li>If the universe has an explanation of its existence, that explanation is God.</li>
<li>The universe exists.</li>
<li>Therefore, the universe has an explanation of its existence (from 1, 3)</li>
<li>Therefore, the explanation of the existence of the universe is God (from 2, 4).</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Craig also presents a <a href="http://mind.ucsd.edu/syllabi/02-03/01w/readings/taylor.pdf">Richard Taylor’s</a> illustration of a translucent ball, saying that if someone found a transluscent ball in nature they would probably seek an explanation for the ball&#8217;s exsistence rather than deciding it just exists inexplicably. He claims that the same should apply whether the ball is the size of a person, a car, a planet or a universe. But no matter the size of the ball, we still need evidence to <a href="http://www.maverick-atheism.org/2012/09/leibnizian-cosmological-argument-2.html">determine if the ball began to exist, or has an external cause</a>. And as Victor Stenger states &#8220;no cause is evident in the decay of a radioactive nucleus.&#8221;</p>

<p>Krauss went on to mention how many things in the universe seem to have an apparent design, but are formed randomly. For instance, geodesic domes seem to be designed, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckminsterfullerene">Carbon-60 forms a structure that resembles a geodesic dome</a>. Similarly, life was once thought to be &#8220;fine tuned&#8221; by God on Earth, until we had evidence that self-replicating organic molecules can gain information by evolution though natural selection. And while the universe may appear to be designed for life, the fact that it is the only universe known to have life is not surprising as we&#8217;re in it.</p>

<p>Craig suggested that theology is &#8220;the queen of the sciences&#8221; despite having previously asserted that God is not subject to science. Krauss asked what new information theology had provided in the past 300 years (and mentioned that biology and physics can answer that question without arguing over the semantics of &#8216;knowledge&#8217;). The moderator moved on to another question. Krauss had previously mentioned that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_Leibniz">Leibniz</a>, who died in 1716 had no awareness of Quantum Mechanics, so his views on cosmology were irrelevant.</p>

<p>I would argue that not only are Leibinz&#8217;s ideas irrelevant, they&#8217;ve already been dumped on by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltaire">Voltaire</a>. Leibniz believed that this world is the best of all possible worlds, and coined the word theodicy for his defence of a good God in a world that has much evil. His satirical novella <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candide">Candide</a> eloquently skewers the notion with the ideas of Dr Pangloss (&#8220;All Talk&#8221;):</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;It is demonstrable,&#8221; said he, &#8220;that things cannot be otherwise than as they are; for all being created for an end, all is necessarily for the best end. Observe, that the nose has been formed to bear spectacles—thus we have spectacles. Legs are visibly designed for stockings—and we have stockings. Stones were made to be hewn, and to construct castles—therefore my lord has a magnificent castle; for the greatest baron in the province ought to be the best lodged. Pigs were made to be eaten—therefore we eat pork all the year round. Consequently they who assert that all is well have said a foolish thing, they should have said all is for the best.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Of course, this world of cause and effect exists for <em>sufficient reason</em>:</p>

<blockquote><p>One day Cunegonde, while walking near the castle, in a little wood which they called a park, saw between the bushes, Dr. Pangloss giving a lesson in experimental natural philosophy to her mother&#8217;s chamber-maid, a little brown wench, very pretty and very docile. As Miss Cunegonde had a great disposition for the sciences, she breathlessly observed the repeated experiments of which she was a witness; she clearly perceived the force of the Doctor&#8217;s reasons, the effects, and the causes; she turned back greatly flurried, quite pensive, and filled with the desire to be learned; dreaming that she might well be a <strong>sufficient reason</strong> for young Candide, and he for her.</p>

<p>She met Candide on reaching the castle and blushed; Candide blushed also; she wished him good morrow in a faltering tone, and Candide spoke to her without knowing what he said. The next day after dinner, as they went from table, Cunegonde and Candide found themselves behind a screen; Cunegonde let fall her handkerchief, Candide picked it up, she took him innocently by the hand, the youth as innocently kissed the young lady&#8217;s hand with particular vivacity, sensibility, and grace; their lips met, their eyes sparkled, their knees trembled, their hands strayed. Baron Thunder-ten-Tronckh passed near the screen and beholding this <strong>cause and effect</strong> chased Candide from the castle with great kicks on the backside; Cunegonde fainted away; she was boxed on the ears by the Baroness, as soon as she came to herself; and all was consternation in this most magnificent and most agreeable of all possible castles.</p></blockquote>

<p>He goes on to satirically reflect on the theodicy of Leibniz&#8217;s free will defence:</p>

<blockquote><p>After the earthquake had destroyed three-fourths of Lisbon, the sages of that country could think of no means more effectual to prevent utter ruin than to give the people a beautiful auto-da-fé; for it had been decided by the University of Coimbra, that the burning of a few people alive by a slow fire, and with great ceremony, is an infallible secret to hinder the earth from quaking.</p>

<p>In consequence hereof, they had seized on a Biscayner, convicted of having married his godmother, and on two Portuguese, for rejecting the bacon which larded a chicken they were eating; after dinner, they came and secured Dr. Pangloss, and his disciple Candide, the one for speaking his mind, the other for having listened with an air of approbation. They were conducted to separate apartments, extremely cold, as they were never incommoded by the sun&#8230; They marched in procession thus habited and heard a very pathetic sermon, followed by fine church music. Candide was whipped in cadence while they were singing; the Biscayner, and the two men who had refused to eat bacon, were burnt; and Pangloss was hanged, though that was not the custom. The same day the earth sustained a most violent concussion.</p></blockquote>

<p>Lenny Bernstein&#8217;s oparetta is similarly brilliant. This is him conducting the opening overture:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('422-yb8TXj8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/422-yb8TXj8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('422-yb8TXj8-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/422-yb8TXj8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=422-yb8TXj8" id="422-yb8TXj8" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/422-yb8TXj8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=422-yb8TXj8" id="422-yb8TXj8-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Candide Overture: Leonard Bernstein conducting</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Candide Overture, conducted by the composer himself, Leonard Bernstein.  Concert performance of Candide with June Anderson, Jerry Hadley, Christa Ludwig, Nicolai Gedda - London Symphony Orchestra (London, December 13, 1989).</div>
</div>


<p>Auto da fe</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('oEZon0KvXyw');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/oEZon0KvXyw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('oEZon0KvXyw-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/oEZon0KvXyw/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oEZon0KvXyw" id="oEZon0KvXyw" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/oEZon0KvXyw/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oEZon0KvXyw" id="oEZon0KvXyw-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Candide - Auto-da-fé (Hadley/Green/Bayley/Jenkins/Benson/Suart/Treleaven)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Auto-da-fé (What a day!)

Jerry Hadley (Candide)
Adolph Green (Dr. Pangloss)
Clive Bayley (Bear-keeper/Inquisitor)
Neil Jenkins (Cosmetic merchant/Inquisitor)
Lindsay Benson (Doctor/Inquisitor)
Richard Suart (Junkman/Inquisitor)
John Treleaven (Alchemist/Inquisitor)
London Symphonic Chorus
London Symphonic Orchestra

Director: Leonard Bernstein</div>
</div>


<p>Diana Damrau singing Glitter and be Gay</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('oByViX0t-IE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/oByViX0t-IE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('oByViX0t-IE-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/oByViX0t-IE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oByViX0t-IE" id="oByViX0t-IE" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/oByViX0t-IE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oByViX0t-IE" id="oByViX0t-IE-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Diana Damrau - Glitter and be Gay</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Diana Damrau sings Glitter and be Gay from Bernstein&#8217;s &#8220;Candide&#8221; at the 2007 Richard Tucker Music Foundation Gala. Asher Fisch, Conductor and member of the Metropolitan Opera Orchestra.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Failure of the Western Gospel]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/19/failure-of-the-western-gospel/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T12:57:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/19/failure-of-the-western-gospel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>http://markbiwwa.com/2011/06/08/26-awesomely-funny-church-signs/</p>

<p>Christians in the West have a habit of making all the depictions of biblical figures white. This is painfully evident in The Bible series on the History Channel. The series starts its Eurocentric presentation of Jewish scriptures with Adam and Eve as white supermodels:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/adam-eve.jpg" alt="Adam and Eve as white supermodels" /></p>

<p>At least they figured out that &#8220;forbidden fruit&#8221; is a fig, long believed to be an aphrodisiac in the Middle East. The producers also cast Mohamen Mehdi Ouazanni as Satan, someone <a href="http://www.news.com.au/entertainment/television/barack-obama-lookalike-mohamen-mehdi-ouazanni-cast-as-satan-in-the-bible/story-e6frfmyi-1226600220510">many have commented has a resemblence to Barak Obama</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/satan-obama.jpg" alt="Barack Obama looks like Satan" /></p>

<p>While Jesus is shown as distinctively Causasian, Samson was cast as a black actor leading Reverend Wil Gafney to call the series <a href="http://www.wilgafney.com/2013/03/11/black-samson-white-women-on-the-history-channel">&#8220;a continuation of slave-holding racist exegesis.&#8221;</a> The December 2002 cover of Popular Mechanics featured a <a href="http://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/forensics/1282186">reconstruction of the faces of males from around the time of Jesus</a>. The New Testament says that Jesus disappeared into crowds, and if Jesus looked like other men of the time this is what he would have looked like:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/black-jesus-face.jpg" alt="Black Jesus by Popular Mechanics" /></p>

<p>The Irish producer Roma Downey chose to cast herself as Mary the mother of Jesus, and chose to give the role of Jesus of Nazareth to a similarly white skinned Portugese actor Diogo Morgado:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/white-jesus.jpg" alt="White Jesus" /></p>

<p>If Jesus ever had hair this long, he&#8217;d probably get it stuck in his vice. Europeans love to show Jesus with long hair, despite Paul&#8217;s teaching in 1 Corinthians 11:14 clearly specifying &#8220;Does not nature itself teach you that if a man has long hair, it is a disgrace for him&#8221;. In fact, many contemporary scholars have noted that the Corinthian church existed at a time when male prostitutes had longer hair than other men to make them stand out as homosexuals. Despite this, modern evangelicals have remoulded Orthodox representations of Jesus into a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_movement">New Age white hippie</a>.</p>

<p>But this isn&#8217;t the only way that Westerners present biblical stories specifically moulded to their target audience, against the grain of what the bible actually says. Western individualists love to read bible passages as written specifically for them, ignoring the original audience and context. For most of the history of Christianity, lay people did not read scriputre themselves, they had the bible read in a corporate context. It wasn&#8217;t until 1455 that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gutenberg_Bible">Johannes Gutenberg mass produced 180 bibles</a> and until 1561 that John Knox demanded universal education.</p>

<p>Now Americans complain that while most <a href="http://global.christianpost.com/news/dr-lamar-vest-on-why-owning-seven-bibles-is-not-enough-70608/">own four to seven bibles they hardly ever get time to read them</a>. Instead they&#8217;ll be encouraged to read the bible just <a href="http://au.christiantoday.com/article/Daily-Bible-reading-best-predictor-of-spiritual-growth/13987.htm">25 words at a time</a>. Not only are Westerners time-poor, they all too often seek a <a href="http://rachelheldevans.com/blog/bible-not-into-you">&#8220;reaffirmation of the individualistic, me-centered, and consumerist tendencies of American religious culture.&#8221;</a> Many megachurches are happy to give them a &#8220;seeker friendly&#8221; doctrine written by and for modern American individualists:</p>

<blockquote><p>Passages that were originally written for groups of people, and intended to be read and applied in a community setting (the nation of Israel, the various early churches, the first followers of Jesus), have been manipulated to communicate a personal, individual message&#8230;</p>

<p>We see this everywhere: in worship set lists that focus exclusively on individual worship, individual sin, and individual connection to God; in desk calendars that turn Jeremiah 29:11 (“For I know the plans I have for you, says the Lord…”)  into a personal promise; in the disproportionate emphasis in our churches on personal Bible study, personal prayer, and one’s “personal walk with God.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Worse, publishers responding to people who like the sound of their own names will &#8220;personalize&#8221; the bible for them, massaging scripture into an ego stoking circlejerk. Isiah 53 no longer reads &#8220;he was pierced for <strong>our</strong> transgressions&#8221; but can be made to say &#8220;he was pierced for <strong>Rachel&#8217;s</strong> transgressions. He was crushed for <strong>Rachel&#8217;s</strong> iniquities.&#8221; The website lets you put in literally any name at all:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/dahmer.jpg" alt="The bible according to Jeffrey Dahmer" /></p>

<h3>It ain&#8217;t in the bible, but it outta be</h3>

<p>This culture is happy to change the bible not only to suit the emotional desires of consumerists but also to make it suit contemporary social and political needs. Often Jesus is not presented as a redeemer saving individuals into a community, but is presented as a &#8220;package deal&#8221; that will provide for individual emotional and physical wants and needs, so long as they conform to the social and political aims of the church of the day.</p>

<p>Making the message &#8220;culturally relevant&#8221; can lead to presenting cultural idiosyncrasies along with religious doctrines until the two become confused. In one study, 10% of Americans thought that <a href="http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2007/0704.balmer.html">Noah&#8217;s wife was Joan of Arc, and two thirds thought Billy Graham preached the Sermon on the Mount</a>. The most popular &#8220;bible verse&#8221; in America the Benjamin Franklin quote is &#8220;God helps those who help themselves.&#8221; When challenged on the whether there is a any substantiation to claimed biblical backing of modern ideas, many Christians will fall back to the old line &#8220;well it ain&#8217;t in the bible, but it outta be&#8221;. Other common platitudes like &#8220;When God closes a door he opens a window&#8221; might give comfort to those struggling with flatulence, but are similarly unscriptural.</p>

<p>Unfortunately many Christians debate back and forward whether the <a href="http://www.myobamayear.com/2013/04/the-good-samaritan/">good Samaritan was a Democrat or a Republican</a>, missing the futitlity of massaging a 2000 year old religious parable into modern political doctrine. And yet this is exactly what politicians do, with to one of the best known quotes of Jesus saying &#8220;the poor you will always have among you&#8221; being frequently <a href="www.smh.com.au/opinion/bible-bashing-the-homeless-abbott-style-20100215-o2tj.html">used to oppose social justice initiatives on financial grounds</a> despite the fact the writers of the gospels place Jesus saying it in the house of <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matt26.6-13;mark14.3-9&amp;version=NET">Simon the leper</a> or with <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=jn12.1-8&amp;version=NET">Lazarus, who he raised from the dead</a>.</p>

<p>As bart ehrman states</p>

<blockquote><p>Most televangelists, popular Christian preacher icons, and heads of those corporations that we call megachurches share an unreflective modern view of Jesus – that he translates easily and almost automatically into a modern idiom. The fact is, however, that Jesus was not a person of the twenty-first century who spoke the language of contemporary Christian America (or England or Germany or anywhere else). Jesus was inescapably and ineluctably a Jew living in first-century Palestine. He was not like us, and if we make him like us we transform the historical Jesus into a creature that we have invented for ourselves and for our own purposes.</p>

<p>Jesus would not recognize himself in the preaching of most of his followers today. He knew nothing of our world. He was not a capitalist. He did not believe in free enterprise. He did not support the acquisition of wealth or the good things of life. He did not believe in massive education. He had never heard of democracy. He had nothing to do with going to church on Sunday. He knew nothing of social security, food stamps, welfare, American exceptionalism, unemployment numbers, or immigration. He had no views on tax reform, health care (apart from wanting to heal leprosy), or the welfare state. So far as we know, he expressed no opinion on the ethical issues that plague us today: abortion and reproductive rights, gay marriage, euthanasia, or bombing Iraq. His world was not ours, his concerns were not ours and – most striking of all – his beliefs were not ours.</p>

<p>Jesus was a first-century Jew, and when we try to make him into a twenty-first century American we distort everything he was and everything he stood for. Jesus himself was a complete supernaturalist. He believed in the Devil and demons and the forces of evil at work in this world. He knew little – possibly almost nothing – about the workings of the Roman Empire. But what little he knew, he considered evil. He may have considered all government evil unless it was a (future) theocracy to be run by God himself through his messiah. he certainly was no proponent of our political views, whatever our views happen to be….</p>

<p>The problem then with Jesus is that he cannot be removed from his time and transplanted into our own without simply creating him anew. When we create him anew we longer have the Jesus of history but the Jesus of our own imagination, a monstrous invention created to serve our own purposes. But Jesus is not so easily moved and changed. He is powerfully resistant. He remains always in his own time. As Jesus fads come and go, as new Jesuses come to take the place of the old, the real, historical Jesus continues to exist, back there in the past, the apocalyptic prophet who expected that a cataclysmic break would occur within his own generation when God would destroy the forces of evil, bring in his kingdom, and install Jesus himself on the throne. This is the historical Jesus. And he obviously far too historical for modern tastes. That is why so many Christians today try to reform him.</p>

<p>In my view, humanists, agnostics, atheists, mythicists, and anyone else who does not advocate belief in Jesus would be better served to stress that the Jesus of history is not the Jesus of modern Christianity than to insist – wrongly and counterproductively – that Jesus never existed. Jesus did exist. He simply was not the person that most believers today think he was.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Action bible</h3>

<p>Many bible publishers are trying to contextualise the biblical ideas into american culture. Thomas Nelson has created an <a href="http://www.thomasnelson.com/the-american-patriot-s-bible-1.html">American Patriot Bible</a> with references to American Independance thoughout the biblical text. Others seek to
<a href="http://www.sbl-site.org/publications/article.aspx?ArticleId=853">Stock car racing bible</a></p>

<div class="figure"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/leewalker28/4989621730/"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/jesuscar.jpg" link="http://www.flickr.com/photos/leewalker28/4989621730/" title="Jesus car by Lee Walker" ><p>Jesus car by Lee Walker</span></a></div>


<h3>Prosperity theology</h3>

<p>http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2013/06/19/texas-pastor-donate-to-fix-my-helicopter-and-get-a-new-car-from-god/
http://www.christianpost.com/news/televangelist-asks-followers-for-79k-to-do-paint-job-on-lords-jet-he-bought-last-year-98435/</p>

<h3>God as husband</h3>

<p>Ultimately many Christians don&#8217;t base their views of their god on the bible, viewing the bible through the lens of the culture they&#8217;re in, which is why their god&#8217;s actions and character reflect their own personal desires and perferences. When one&#8217;s understanding of the Christian God is grounded in pre-existing cultural and social assumptions, statements like this make sense:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/god-husband.jpg" alt="God as husband" /></p>

<p>This &#8220;deal&#8221; is not the gospel of Christianity, it&#8217;s a <a href="http://ajoyfulvapour.tumblr.com/post/45499852946/this-is-a-load-of-crap-where-is-its-scriptual">load of crap, and a lie, and a load of bollocks</a>. If they don&#8217;t get these stupid ideas from the bible, where do they get them from? There is a widespread cultural assumption that &#8220;everyone knows&#8221; that god wants people to marry &#8220;the one&#8221; for them. Many Christians are happy to play into cultural anxieties about love, sex and singleness to present marriage as part of the &#8220;package deal&#8221; of Christianity. Dagmar Herzog describes the American religious right as pushing a regressive social agenda by painting a rosy picture of marriage, and building on the insecurities of sexual inexperience in youth:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('CYVicYHNrAA');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CYVicYHNrAA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('CYVicYHNrAA-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CYVicYHNrAA/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CYVicYHNrAA" id="CYVicYHNrAA" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CYVicYHNrAA/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CYVicYHNrAA" id="CYVicYHNrAA-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">&#8216;Soulgasms&#8217; and the War on Masturbation</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Complete videos at: http://fora.tv/2008/11/17/Power__Sex_Americas_War_on_Sexual_Rights

Author Dagmar Herzog examines the efforts of religious conservatives to influence sexual culture in the U.S. during the Bush Administration. Herzog claims widespread increases in religion-themed sex education, therapy, and medical research as examples.

&#8212;&#8211;

Has the conservative agenda come to dominate the national and international conversation on sexual rights?

Obama&#8217;s victory and the vote against abortion bans in Colorado and South Dakota brought some sexual rights back from the edge of a political precipice, but others remain in the balance.

Join scholars, journalists, and policy makers to talk about how we can help the new administration change policies and reframe national and international thinking on sexual rights.

Participants include Dagmar Herzog, author of Sex in Crisis: The New Sexual Revolution and the Future of American Politics and Professor of History, Lynn Paltrow, Executive Director of National Advocates for Pregnant Women, Nation columnist Katha Pollitt, and Faye Wattleton, Director of the Center for the Advancement of Women.

Discussant: Rosalind Petchesky, author of Sexuality, Health and Human Rights and Distinguished Professor of Political Science. Moderated by Michelle Fine, Distinguished Professor of Psychology at the Graduate Center, CUNY - City University of New York

Dagmar Herzog is a Professor of History at the Graduate Center, CUNY, where she focuses on modern European history, the history of sexuality, and the history of the religion. She has written three books, Sex after Fascism: Memory and Morality in Twentieth-Century Germany; Intimacy and Exclusion: Religious Politics in Pre-Revolutionary Bade; and, most recently, Sex in Crisis: The New Sexual Revolution and the Future of American Politics.  In addition to her books, she has edited or co-edited four volumes and has published numerous academic articles on the history of sexuality.</div>
</div>


<p>The Materialistic Western culture is built on functional saviours. Shampoo is sold to people by telling them that unclean hair makes them undesirable, then promising to make them beautiful if they buy more product. Targetting this culture with &#8220;seeker friendly&#8221; material often means presenting a relationship Jesus as a functional saviour, a means to an end for the individual, rather than an end in and of itself. &#8220;The most important relationship you can have &#8211; one that will make you a better husband and father &#8211; is a relationship with God&#8221; reads an altar call in one <a href="http://www.everystudent.com/features/wolves.html">mendacious promise of long lasting and happy marriages</a>. Another promises &#8221;<a href="http://www.everystudent.com/features/marriage.html">hope for a lasting marriage</a>&#8221; if only one accepts Jesus. Others offer Jesus as a way for <a href="http://www.everystudent.com/wires/toxic.html">men</a> and <a href="http://www.everystudent.com/wires/jenniferm.html">women</a> to stop looking at porn. People accepting these altar calls and praying their sinner&#8217;s prayers will never know what they&#8217;ve accepted unless they read the bible to understand what is actually in it, and what &#8220;outta be&#8221;.</p>

<h3>Myths and misinformation pushing shame and intimidation</h3>

<p>The relationships altar call comes after two and a half A4 pages of bullshit about how &#8220;Waiting to have sex with my wife will mean better sex in my marriage.&#8221; It launches into all the standard canards Christians have been told to believe &#8220;the more I bond with other girls, the less I&#8217;ll be able to bond with my future wife. It&#8217;s like a piece of scotch tape &#8211; the more you use it on different surfaces, the less it sticks to things.&#8221; When entire mission strategies are built around ignorance on sex and relationships, Christians will do anything in their power to promote misinformation. Because they are offering Chrsitianity as a solution to problems of their own making.</p>

<p>Abstinance only sex education programs reinforce ignorance in 30% of United States public schools. They <a href="http://www.siecus.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Page.ViewPage&amp;PageID=1199">teach canards like</a> “Condoms can never protect someone from the emotional problems that can result from multiple sexual partners and premature sexual activity.” And “AIDS can be transmitted by skin-to-skin contact.” They discourage the responsible use of barrier methods like condoms, teaching that “The only safe sex is in a marriage relationship where a man and a woman are faithful to each other for life.”</p>

<p>These programs not only promote the idea that premarital sex has risks, but demonises it as permanantly scarring. “If [a girl] has been involved in sexual activity…sexually, she is no longer a virgin, she is no longer pure, unspoiled, fresh&#8221; they teach. They warn that “The consequences of pre-marital sex include “guilt, disappointment, worry, depression, sadness, loneliness, and loss of self-esteem.” They warn 6th grade children &#8220;Going on this ride could change your life forever, result in poverty, heartache, disease, and even DEATH.” It goes on to say that many “will board this ride and come out losers.” The manual goads “did you know that sexual activity outside of the commitment of marriage could put YOUR FUTURE at risk?”</p>

<p>If you don&#8217;t believe that they teach children that they&#8217;ll die, watch this:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('k2h6CrIOrKg');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/k2h6CrIOrKg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('k2h6CrIOrKg-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/k2h6CrIOrKg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k2h6CrIOrKg" id="k2h6CrIOrKg" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/k2h6CrIOrKg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k2h6CrIOrKg" id="k2h6CrIOrKg-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Sex Before Marriage? PREPARE TO DIE!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Kid at 1:40 just had his day ruined.</div>
</div>


<p>These teachings encourage a culture of shame and permanent condemnation. In a survey, when researchers dropped a live cockroach into orange juice, then removed the cockroach and sterilised the juice, <a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com.au/2013/02/the-psychology-of-christian-purity.html">the majority of participants wouldn&#8217;t drink it</a>. Paul Rozin, author of the study also found that <a href="http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2005-10-27/entertainment/0510260352_1_disgusting-paul-rozin-important-part">40% of participants would refuse to eat poo-shaped chocolate, or drink juice from a brand-new bedpan</a>. Even when people know that disgusting looking food is safe to eat, emotionally, many refuse. While many sins that the bible speaks against are presented as mistakes, conservative evangelicals always talk about sexual integrity in terms of purity. They encourage the view that anyone who isn&#8217;t a virgin is permanantly broken, corrupted, contaminated and that they cannot make themselves clean again.</p>

<h3>The overreach and failure of the purity doctrine</h3>

<p>Demonising pre-marital sex as permanantly scarring and unforgivable has created a culture in which people are afraid even to date. &#8220;There is no condom for the human heart&#8221; teach the fear mongers. They preach not only that virginity is the most important gift a girl can give her husband, but that they should be &#8220;emotional virgins&#8221; and not <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2011/09/love-virginity.html">&#8220;give away pieces of their heart.&#8221;</a> This is bullshit. And yet, it has almost lured a <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2012/10/what-i-learned-from-joshua-harris.html">whole generation out of dating until they are sure they can marry</a>. This hooks into the intuition that &#8220;everyone knows&#8221; that God will provide them with &#8220;the one&#8221;, which &#8220;outta be&#8221; in the bible there somewhere. Single Christian women who spend the last decade in the purity culture suddenly find themselves <a href="http://sydneyanglicans.net/life/daytoday/single_christian_female_30">ostracised and isolated as church ministries direct all their 30+ ministries to families</a>.</p>

<p>Many women have given up on wearing purity rings. For some, it&#8217;s because they <a href="http://gracefortheroad.com/2012/02/03/idontwait/">feel complete in their relationship with Jesus, and aren&#8217;t &#8220;waiting&#8221; anymore</a></p>

<blockquote><p>There are a lot of girls out there who don’t know who God is anymore – the God of their youth group years just isn’t working out. Back then, that God said to wait for sex until they are married, until He brings the right man along for a husband. They signed a card and put it on the altar and pledged to wait&#8230;</p>

<p>Some of them have prayed their whole lives for a husband, and he hasn’t shown up. They’ve heard the advice to “be the woman God made you to be, focus on that, and then the husband will come.” They’ve read “Lady in Waiting,” gotten super involved in church and honed their domestic skills.</p>

<p>More than a decade ago, a youth leader handed them a photocopied poem in Sunday School written to them from “God” that said, “The reason you don’t have anyone yet is because you’re not fully satisfied in Me. You have to be satisfied with Me and then when you least expect it, I’ll bring you the person I meant for you.”</p>

<p>&#8230;Many of them – if they’re honest – will tell you that time has passed, and it’s wrecking their view of God.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others have given up on the culture of bullying and intimidation that <a href="http://sexetc.org/info-center/post/why-i-stopped-wearing-a-purity-ring/">accompanies the purity culture</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Originally, when I made the commitment to wait until marriage, I really only saw my ring as a symbol of how personally valuable my virginity was to me. However, after I saw how readily my peers bullied and mocked girls who they thought were sexually active, my ring seemed like more of a constant reminder of how dirty and useless people might think I was if I wasn’t a virgin anymore.</p></blockquote>

<p>For some, it&#8217;s the knowledge that <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1802108/">95% of Americans have sex before marriage</a>, or that <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2768056/">Five years after taking a virginity pledge, 82% of pledgers denied having ever pledged</a>. Others note that even in Southern Baptist churches <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3156853/">70% of engaged Christians quietly have sex before marrying</a>. Many women who hit this inevitable conclusion are finding the courage to speak out about the <a href="http://www.prodigalmagazine.com/the-day-i-turned-in-my-v-card/">deep and long lasting damage of the purity culture</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> I broke a barrier and gave up an idea I’d held onto as a “Good Christian Girl” for a long, long time. If you grew up in American Christian culture, you know that a statement like mine is one of the most life changing, socially desolating, parentally disappointing pronouncements you can make. Especially if you’re a girl.</p>

<p> But I don’t care anymore; I’m done with virginity.</p>

<p> I’m done with that word and that idea. I’m done defining myself, my past and my future, in terms of who’s what has been where, or hasn’t. I’m done with stories for virgins and non-virgins, promises and praises, and sentiments of “restoration” that just push forward bulldozer loads of this horrible twisted shame.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others are speaking out for those who have <a href="http://deeperstory.com/i-am-damaged-goods/">been damaged by the notion that their sexual past is keeping them back from being a Christian</a></p>

<blockquote><p> I was nineteen years old and crazy in love with Jesus when that preacher told an auditorium I was “damaged goods” because of my sexual past. He was making every effort to encourage this crowd of young adults to “stay pure for marriage.” He was passionate, yes, well-intentioned, and he was a good speaker, very convincing indeed.</p>

<p> And he stood up there and shamed me, over and over and over again.</p>

<p> Oh, he didn’t call me up to the front and name me. But he stood up there and talked about me with such disgust, like I couldn’t be in that real-life crowd of young people worshipping in that church. I felt spotlighted and singled out amongst the holy, surely my red face announced my guilt to every one&#8230;</p>

<p> And so here, now, I’ll stand up and say it, the way I wish someone had said it to me fifteen years ago when I was sitting in that packed auditorium with my heart racing, wrists aching, eyes stinging, drowning and silenced by the imposition of shame masquerading as ashes of repentance:</p>

<p> “So, you had sex before you were married.</p>

<p> It’s okay.</p>

<p> Really. It’s okay.</p>

<p> There is no shame in Christ’s love. Let him without sin cast the first stone. You are more than your virginity – or lack thereof – and more than your sexual past.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others who kept their virginity are also <a href="http://www.elizabethesther.com/2013/01/virginity-new-improved.html">pushing back on the purity culture that teaches that non-sexual relationships are as dangerous as sexual ones</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> Yes, I was a virgin on my wedding day. Then again, I was only 20. Yes, remaining a virgin until my wedding day saved me from some romantic heartbreak. Then again, I’ve had other heartbreaks. Yes, chastity is special. Then again, so are lots of virtues. Except, as a 20 year old bride, I thought virginity was extra-extra special and would win me lots of special prizes like: a happily ever after marriage.</p>

<p> It took me a long time to realize I idolized virginity. I kept saying I was just promoting virtue and chastity and purity! Nothing wrong with pushing purity, right? Nothing wrong with Being Good!</p>

<p> Like other Christians, I talked about the “sacrifice” of abstinence. There were princess-themed books about saving our first kiss. Some of us wore purity rings and made pledges to our Daddies not to have sex until we’re married.</p>

<p> Ultimately, we implied that <strong>a woman’s inherent worth and dignity could be measured by whether or not a man has touched her</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>As women who spend their young adult years believing that pre-marital sex is &#8220;not all it&#8217;s cracked up to be&#8221; start hitting struggles in their own &#8220;perfect&#8221; marriages, the church is happy to offer a whole industry of Christian sex advice.</p>

<h3>Race to the bottom</h3>

<p>This gospel offers &#8220;perfect&#8221; sex in a &#8220;perfect&#8221; marriage so long as one accepts the &#8220;package deal&#8221; of White Jesus with the cultural vestments of looking, sounding and voting Christian.</p>

<p>Christian Delusion
http://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/the-christian-delusion-john-w-loftus/1111758093?ean=9781616141684</p>

<p>Bart Ehrman</p>

<p>Most televangelists, popular Christian preacher icons, and heads of those corporations that we call megachurches share an unreflective modern view of Jesus – that he translates easily and almost automatically into a modern idiom. The fact is, however, that Jesus was not a person of the twenty-first century who spoke the language of contemporary Christian America (or England or Germany or anywhere else). Jesus was inescapably and ineluctably a Jew living in first-century Palestine. He was not like us, and if we make him like us we transform the historical Jesus into a creature that we have invented for ourselves and for our own purposes.</p>

<p>Jesus would not recognize himself in the preaching of most of his followers today. He knew nothing of our world. He was not a capitalist. He did not believe in free enterprise. He did not support the acquisition of wealth or the good things of life. He did not believe in massive education. He had never heard of democracy. He had nothing to do with going to church on Sunday. He knew nothing of social security, food stamps, welfare, American exceptionalism, unemployment numbers, or immigration. He had no views on tax reform, health care (apart from wanting to heal leprosy), or the welfare state. So far as we know, he expressed no opinion on the ethical issues that plague us today: abortion and reproductive rights, gay marriage, euthanasia, or bombing Iraq. His world was not ours, his concerns were not ours and – most striking of all – his beliefs were not ours.</p>

<p>Jesus was a first-century Jew, and when we try to make him into a twenty-first century American we distort everything he was and everything he stood for. Jesus himself was a complete supernaturalist. He believed in the Devil and demons and the forces of evil at work in this world. He knew little – possibly almost nothing – about the workings of the Roman Empire. But what little he knew, he considered evil. He may have considered all government evil unless it was a (future) theocracy to be run by God himself through his messiah. he certainly was no proponent of our political views, whatever our views happen to be….</p>

<p>The problem then with Jesus is that he cannot be removed from his time and transplanted into our own without simply creating him anew. When we create him anew we longer have the Jesus of history but the Jesus of our own imagination, a monstrous invention created to serve our own purposes. But Jesus is not so easily moved and changed. He is powerfully resistant. He remains always in his own time. As Jesus fads come and go, as new Jesuses come to take the place of the old, the real, historical Jesus continues to exist, back there in the past, the apocalyptic prophet who expected that a cataclysmic break would occur within his own generation when God would destroy the forces of evil, bring in his kingdom, and install Jesus himself on the throne. This is the historical Jesus. And he obviously far too historical for modern tastes. That is why so many Christians today try to reform him.</p>

<p>In my view, humanists, agnostics, atheists, mythicists, and anyone else who does not advocate belief in Jesus would be better served to stress that the Jesus of history is not the Jesus of modern Christianity than to insist – wrongly and counterproductively – that Jesus never existed. Jesus did exist. He simply was not the person that most believers today think he was.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do Atheists Believe in One God Less?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/08/one-god-less/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T19:45:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/08/one-god-less</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John Dickson, founder of the Centre for Public Christianity recently <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/religion/articles/2013/07/08/3798272.htm">wrote in ABC religion and ethics</a> that he hates the atheist one-liner &#8220;There have been 10,000 gods through history, you reject 9,999 of them. I just go one god further!&#8221; He writes:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was a well-rehearsed line straight out of the atheist joke book - Dawkins likes to tell it, too. It got the laugh a witticism deserves. Simon replied laconically, &#8220;Is that meant to be an argument, Fitz?&#8221; Apparently, it was. &#8220;I&#8217;ve put this to a lot of believers over the years,&#8221; FitzSimons said with gusto, &#8220;and none of them has been able to reply.&#8221; I was surprised to hear that. So let me give it a go.</p>

<p>&#8220;Atheists just go one god further&#8221; is an aphorism regularly offered but rarely thought through. The idea it asks us to consider is something like this: when Christians reflect on why they reject Zeus, Ra, Isis, Vishnu et al., they will come to see the good sense of the atheist who simply adds one more deity to the rubbish bin. The arguments Christians employ against other gods, so the logic goes, come back to bite the Christian god as well. It is cute but silly.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Rubbish bin usually has the words &#8220;Don&#8217;t litter my mind.&#8221;</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/dickson.jpg" alt="Don't Litter my Mind" /></p>

<blockquote><p>For one thing, believers in any particular religion do not reject the other gods in toto. They deny the manifestations and stories of the other deities, but not necessarily their substance. A Christian may reject the elaborations and add-on characteristics of, say, Ra or Vishnu, but they happily acknowledge the wisdom of the ancient Egyptians and Indians in positing the existence of a powerful Intelligence which orders the universe.</p>

<p>There is, in other words, an irreducible shared conviction among most worshipers: the rational order of the universe is best explained by the existence of an almighty Mind (or Minds) behind it all. This is why the apostle Paul in Athens (Acts 17) can happily quote a line from a hymn to Zeus in his argument about God: &#8220;We are his offspring.&#8221; Paul did not think the stories about Zeus were true, but he agreed with the idea of divine power and intelligence which belief in Zeus embodied. Fitz and others are simply misguided to liken a Christian&#8217;s rejection of particular versions of divinity with the atheist&#8217;s denial of divinity altogether.</p></blockquote>

<p>Paul of Tarsus quotes Aratus and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epimenides_paradox">Epimenides the Cretan</a> in Acts 17:28 and Titus 1:12.</p>

<blockquote><p>An analogy highlights the error. In choosing to marry my wife, it is true that I rejected all other potential spouses (not that there were that many). Does this mean I have rejected the idea at the core of other people&#8217;s marriages? Of course not. But imagine a zealous celibate, who rejected marriage altogether and tried to use my own decision to marry one person as an argument against matrimony itself: &#8220;When you consider why you rejected other women in favour of her, then you will see the good sense of rejecting marriage altogether.&#8221;</p>

<p>I hardly need to point out that the difference between committed marriage and deliberate celibacy is not one of degree. Rejecting particular partners is nothing like rejecting the idea of partnership altogether. The analogy isn&#8217;t perfect but it makes one point clear: &#8220;we atheists just go one god further&#8221; is no more compelling than &#8220;we celibates just go one partner further.&#8221;</p>

<p>A believer&#8217;s denial of particular manifestations of the divine offers no support whatsoever for the atheist&#8217;s rejection of divinity itself. One-liners like this from the 101 Jokes for Atheists book should indeed be the object of laughter.</p></blockquote>

<p>The reason why people make these jokes is not because of the number of deities in the world, but how far reason and science has taken us away from the superstition that created them.</p>

<p>If you believe that Christianity is true and other religions are false, ask yourself a few questions:</p>

<p>Is the <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=josh10.10-15&amp;version=NET">book of Joshua</a> any less wrong about heliocentrism than the belief that Ra drives a chariot of fire across the sky? If Christian views on cosmology, inspired by a literal reading of the book of Joshua weren&#8217;t threatened by heliocentrism, then why did Catholic inquisitors force Galileo to recant his scientific theories and die under house arrest?</p>

<p>If Mithraism is false, why did Justin Martyr and Tertullian see a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_Christ_in_comparative_mythology">similarity between Mithraic initiation ceremonies and Christian Eucharist</a>?</p>

<p>Why does the Ancient Egyptian idea of eternal damnation in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_of_Fire">lake of fire</a> for those whose hearts are too heavy with sin predate the Chrisitan idea of salvation from eternal punishment in a lake of molten sulfur? Why do the 42 Negative Confessions of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maat">Maat</a> pre-date <a href="http://www.religioustolerance.org/chr_10cl.htm">the 10 commandments</a>? Why does Job&#8217;s <a href="http://bookofjob.org/act2.htm">Oath of Innocence</a>(Job 31) sound like a mirror immage of the negative confession?</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/maat-feather2.jpg" alt="Ancient Egyptian depiction of the weighing of a soul" /></p>

<p>If Osiris is a made up god, then why does Yahweh introduce Jesus as &#8220;This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.&#8221;(<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matt17.5&amp;version=NET">Matt 17:5</a>) when Osiris is introduced as &#8221;<a href="http://www.egyptorigins.org/osirisandjesusII.htm">I say by Nut, the brilliant, the great: This is my son, my first-born, opener of my womb; this is my beloved, with whom I am pleased</a>.&#8221;</p>

<p>If there is only one God, Yahweh, why does he insist in the first commandment, &#8221;<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=ex20&amp;version=NET">You shall have no other gods before me</a>&#8221; ? Did Judaism evolve from a polytheistic Caananite religion? Why does the Torah use the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetragrammaton">tetragrammaton</a> YHWH interchangably with the older Caananite word for the leader of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_(deity">polytheistic pantheon, El</a>)? If El is not a real god, then why do the Jewish people (Yiśrāʾ ēl, those who wrestle with god) use the same word for their god?</p>

<p>Why does Psalm 82:1 say &#8221;<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=ps82.1&amp;version=NET">God stands in the assembly of El, in the midst of the gods he renders judgment</a>&#8220;(NET bible) if the polytheistic El (with his divine assembly) is made up?</p>

<p>One of the most important figures int he Old Testament, Moses, appears to have much in common with the myths of other deities. His story of being put in an ark of bullrushes (same hebrew word as Noah&#8217;s ark) is <a href="http://www.sacred-texts.com/neu/mbh/index.htm">similar to the stories of heroes</a> like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sargon_of_Akkad">Sargon of Akkad</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karna">Karna</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyrus_the_Great">Cyrus</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romulus_and_Remus">Romulus</a></p>

<p>Was the miracle of Moses dividing the waters of the Sea of Reeds inspired by Egyptian stories of magic. The fictional magician <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djadjaemankh">Djadjaemankh</a> was rumoured to be able to fold a body of water in half. The story starts with the pharaoh <a href="http://www.thekeep.org/~kunoichi/kunoichi/themestream/egypt_magic.html">Snefru being bored</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;&#8230;His majesty said to him: [&#8216;I have gone through all the rooms] of the palace in search of relaxation and found none.&#8217; Djadjaemankh said to him: &#8216;May your majesty proceed to the lake of the palace. Fill a boat with all the beautiful girls of your palace. Your majesty&#8217;s heart will be refreshed by seeing them row, a rowing up and down. As you observe the fine nesting places of your lake, as you observe its beautiful fields and shores, your heart will be refreshed by it.&#8217;</p>

<p>&#8220;Said his majesty: &#8216;Indeed, I shall go boating! Let there be brought to me twenty oars of ebony plated with gold, their handles of sandalwood plated with electrum. Let there be brought to me twenty women with the shapeliest bodies, breasts, and braids, who have not yet given birth. Also let there be brought to me twenty nets and give these nets to these women in place of their clothes!&#8217; All was done as his majesty commanded.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Wanting a beautiful maiden brought to him also has some parallels with King David, but that could just be that it makes sense to cast ancient kings as creeps. While the king is making his heart glad perving on the beautiful virgins, they stop:</p>

<blockquote><p>And so they row to and fro and Sneferu&#8217;s heart is gladdened when he sees the girls row. Then it happens that the stroke maiden goes through her braids with her fingers and a hair pendant in the shape of a fish, made of malachite, falls into the water of the lake. The stroke maiden becomes silent in shock and grief and stops specifying the clock. Her complete line of rowers becomes silent, too, and they all stop rowing.</p></blockquote>

<p>Snefru wants to make the stroke maiden happy and offers her a new fish pendant, but she refuses, demanding the recovery of the original. The story goes on with magic division of the lake:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Djadjaemankh utters a secret spell which makes the waters of the lake move, so that one half side of the lake now rests on the other half. The water which had been 12 cubits in height becomes now 24 cubits at one side, whilst the other side is dry now. Djadjaemankh enters the lake&#8217;s ground and picks up the lost fish-pendant, which was lying on a pot-shard. He brings the amulet back to the stroke maiden and then removes the waters magically back to their original positions.</p></blockquote>

<p>Does this sound at all like Moses dividing water with magic powers, walking on dry ground, and then letting the water flow back again? The birth story of Moses being protected in an ark of bullrushes has similarities to the birth narrative of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sargon_of_Akkad">Sargon</a>.</p>

<p>The burden of proof on Christian believers is not just to prove that their deity exists, but also that the claims they make about their god are substantially different to older polytheistic deities now dismissed as unscientific myths.</p>

<p>Aron Ra gives further examples of the myths similar to the Torah myths:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('FLviKiEuj30');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/FLviKiEuj30&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('FLviKiEuj30-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/FLviKiEuj30/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLviKiEuj30" id="FLviKiEuj30" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/FLviKiEuj30/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLviKiEuj30" id="FLviKiEuj30-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">the Evolution of Genesis</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >This is my lecture on the origins of Biblical fables, presented for the Secular Student Alliance in the University of North Texas at Denton on 2013/04/11. I was running late. It was a crowded classroom, and there was no time or available outlets to set the camera up any better, but at least you should be able to hear what is being said.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Church Teaching Against Women from St. Augustine to Pat Robertson]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/06/biblical-mysoginy/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-06T14:52:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/06/biblical-mysoginy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whether it&#8217;s saying that it&#8217;s God&#8217;s will that women get pregnant from rape, or that women can&#8217;t get pregnant from &#8221;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rape_and_pregnancy_controversies_in_United_States_elections,_2012">legitimate rape</a>&#8221; because women can &#8220;shut that whole thing down&#8221;, Republican senators seem to be living on another planet when they talk about women. One street preacher, proud to be a virgin, declares that women at a Take Back The Night march on <a href="http://www.digitaljournal.com/article/348898">his campus deserve to be raped</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/deserve-rape.jpg" alt="You Deserve Rape sign" /></p>

<p>While his pro rape trolling is crazy by modern standards, it&#8217;s sadly not far outside Christian tradition for much of the last 2000 years.
Dr Valerie Tarico has compiled a list of <a href="http://awaypoint.wordpress.com/2013/07/01/mysogynistquoteschurchfathers/">vile quotes from church fathers thoughout history teaching their flock to hate women</a></p>

<blockquote><p>What with diatribes about entertainers who <a href="http://www.leftfootforward.org/2013/06/daily-mail-columnist-says-rihannas-fashion-sense-invites-rape/">invite rape</a>
and moms who are <a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/psysociety/2013/06/03/fox-news-fact-check-is-it-bad-for-lower-income-kids-if-mom-has-a-job-outside-the-home/">destroying America</a>
by supporting their families &#8230; with ignorant arguments about
<a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/xx_factor/2013/06/18/rep_mike_burgess_of_texas_suggests_banning_abortion_because_fetuses_masturbate.html">fetuses that masturbate</a>,
and females who might as well <a href="http://www.lifesitenews.com/news/contracepting-america-the-real-war-on-women">if they use contraception</a>,
and fetal personhood that trumps the personhood of females &#8230; . it’s
tempting to think that Christian conservatives, have reached some new
pinnacle of hating women and sexuality. But the sad reality is that even
the media’s most unabashed misogynists like Michelle Bachman, Michael
Burgess, Lou Dobbs or Juan Williams are actually tame compared to their
ideological ancestors, which include some of the biggest names in
Christian history.</p>

<p>In past centuries, men who were hailed as Church Fathers, Patriarchs,
Doctors, and even Saints boldly expressed their view that females are
inferior and loathsome; and they explained at length why God shared
their perspective. Lest we fall into the <em>conservative</em> trap of thinking
that the past was somehow better than the nasty messes we face today,
it’s worth pondering some of the lovely tidbits that the Church has
thought fit to preserve and promote in the centuries since Christianity
was founded. Here are some of the most savory. They come from three
waves of religious leaders: “Fathers” of the Catholic Church, Protestant
Reformers, and American patriarchs who inherited the mantle of both.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Church Doctors and Fathers</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Woman is a temple built over a sewer.
<strong>–</strong><em>Tertullian, “the father of Latin Christianity” (c160-225)</em></p></li>
<li><p>In pain shall you bring forth children, woman, and you shall turn to
your husband and he shall rule over you. And do you not know that
you are Eve? God’s sentence hangs still over all your sex and His
punishment weighs down upon you. You are the devil’s gateway; you
are she who first violated the forbidden tree and broke the law of
God. It was you who coaxed your way around him whom the devil had
not the force to attack. With what ease you shattered that image of
God: Man! Because of the death you merited, even the Son of God had
to die… <strong>Woman, you are the gate to hell</strong>.
<strong>–</strong><em>Tertullian, “the father of Latin Christianity” (c160-225)</em></p></li>
<li><p>[Women&#8217;s] very consciousness of their own nature must evoke feelings
of shame.–<em>Saint Clement of Alexandria, Christian theologian (c150-215) Pedagogues II, 33, 2</em></p></li>
<li><p>Nor are the women to smear their faces with the ensnaring devices of
wily cunning&#8230; The Instructor [Christ] orders them to go forth
“in becoming apparel, and adorn themselves with shamefacedness and
sobriety, subject to their own husbands.”
–<em>Saint Clement of Alexandria, Christian theologian (c150-215), <a href="http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/clement-instructor-book3.html">The Instructor</a></em></p></li>
<li><p>For it is improper for a woman to speak in an assembly, no matter
what she says,
even if she says admirable things, or even saintly things, that is
of little
consequence, since they come from the mouth of a woman.
<em><strong>–</strong>Origen (d. 258), </em>Fragments on First Corinthians<em>, 74</em></p></li>
<li><p>Woman does not possess the image of God in herself but only when
taken together
 with the male who is her head, so that the whole substance is one
image. But
 when she is assigned the role as helpmate, a function that pertains
to her
 alone, then she is not the image of God. But as far as the man is
concerned, he
 is by himself alone the image of God just as fully and completely
as when he and
 the woman are joined together into one. –<em>Saint Augustine, Bishop
of Hippo Regius (354-430)</em></p></li>
<li><p>What is the difference whether it is in a wife or a mother, it is
still Eve the temptress that we must beware of in any woman… I fail
to see what use woman can be to man, if one excludes the function of
bearing children. <em>–Saint Augustine, Bishop of Hippo Regius (354 –
430)</em></p></li>
<li><p>To embrace a woman is to embrace a sack of manure. - Odo of Cluny stated</p></li>
<li><p>Woman is a misbegotten man and has a faulty and defective nature in
comparison to his. Therefore she is unsure in herself. What she
cannot get, she seeks to obtain through lying and diabolical
deceptions. And so, to put it briefly, one must be on one’s guard
with every woman, as if she were a poisonous snake and the horned
devil. … Thus in evil and perverse doings woman is cleverer, that
is, slyer, than man. Her feelings drive woman toward every evil,
just as reason impels man toward all good. <em>–Saint Albertus Magnus,
Dominican theologian, 13th century</em></p></li>
<li><p>As regards the individual nature, woman is defective and
misbegotten, for the active force in the male seed tends to the
production of a perfect likeness in the masculine sex; while the
production of woman comes from a defect in the active force or from
some material indisposition, or even from some external influence.
<em>–Thomas Aquinas, Doctor of the Church, 13th century, Summa Theologica</em></p></li>
<li><p>All witchcraft comes from carnal lust, which is in women insatiable. - <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malleus_Maleficarum">Malleus Maleficarum</a>, 1486</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Protestant Reformers</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>The word and works of God is quite clear, that women were made
either to be wives or prostitutes. –<em>Martin Luther, Works 12.94</em></p></li>
<li><p>Men have broad and large chests, and small narrow hips, and more
understanding than women, who have but small and narrow breasts, and
broad hips, to the end they should remain at home, sit still, keep
house, and bear and bring up children. –<em>Martin Luther, Table Talk</em></p></li>
<li><p>No gown worse becomes a woman than the desire to be wise. -<em>Martin Luther</em></p></li>
<li><p>Even though they grow weary and wear themselves out with child-bearing, it does not matter; let them go on bearing children till they die, that is what they are there for. <em>Martin Luther, Works 20.84</em></p></li>
<li><p>God created Adam master and lord of living creatures, but Eve spoilt all, when she persuaded him to set himself above God&#8217;s will. &#8216;Tis you women, with your tricks and artifices, that lead men into error. -<em>Martin Luther</em></p></li>
<li><p>We may well lie with what seems to be a woman of flesh and blood, and yet all the time it is only a devil in the shape of a woman. -<em>Martin Luther</em></p></li>
<li><p>“If a woman grows weary and at last dies from childbearing, it matters not. Let her only die from bearing; she is there to do it.” —<em>Martin Luther</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thus the woman, who had perversely exceeded her proper bounds, is
forced back to her own position. She had, indeed, previously been
subject to her husband, but that was a liberal and gentle
subjection; now, however, she is cast into servitude.<strong>–</strong><em>John
Calvin, Reformer (1509-1564), Commentary on Genesis, p. 172.</em></p></li>
<li><p>Do not any longer contend for mastery, for power, money, or praise.
Be content to be a private, insignificant person, known and loved by
God and me&#8230; . of what importance is your character to mankind,
if you was buried just now Or if you had never lived, what loss
would it be to the cause of God.<strong>–</strong><em>John Wesley, founder of
Methodist movement (1703-1791), <a href="http://wesley.nnu.edu/john-wesley/the-letters-of-john-wesley/wesleys-letters-1774/">letter to his wife</a>,
July 15, 1774</em></p></li>
</ul>


<h3>American Patriarchs (Puritan, Mormon, Baptist, Evangelical)</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Even as the church must fear Christ Jesus, so must the wives also
fear their husbands. And this inward fear must be shewed by an
outward meekness and lowliness in her speeches and carriage to her
husband&#8230; . For if there be not fear and reverence in the
inferior, there can be no sound nor constant honor yielded to the
superior. –<em>John Dod, A Plaine and Familiar Exposition of the Ten
Commandements</em>, <em>Puritan guidebook first published in 1603</em>**</p></li>
<li><p>The second duty of the wife is constant obedience and subjection.
–<em>John Dod, A Plaine and Familiar Exposition of the Ten
Commandements</em>, <em>Puritan guidebook first published in 1603</em>**</p></li>
<li><p>The root of masculine is stronger, and of feminine weaker. The sun
is a governing planet to certain planets, while the moon borrows her
light from the sun, and is less or weaker. <em>–Joseph Smith, founder
of LDS movement (1805-1844), History of the Church, V, p. 211</em></p></li>
<li><p>Women are made to be led, and counseled, and directed&#8230; . And if
I am not a good man, I have no just right in this Church to a wife
or wives, or the power to propagate my species. What then should be
done with me? Make a eunuch of me, and stop my propagation. <em>–Heber
C. Kimball, venerated early LDS apostle (1801-1868), JD 5:29</em></p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Modern mysogninists</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>A wife is to submit graciously to the servant leadership of her
husband, even as the church willingly submits to the headship of
Christ. <em>–Official Faith and Message Statement of Southern Baptist
Convention, Summer 1998, (15.7 million members)</em></p></li>
<li><p>The feminist agenda is not about equal rights for women. It is about
a socialist, anti-family political movement that encourages women to
leave their husbands, kill their children, practice witchcraft,
destroy capitalism and become lesbians. — <em>Pat Robertson, Southern
Baptist leader (1930-), <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/08/26/us/robertson-letter-attacks-feminists.html">fundraising
letter</a>
July 1992</em></p></li>
<li><p>The Holiness of God is not evidenced in women when they are brash,
brassy, boisterous, brazen, head-strong, strong-willed,
loud-mouthed, overly-talkative, having to have the last word,
challenging, controlling, manipulative, critical, conceited,
arrogant, aggressive, assertive, strident, interruptive,
undisciplined, insubordinate, disruptive, dominating, domineering,
or clamoring for power. Rather, women accept God’s holy order and
character by being humbly and unobtrusively respectful and receptive
in functional subordination to God, church leadership, and husbands.
<em>–James Fowler, Women in the Church, 1999</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Women will be saved by going back to that role that God has chosen
for them. Ladies, if the hair on the back of your neck stands up it
is because you are fighting your role in the scripture. <em>–<a href="http://community.feministing.com/2010/06/23/mark-driscoll-misogyny-and-masculinity/">Mark Driscoll</a>,
founder of Mars Hill nondenominational mega-church franchise.
(1970-), <a href="http://lineout.thestranger.com/2008/04/everclear_to_play_mars_hill_church">sermon 2008</a></em></p></li>
</ul>


<p>Michael and Debi Pearl are advocates of extreme physical discipline and female submission. Their book to train up a child encourages physical violence against childen as young as 6 months to &#8220;break their spirit.&#8221; Michael advocates that fathers have fun disciplining hitting their children:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('R12CVm9WvNE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/R12CVm9WvNE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('R12CVm9WvNE-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/R12CVm9WvNE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R12CVm9WvNE" id="R12CVm9WvNE" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/R12CVm9WvNE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R12CVm9WvNE" id="R12CVm9WvNE-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Christain love and censorship from child abuser Michael Pearl.</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >A video about a child abusing neanderthal, I cut out the speech to jump right to the action. Make sure you watch the original as themudbrooker has said more then anyone else could about this man&#8217;s blatant disregard for copyright law. This man&#8217;s books have lead to the beating deaths of children, lets show this clown the internet doesn&#8217;t accept his shit.

The original video:
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GNv61rb7TNc


TheMudbrooker&#8217;s Channel
http://www.youtube.com/user/TheMudbrooker

Everything is terrible. Check it out it has hilarious content.
http://www.everythingisterrible.com/


17 U.S.C. § 107

Notwithstanding the provisions of sections 17 U.S.C. § 106 and 17 U.S.C. § 106A, the fair use of a copyrighted work, including such use by reproduction in copies or phonorecords or by any other means specified by that section, for purposes such as criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, This falls under this act, I will send counter claims.</div>
</div>


<p>Debi Pearl has published a long exposition of her Christian version of Stockholm Syndrome called <a href="http://eaandfaith.blogspot.com.au/2008/04/debi-pearls-created-to-be-helpmate.html">Created to be his helpmeet</a>. It encourages women in abusive relationships to submit to violent partners:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Page 263: “Lady, you were created to give glory to God. When God puts you in
subjection to a man whom he knows is going to cause you to suffer, it is with
the understanding that <strong>you are obeying God by enduring the wrongful suffering</strong>.
And when you suffer wrongfully, as unto the Lord, you bring great glory to God
in heaven.”</p></li>
<li><p>Page 263: “Has your husband reviled and threatened you? You are exhorted to respond as Jesus did. When he was reviled and threatened, he suffered by
committing himself to a higher judge who is righteous. You must commit yourself
to the one who placed you under your husband’s command. Your husband will answer
to God, and you must answer to God for how you respond to your husband, even
when he causes you to suffer.”</p></li>
<li><p>Page 264: “You can freely call your husband “lord” when you know that you are addressing the one who put him in charge and asked you to suffer at your
husband’s hands just as our Lord suffered at the hands of unjust authorities… I
know that this must be an amazing doctrine to many of you. Nonetheless, it is no
less radical than Jesus was radical, and it is God’s way.”</p></li>
<li><p>Page 265: “For the eyes of the Lord see all that take place. His ears are open to your prayers when you obey him and obey your husband. And then comes the
promise: if you are following God, no harm will come to you by doing what is
good… You will receive a blessing when you suffer for righteousness’ sake, that
is, when you obey God by obeying your husband and not returning evil for evil.
You will be happy, so don’t be afraid or troubled by the things you must
endure.”</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Dr Tarico concludes:</p>

<blockquote><p>Why has the main current of Christianity produced a steady diet of
misogyny for over 2000 years? The answer may lay partly in human biology
and culture. But it also lies in the Iron Age texts of the Bible itself.
The Judeo-Christian tradition of building up men by tearing down women
goes all the way back to the most ancient parts of the biblical
collection, to the opening pages of Genesis, and continues unabated
through the New Testament. (I’ve written elsewhere about <a href="http://awaypoint.wordpress.com/2012/03/09/15-bible-texts-reveal-why-gods-own-party-is-at-war-with-women/">15 of those Bible verses</a>
because they partly explain the conservative assault on women.) As Mr.
Driscoll <a href="http://lineout.thestranger.com/2008/04/everclear_to_play_mars_hill_church">likes to</a>
remind his followers, “Every single book in your Bible is written by a
man.”</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You can heal cancer naturally with coffee enemas, but only if they're organic]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/24/coffee-enema/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-24T21:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/24/coffee-enema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No, wait, you can&#8217;t. Jessica Ainscough, a self proclaimed &#8220;wellness warrior&#8221; has recently complained that she felt &#8220;dirty&#8221; after eating a vegan burger that wasn&#8217;t 100% organic. The burger was billed by the not-for-profit vegetarian cafe as &#8220;cancer fighting rather than cancer causing.&#8221; Ainscough later rang the cafe to check up on some of their claims, but not whether any of the claimed miraculous healing properties had any empirical basis, but rather if their food was 100% organic. The revelation that her burger and juice weren&#8217;t purely organic made her feel like such a dirty, dirty woman that <a href="http://www.thewellnesswarrior.com.au/2013/06/beware-of-organic-cafes-that-lie-to-us/">she needed detoxifying</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>I felt dirty. <strong>I felt like I needed to give my insides about 10 showers</strong>. I was so shocked that I just hung up the phone, but I wish I’d told her that her since her “cancer fighting” burger contains pesticides it is actually cancer causing.</p></blockquote>

<p>Emphasis hers. The poor woman is very slowly dying of a rare type of cancer, epithelioid sarcoma, which tends to show up in young patients. Unfortunately, with no paletable treatment options available, the woman has chosen to believe in the claimed &#8220;natural healing power&#8221; of miracle diets to avoid acknowledging her fate. The yellow journalism of the Daily Tele <a href="http://www.news.com.au/entertainment/restaurants-bars/jess-ainscough-claims-8216organic8217-cafe-misled-with-veggie-burger/story-fn93ypt9-1226668814935">repeats this bunk untramelled</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The holistic health coach, who was in Byron Bay last week, follows a strict organic diet after overcoming cancer without using modern medicine.</p></blockquote>

<p>She follows <a href="http://skepdic.com/gersontherapy.html">Gerson Therapy</a>, a debunked therapy that claims to be able to cure cancer by following a diet and &#8220;cleansing&#8221; unknown &#8220;toxins&#8221; from the body by coffee enemas. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerson_therapy#Gerson_Therapy">diet and enemas</a> are not proven to be effective in any <a href="http://www.cancer.org/treatment/treatmentsandsideeffects/complementaryandalternativemedicine/dietandnutrition/gerson-therapy">large scale peer reviewed studies</a>, and coffee enemas have been linked to the <a href="http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/pdq/cam/gerson/patient/Page2#Section_28">deaths of three people in the US</a>. Most notably, the advocates of these therapies often take over $10,000 a time from dying patients, telling them to <a href="https://www.google.com.au/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CCoQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.theaustralian.com.au%2Fnews%2Ffeatures%2Fholding-out-for-a-miracle%2Fstory-e6frg8h6-1226476739168&amp;ei=p00KUoqiLMnwlAXdhIDwCg&amp;usg=AFQjCNHKviBCjXOnTlzqfpGUgo78qY3pOA&amp;sig2=MDGCuS_q5Zjj4x_uM45gKg&amp;bvm=bv.50500085,d.dGI">give up conventional treatments and pain medication</a> while they die. They are part of a growing number of natropaths encouraging people to die without conventional medicine, and they have a growing number of adherants:</p>

<blockquote><p>Last year Perth mother-of-four Gemma Bond staged her own public renunciation of conventional medicine after being diagnosed with ovarian and uterine cancer. After agreeing to a hysterectomy on her doctor&#8217;s recommendation, Bond declined all further treatment in favour of a regime of coffee enemas, ozone therapy, intravenous vitamins and supplements</p></blockquote>

<p>Last year there was an investigation by the West Australian government into the deaths of 20 cancer patients.</p>

<blockquote><p>Evelyn Vicker details how roughly 20 terminal cancer patients paid as much as $40,000 each to be subjected to an experimental treatment advertised on the internet and administered in Darwin and Perth in 2004-05. All of them were told to abandon conventional medical treatment, including painkillers; all were seduced by a claimed 95 per cent success rate; all of them died, many in agony.</p></blockquote>

<p>The coroner&#8217;s report recommended criminal proceedings against the doctor that <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-07-04/coroner-finds-against-alternative-cancer-therapy/4110182">promoted the therapy</a>, that include DMSO. The industrial solvent dimethyl sulfoxide is commonly claimed to be a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimethyl_sulfoxide">fake cancer cure</a>. The 281 page coroner&#8217;s report is <a href="http://www.safetyandquality.health.wa.gov.au/docs/mortality_review/inquest_finding/Operation_Lantana_finding.pdf">available online</a>, detailing how the patients died:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sartori lacked clinical skills and was unable to provide proper medical care while the treatment was occurring. Patients are at risk of suffering serious harm or dying due to the questionable clinical care received under his instruction. Those promoting the treatment claim it is “natural” and “safe”. Sartori’s form of this treatment is neither. It requires high doses of industrially manufactured substances and is manifestly unsafe, as are a number of other purportedly ‘natural’ products.</p></blockquote>

<p>Ainscough describes how her <a href="http://dolly.ninemsn.com.au/girltalk/realityreads/8399381/im-healing-myself-from-cancer-naturally">treatment supposedly works</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>This research led me to Gerson Therapy which ensures you have a perfectly balanced diet for optimum health, assisting your body to flush out nasties whilst feeding it with all the goodness it needs to flourish.</p>

<p>The therapy involves drinking 13 fresh organic veggie juices per day (yes that’s one an hour, every hour of my waking day), five coffee enemas per day and a basic organic whole food plant-based diet with additional supplements.</p></blockquote>

<p>There aren&#8217;t many jobs in which someone could have five or <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Health/florida-couple-addicted-coffee-enemas/story?id=18433235#.UchQKUE-cT8">more coffee enemas a day</a>. And while drinking juices may not be harmful, there is <a href="http://skepdic.com/gersontherapy.html">no evidence that the treatment works in the ways it says it does</a>, but is unfortunately continuing to exploit desperate people.</p>

<p>She goes on to invent &#8221;<a href="http://www.thewellnesswarrior.com.au/2013/06/how-your-thoughts-can-help-clean-up-the-planet/">psychic pollution</a>&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><p>Did you know that pollution on our planet is not only caused by greenhouse gases, littering and chemical waste but also by our negative thoughts?
Yes, you did read that last sentence correctly; our negative thoughts also contribute to pollution on our planet. This is called ‘psychic pollution.’
This fact has been proven: what we think and feel has a direct impact on the world around us.</p></blockquote>

<p>[Citation needed]</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('HhGuXCuDb1U');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HhGuXCuDb1U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('HhGuXCuDb1U-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/HhGuXCuDb1U/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HhGuXCuDb1U" id="HhGuXCuDb1U" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/HhGuXCuDb1U/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HhGuXCuDb1U" id="HhGuXCuDb1U-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Tim Minchin&#8217;s Storm the Animated Movie</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >In the confines of a London dinner party, comedian Tim Minchin argues with a hippy named Storm. While Storm herself may not be converted, audiences from London to LA have been won over by Tim&#8217;s wordplay and the timely message of the film in a society where science and reason are portrayed as the enemy of belief.

Written and performed by Tim Minchin @timminchin. Directed by DC Turner @dcturner. Produced by Tracy King @tkingdoll. www.stormmovie.net

Italian subtitles by www.comedysubs.org
English subtitles by Jason Livingston
Russian subtitles by Denis Olshin</div>
</div>


<p>If you want to see Ainscough talk about putting a tube in her butt, she describes the process <a href="http://healthtalkstv.com/detoxification/jess-ainscough-the-coffee-enema/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[when-culture-wars-kill]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/20/when-culture-wars-kill/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T10:51:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/20/when-culture-wars-kill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>http://www.exgaywatch.com/2013/06/is-the-end-of-exodus-near/
http://www.exgaywatch.com/2013/06/hardliners-pre-emptively-spin-expose-of-survivors-of-ex-gay-abuse/</p>

<p>http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry/
http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2013/06/35755/
http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2013/06/35664/</p>

<p>http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2013/06/35751/</p>

<p>http://www.exgaywatch.com/2011/07/exodus-says-ex-gay-boot-camps-dont-exist-survivors-say-otherwise/</p>

<p>http://www.theage.com.au/victoria/when-faith-and-sexuality-collide-20130413-2hskc.html#
&#8220;I know of a church where one of the pastors recommended to a guy that he go and see a female prostitute because he couldn&#8217;t comprehend that this guy could not be attracted to or enjoy sex with a woman&#8221;</p>

<p>Chambers
http://www.boxturtlebulletin.com/2010/03/04/20825“the majority of people that I have met, and I would say the majority meaning 99.9% of them, have not experienced a change in their orientation or have gotten to a place where they could say that they could never be tempted or are not tempted in some way or experience some level of same-sex attraction.”</p>

<p>In advance of the Exodus Freedom Conference in Irvine, California, and of
the airing of Lisa Ling’s <em>Our America</em> tomorrow night, in which he is
confronted by “ex-gay” survivors, Alan Chambers <a href="http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry/">has issued a long
apology</a> to the
LGBTQ community on Exodus’s website. While much more work obviously
remains to be done to make sure that Exodus is truly serious about never
again destroying the lives and families of LGBTQ people in the name of
faith, the apology is striking in that there is little to no
equivocation. I’m going to excerpt most of it, bolding parts that I feel
important, and we will have more commentary on this in the coming days:</p>

<blockquote><p>Recently, I have begun thinking again about how to apologize to the
people that have been hurt by Exodus International through an
experience or by a message. I have heard many firsthand stories from
people called ex-gay survivors. Stories of people who went to Exodus
affiliated ministries or ministers for help only to experience more
trauma. I have heard stories of shame, sexual misconduct, and false
hope. In every case that has been brought to my attention, there has
been swift action resulting in the removal of these leaders and/or
their organizations. But rarely was there an apology or a public
acknowledgement by me.</p>

<p>And then there is the trauma that I have caused. <strong>There were several
years that I conveniently omitted my ongoing same-sex attractions.</strong> I
was afraid to share them as readily and easily as I do today. They
brought me tremendous shame and I hid them in the hopes they would go
away. <strong>Looking back, it seems so odd that I thought I could do
something to make them stop. Today, however, I accept these feelings
as parts of my life that will likely always be there.</strong> The days of
feeling shame over being human in that way are long over, and I feel
free simply accepting myself as my wife and family does. As my friends
do. As God does.</p>

<p>Never in a million years would I intentionally hurt another person.
<strong>Yet, here I sit having hurt so many by failing to acknowledge the
pain some affiliated with Exodus International caused, and by failing
to share the whole truth about my own story. My good intentions matter
very little and fail to diminish the pain and hurt others have
experienced on my watch.</strong> The good that we have done at Exodus is
overshadowed by all of this.</p>

<p>Friends and critics alike have said it’s not enough to simply change
our message or website. I agree. I cannot simply move on and pretend
that I have always been the friend that I long to be today. <strong>I
understand why I am distrusted and why Exodus is hated.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Please know that I am deeply sorry. I am sorry for the pain and hurt
many of you have experienced. I am sorry that some of you spent years
working through the shame and guilt you felt when your attractions
didn’t change. I am sorry we promoted sexual orientation change
efforts and reparative theories about sexual orientation that
stigmatized parents. I am sorry that there were times I didn’t stand
up to people publicly “on my side” who called you names like
sodomite—or worse. I am sorry that I, knowing some of you so well,
failed to share publicly that the gay and lesbian people I know were
every bit as capable of being amazing parents as the straight people
that I know. I am sorry that when I celebrated a person coming to
Christ and surrendering their sexuality to Him that I callously
celebrated the end of relationships that broke your heart. I am sorry
that I have communicated that you and your families are less than me
and mine.</strong></p>

<p>More than anything, I am sorry that so many have interpreted this
religious rejection by Christians as God’s rejection. I am profoundly
sorry that many have walked away from their faith and that some have
chosen to end their lives. For the rest of my life I will proclaim
nothing but the whole truth of the Gospel, one of grace, mercy and
open invitation to all to enter into an inseverable relationship with
almighty God.</p>

<p>I cannot apologize for my deeply held biblical beliefs about the
boundaries I see in scripture surrounding sex, but I will exercise my
beliefs with great care and respect for those who do not share them. I
cannot apologize for my beliefs about marriage. <strong>But I do not have
any desire to fight you on your beliefs or the rights that you seek.
My beliefs about these things will never again interfere with God’s
command to love my neighbor as I love myself.</strong></p>

<p><strong>You have never been my enemy. I am very sorry that I have been
yours.</strong> I hope the changes in my own life, as well as the ones we
announce tonight regarding Exodus International, will bring
resolution, and show that I am serious in both my regret and my offer
of friendship. I pledge that future endeavors will be focused on peace
and common good.</p>

<p>Moving forward, we will serve in our pluralistic culture by hosting
thoughtful and safe conversations about gender and sexuality, while
partnering with others to reduce fear, inspire hope, and cultivate
human flourishing.</p></blockquote>

<p>Words are words, but words matter in that they are a start. We anxiously
await the announcements regarding Exodus’s future that Alan mentioned,
and we hope that Exodus’s “future” is that there won’t be one. That
would seem to be the only surefire way to stop the bleeding.</p>

<p>Lisa Ling’s special on Exodus airs tomorrow night at 10 EDT on the OWN
network.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are You a Racist?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/12/are-you-a-racist/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T11:08:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/12/are-you-a-racist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A team of Harvard psychologists recently completed a study showing a correlation between religious belief and performance on the well-known Cognitive Reflection Test The CRT goes like this; consider these simple maths quesions:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>A bat and a ball cost $1.10 in total.  The bat costs $1.00 more than the ball.  How much does the ball cost?</li>
<li>If it takes five machines five minutes to make five widgets, how long does it take 100 machines to make 100 widgets?</li>
<li>In a lake, there is a patch of lily pads.  Every day, the patch doubles in size.  If it takes 48 days for the patch to cover the entire lake, how long would it take for the patch to cover half of the lake?</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>You may have confidence in your answers. The answers are below these optical illusions, that show how you interpret the world may be mistaken:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/illusion-Zollner.png" alt="Zollner Illusion" /></p>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z%C3%B6llner_illusion">Zöllner illusion</a> demonstrates that while lines actually run in parallel, they look wonky when a pattern makes you believe that they aren&#8217;t straight.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/illusion-pisa789.jpg" alt="Double Leaning Tower of Pisa Illusion" /></p>

<p>Both of these images are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leaning_tower_illusion">exactly the same</a>. Try covering one of them with your hand. When you see both images along side each other, your mind automatically assumes that the one on the right must come from a different angle.</p>

<p><strong>Answers</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>You would expect the ball to cost $0.10 if the bat cost $1.00, but the bat costs $1.00 <em>more</em> than the ball, giving the correct answer of <strong>$0.05</strong></li>
<li>While the intuitive answer is 100 minutes, it takes five machines five minutes to produce one widget each, so it takes 100 machines five minutes to produce one widget each (100 widgets).</li>
<li>The intuitive answer is half the days (24), the correct answer is 47 (because the patch doubles each day).</li>
</ol>


<p>These aren&#8217;t difficult questions, but many people get the answers wrong when they don&#8217;t think the problem though methodically, relying on intuition instead of slow, methodical, rational thought. More religious people <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/matthew-hutson/what-kind-of-thinker-beli_b_2759701.html">tend to get more of the answers wrong</a>, trusting their intuition more than less religious participants.</p>

<p>David Hume said &#8220;reason is the slave of the passions&#8221; and modern neuroscience backs the claim up.
Daniel Kahneman has noted differences in the way that people <a href="http://edge.org/conversation/the-marvels-and-flaws-of-intuitive-thinking">process information quickly and intuitively, compared to how they think slowly and methodically</a>.</p>

<p>In 2008 Transport for London received international recognition on the Gruen Transfer for this ad about recognition of cyclists:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('Ahg6qcgoay4');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ahg6qcgoay4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('Ahg6qcgoay4-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Ahg6qcgoay4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ahg6qcgoay4" id="Ahg6qcgoay4" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Ahg6qcgoay4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ahg6qcgoay4" id="Ahg6qcgoay4-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Test Your Awareness: Do The Test</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >How many passes does the team in white make? Test your awareness and Do the Test! TFL cycling safetly advert! Count the number of passes the White team makes. Do you see the Moonwalking bear?</div>
</div>


<p>Very often we can fail to spot things that we&#8217;re not looking out for. Today <em>Scientific American</em> published an article on selective attention, where people can fail to notice the things &#8221;<a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=your-hidden-censor-what-your-mind-will-not-let-you-see&amp;page=1">your mind will not let you see</a>.&#8221; In one study white women were asked to concentrate on a ball-tossing video, then asked if they noticed a black man or a white man in the middle. One group primed on a task aimed at finding a &#8220;a suitable neighbor or co-worker&#8221; were equally likely to see both men. Another group primed on looking for a friend or date noticed the white man more than twice as often as the black man.</p>

<p>Many societies that have multicultural workplaces don&#8217;t have as many mixed ethnicity marriages, meaning that many people may be more subconsiously accustomed to seeing people of other races in a distant setting but not as accustomed to them being friends or family. In several studies where participants <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/108/13/E46.full">were given a shot of oxytocin</a>, the participants showed increased trust and co-operation with their in-group, while maintaining the same level of trust with their out-group. In <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/108/4/1262.full">one study</a>, participants performed an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Implicit_Association_Test">implicit association test</a>, where participants are timed in their categorisation of images of faces by grouping them with words that have positive or negative emotions. We often perceive visual information quickly, while rationally processing it takes longer. The Scientific American article mentions a similar study:</p>

<blockquote><p>On some trials of their experiment, one eye saw a neutral picture like a lamp, and the other eye saw a bloody scene of violence. On other trials, one eye saw a neutral picture and the other saw an erotic nude picture. The subjects’ conscious experiences of the pictures flipped back and forth, but the scenes of sex and violence were more likely to be the first ones seen, and they occupied consciousness much longer than the boring neutral images. Several studies have now confirmed that dangerous things like snakes, angry men, and snarling dogs can break through our concentration and intrude on consciousness. Dirty words and naughty pictures have the same effects&#8230; If it gets your heart racing it will get your attention.</p></blockquote>

<p>Make sure you don&#8217;t get distracted when considering the beautiful dolphins on this bottle:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/dolphinsex.jpg" alt="Dolphin Illusion" /></p>

<p>In a hunter-gatherer context, humans would need to interrupt their slow thinking processes to quickly react to a predator that suddenly appears, leaving us with sex and violence being distracting and intensely engaging in ways that reflective modes of thought aren&#8217;t. Why else would there be so much sex and violence on HBO shows like <em>Game of Thrones</em>?</p>

<p>The article goes on with this clincher:</p>

<blockquote><p>There is something particularly disquieting about this brand of bias, because there is a power asymmetry. The unconscious screener shapes what the conscious “you” gets to see, but the conscious “you” doesn’t have veto power over that decision. Of course, you could try to shift your attention or change your goals once you are aware of them, but by then it may be too late. The unconscious always has a head start.</p></blockquote>

<p>Jonathan Haidt likens fast and slow thinking to an <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/news/opinion/the-mind-has-an-elephant-of-its-own/2006/07/25/1153816179991.html?page=fullpage">emotional elephant with a rational rider</a>. The rider likes to think that he is in control, but really, the much larger elephant has most of the say in what direction the pair takes. In <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/files/emotional_dog_and_rational_tail.pdf">The Emotional Dog and its Rational Tail</a> Haidt states &#8220;moral reasoning is usually a post-hoc construction, generated after a judgment has been reached.&#8221; We assume that we are in control of our decisions, and yet psychology and behavioral economics shows that most of our rational decisions are a &#8220;slave&#8221; to the snap emotional judgements we make.</p>

<p>Consider Eddie McGuire&#8217;s <a href="http://theconversation.com/racism-in-the-afl-eddie-mcguire-and-the-media-prove-theres-still-a-long-way-to-go-14838">likening of Adam Goodes to King Kong</a> after nearly a week of condemning racially villifying remarks about Aboriginal AFL players. This doesn&#8217;t just highlight Eddie McGuire&#8217;s stupidity but points to the wider problem of people allowing racial stereotypes to colour their sentiments of people, while denying to themselves and others that any bias exists. Even people sincerely opposed to racism can act in <a href="http://theconversation.com/are-you-racist-you-may-be-without-even-knowing-it-10826">ways that express biases without knowing it</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Here’s an example of how this kind of thing can occur, from a <a href="http://socialjudgments.com/docs/Uhlmann%20and%20Cohen%202005.pdf">2005 American study</a>.
In this study, participants were asked to choose the better applicant
for the job of police chief. There were two candidates. One was “street
wise” while the other had more formal education. One was male, one was
female. Some experimental subjects were given the choice between a male
street wise applicant and a female formally educated applicant, while
some got the options reversed, with the female applicant being the
street wise one.</p>

<p>Here’s the interesting finding – both groups tended to pick the male
applicant as the better qualified. They justified this choice by
reference to the qualification the female lacked&#8230;</p>

<p>It looked as though they were making a judgement based on what qualifications they thought were required for police chief. They weren’t really: they were making a judgement based on gender, and justifying it, based on a confabulated theory about what qualifications were required for police chief.</p></blockquote>

<p>Similarly, when right of centre voters criticise Gillard in an excessively personal way (&#8220;Ju-liar&#8221;), a confabulatory process may mask mysoginistic attitudes as a justified criticism of her character and agenda. Worse, a tribal grouping of people who agree with each other&#8217;s politics encourages <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_cognition">cultural cognition</a>, with their own biases being confirmed by mostly talking with people who agree. Worse still is when they believe that their group is <a href="http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Sherif/chap7.htm">pitted against other groups, rather than a part of a political system that has the whole country&#8217;s interests at heart</a>. This will mean going beyong the current 24 hour news cycle driven vituperative personality politics and trying to find bipartisan unity in policy based discourse.</p>

<p>Many figures like Haidt <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/jonathan_haidt_how_common_threats_can_make_common_political_ground.html">want the media to stop feeding into a cycle of partisanship on critical issues</a> like US spending on prison systems, which has liberals denouncing the incaceration rates of ethnic minorities, conservatives concerned at <a href="http://www.rightoncrime.com/the-conservative-case-for-reform/what-conservatives-are-saying/">prisons expenditure risking the bankruptcy of several US states</a> and both concerned at <a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/01/03/rentier-theology/">bribery of the judiciary to raise sentences to increase demand for prison builders</a>.</p>

<p>If smart people can become more aware of their own biases, then they may be more likely to see the things that their subconsious may otherwise ignore, like successful people from racial minorities (or moonwalking bears). Then racism and sexism won&#8217;t be as much of a concern.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('j2odOu0Oguo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/j2odOu0Oguo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('j2odOu0Oguo-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/j2odOu0Oguo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j2odOu0Oguo" id="j2odOu0Oguo" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/j2odOu0Oguo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j2odOu0Oguo" id="j2odOu0Oguo-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Community Clip - Troy & Jeff talk racism/football</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" ></div>
</div>


<p>Online media has the potential to diversify the sources of information that people receive, as well as the potential to propagate <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kP4A6SbRdzM&amp;t=4m37s">extreme crank theories</a>. My belief is that if enough people are able to have a committment to consider the evidence rather than interpret facts though their own filter, then the good will outweigh the bad and most people will benefit from a rational discussion on important issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fundie Ladies Fashion Advice]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/04/fundie-ladies-fashion/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T02:41:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/04/fundie-ladies-fashion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.stufffundieslike.com/2013/06/a-dress-code">Stuff Fundies Like</a>, the Victory Faith Bible KJV1611 Baptist Church Dress Code for Ladies’ (sic). Yes, there are a huge number of typo&#8217;s (couldn&#8217;t refuse). As the old quote attributed to <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Miriam_A._Ferguson">Miriam A. Ferguson</a> goes, &#8220;If the King&#8217;s English was good enough for Jesus Christ, it&#8217;s good enough for the children of Texas!&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><h4>That which pertaineth to a man</h4>

<p>Ladies’ must abstain from all appearance of evil. That means our ladies’ here at VFBKJV1611 Baptist Church should not where pants or shorts.</p></blockquote>

<p>When your church&#8217;s abbreviated name is a mouthfull, you know the commitee that designed it did a good job listening to every one of the paritioners&#8217;.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Tops</h4>

<p>Blouses and dresses must reach the colorbone and be buttoned all the way up. If the buttons gap open at the bust, ladies’ should go up a size or use safety pins to avoid having their <strong>braziers</strong> showing, which can be very tempting to our young men and therefore inappropriate. Blouses should be full and not darted, which means there should be no ungodly emphasis on the waistline or underbust. Arms should be no shorter than the elbow. Sheer materials should be avoidable, but if you must wear a sheer blouse, also wear a <strong>skin-collared brazier</strong> and a full slip to conceal <strong>you’re nakedness</strong>. Tee shirts, tank tops and other immodest tops are not acceptable.</p></blockquote>

<p>I need to add a new favourite Christian pick up line &#8220;Your brazier gets my brazier going.&#8221; A great one to slip in after &#8220;nice bible&#8221; and &#8220;I&#8217;ve been reading Numbers and I realised I don&#8217;t have yours.&#8221;</p>

<p>By way of explanation: Bra is short for Brassiere, pronounced &#8220;/brəˈzɪər/&#8221; in the US, leading to word completion suggesting &#8220;brazier.&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><h4>Skirts</h4>

<p>Skirts should be at least 3 inches below the knee so that you can sit, kneel and otherwise move around without expositing your knee. Your skirt should also be at least a-line and preferably circle or very full to avoid drawring unnecessary attention to your legs. The waist should hit at your natural waist (low waistts are not acceptable) and be gathered to avoid unnecessary attention to the hips. Your skirt should have no slits. Kick pleats should not be necessary if your skirt is properly full. All <strong>ladies’ should where a slip</strong> with their skirts to avoid immodest exposure that could lead to lustful thoughts.</p></blockquote>

<p>Girls, why stop at the knee length skirts? Why not go to a <a href="http://thefbomb.org/2009/11/corduroy-skirts-are-a-sin/">full length corduroy skirt</a>?</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/corduroy.jpg" alt="Corduroy Skirts are a Sin" /></p>

<blockquote><h4>Culottes</h4>

<p>Box pleat culottes are required for outdoors activities, but <strong>we ask that our ladies’ not where them to services</strong>. Culottes should follow the same rules as skirts and reach at least 3 inches below the knee and be sufficiently full that <strong>we do not see the shape of your legs</strong>. Also, if you canot do it modestly in culottes, you should rethink doing it at all. It may just <strong>not be a ladylike actvitiy</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>And if your daughter starts looking too butch, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zyKw4yKfWOU">tell her off</a></p>

<blockquote><h4>Legs</h4>

<p>We know you have them. We do not want to see them. Please wear nylons or tights to conceal the flesh of your legs. Closed-toed shows are not mandatory, but we do ask our ladies’ to consider the fleshly desires of our gentlemen and dress accordingly. Heels that excessively “bunch up” the calf are nightclub attire, not church attire. Bobby socks and canvas tennis shoes are acceptable for certain functions. Please ask Mrs. Pastor for more information.</p></blockquote>

<p>And so the ladies&#8217; all know that the other ladies&#8217; have legs, which the men never, ever see.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Hair</h4>

<p>The KJV1611 says long hair is a glory. We request that our ladies’ <strong>discuss their hair with their husbands or fathers</strong> to determine the most appropriate hair length for godly glory. Hair should be a natural color (no red, pink or blue, please!) and cut in a flattering, modest manner that does not bring undue attention to our godly ladies heads.</p></blockquote>

<p>What the hell is a woman&#8217;s father doing giving you fashion advice? What would a man know about hair other than &#8220;I&#8217;m sure it looks <strong><em>fine</em></strong>.&#8221; At least they&#8217;re not asking <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2012/06/27/the-ugly-side-of-modesty/">grandpa for advice</a>.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Makeup and jewelry</h4>

<p>Ladies, if the barn needs painting, paint it, but <strong>avoid whoriehs excessiveness</strong>. Lipstick should be natural-colored, and leave the false eyelashes at home! Jewelry should be limited to (one) wedding ring and (one) engagement rink. GOD Himself tells us that peircings are a sign of slaves, not godly women, so skip them!</p></blockquote>

<p>Most any modern Christian would interpret biblical references to slavery as part of a bygone era. <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2013/03/doug-wilsons-race-problem.html">Not so in the wonky world of parochial Southern Christianity</a></p>

<blockquote><h4>Bodies</h4>

<p>We understand that ladies come in all shapes and sizes. That said, ladies who are thin should consider the effect of their vanity on their soles. Ladies who are bigger need to <strong>worry about their husbands’ soles and maybe lose some weight</strong> so their husbands are not tempted to stray. The rest of you ladies need to wear looser-fitting clothes to conceal your hips and other lady areas. We recommend jumpers since these offer the best coverage of (we apologize for our course language) curves.</p></blockquote>

<p>Yeah your husband&#8217;s shoes will wear out if he insists on <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2013/03/15/christian-pastor-i-carry-my-wife-around-the-house-every-day-to-show-her-whos-boss/">carrying you around the house to show you who&#8217;s boss</a></p>

<blockquote><h4>Other</h4>

<p>Any other concerns not already mentioned can be discussed with our godly pastor or any of the deacons, who would be happy to set up a private appointment to discuss your modesty needs or <strong>evaluate a particular outfit</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Something tells me most of these evaluations are not initated by the women themselves.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Visitors</h4>

<p>We understand that nonmebers may arrive wearing inappropriate clothing. Although we are always happy to welcome new people, we do feel it is important to emphasize modesty to protect our men from lustful thoughts. If you notice a visitor lady who is wearing a tight skirt, pants or a low-cut blouse, please let her know we love her as a sister, and <strong>offer her one of our spare sweaters</strong> (they are located in the church foyer’s coat rack) to wear over her top or place over her bottom half while she is sitting.</p></blockquote>

<p>Yes, because nothing will make a young woman in normal, socially acceptable knee length shorts feel comfortable than being told she has to put a borrowed sweater over her legs in a condescending &#8220;we just want the best for you&#8221; manner.</p>

<blockquote><p>We appreciate all our sisters’ in Christ taking the time to keep our church modest! Let us know if there is any way we can support you in this endeavor. </p>

<p>Please sign and date this document to signify your agreement to the dress code.</p></blockquote>

<p>The best part is many right wing Independent Fundamentalist Baptist churches support the <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/English-only_movement">English Only movement</a> and are opposed to immigration reform. Just have a look at some of the &#8221;<a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/teabonics-ridiculous-misspelled-tea-party-protest-signs-gallery-1.1918">Teabonics</a>&#8221; on <a href="http://politicalhumor.about.com/od/funnypictures/ig/Funny-Protest-Signs/">these protest signs</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-only-lanoguage.jpg" alt="protest-only-lanoguage.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-crestwood.jpg" alt="protest-crestwood.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-respect-are-country.jpg" alt="protest-respect-are-country.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-thank-you-fox-infromed.jpg" alt="protest-thank-you-fox-infromed.jpg" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-silent.jpg" alt="protest-silent.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-no-amnety.jpg" alt="protest-no-amnety.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-extremey-amesty.jpg" alt="protest-extremey-amesty.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-20-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-20-jpg.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-illiterate-protester.jpg" alt="protest-illiterate-protester.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-18-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-18-jpg.jpg" /></p>

<p>Apparently Illegals are bad, but dressing like Popeye is fantastic.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-22-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-22-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-27-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-27-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-28-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-28-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-29-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-29-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-birth-certifict.jpg" alt="protest-birth-certifict.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-computer.jpg" alt="protest-computer.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-gay-marridged.jpg" alt="protest-gay-marridged.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-homescholers-for-perry.jpg" alt="protest-homescholers-for-perry.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-mitt-fix-washinton.jpg" alt="protest-mitt-fix-washinton.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-morans.jpg" alt="protest-morans.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-obama-read-the-consitution.jpg" alt="protest-obama-read-the-consitution.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-teachchildren.jpg" alt="protest-teachchildren.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-teabagging-jesus-democracy.jpg" alt="protest-teabagging-jesus-democracy.jpg" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creationism is Stupid!]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/01/creationism-is-stupid/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T17:18:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/01/creationism-is-stupid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My latest video, <a href="http://youtu.be/PaimSZ2JDY0">Creationism is Stupid!</a></p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('PaimSZ2JDY0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/PaimSZ2JDY0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('PaimSZ2JDY0-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/PaimSZ2JDY0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PaimSZ2JDY0" id="PaimSZ2JDY0" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/PaimSZ2JDY0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PaimSZ2JDY0" id="PaimSZ2JDY0-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Creationism is Stupid!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Ken Ham, Kent Hovind and the banana man Ray Comfort give their most convincing presentation as to why the earth was definitely created 2000 years after the Sumerians invented glue.</div>
</div>


<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/evolution-sin.jpg" alt="Evolution Causes Sin" /></p>

<p>And here&#8217;s a car powered by fossil fuels driven by a fossil fool:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/evolution-fossils.jpg" alt="Evolution is a Fairy Tale, Apparently" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Evolution is True]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/31/why-evolution-is-true/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-31T19:03:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/31/why-evolution-is-true</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Answering Creation Ministries&#8217;s Questions</h3>

<p>Creation Ministries International run a &#8220;Question Evolution&#8221; campaign, handing out a pamphlet that asks 15 supposedly &#8220;unanswerable&#8221; questions about evolution. This article by <a href="http://www.morganstorey.com/">Morgan Storey</a>, seeks to answer all their questions, with references to find more information. You will have to do some research on your own, that is what science is about: doing the leg work to find out for yourself, nothing is handed to you on a silver platter or in a pretty leather bound book.</p>

<h3>15 questions for &#8220;Evolutionists&#8221; answered.</h3>

<p>Firstly we are not evolutionists; there are people who accept evolution and those that reject it. It would be like saying <a href="http://www.philvaz.com/apologetics/p67.htm">gravityists</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germ_theory_of_disease">germists</a>.</p>

<h3>1. How did life originate?</h3>

<p>A good question to be sure, but not actually an answer for the theory of evolution. As answering how the stars accreted isn&#8217;t an answer for the theory of gravity.</p>

<p>But to answer this, the current field that studies this is a field somewhere between chemistry and biology called abiogenesis. It studies how biological chemicals can form in different environments. Famous experiments such as the Miller-Urey experiment have shown that biological chemicals can form. More recent experiments of this nature have shown more complex biological chemicals forming such as proteins and long chain acid molecules similar to the precursor to DNA, RNA.</p>

<p>There is no definitive answer for how life originated on earth, it is very difficult for this kind of life to have survived till now for us to study it and primitive life would more than likely have not left fossils and even if they did due to subduction these fossils would no longer be accessible, or may have been destroyed by as the earth they were embedded in subducted back into the magma of the mantle.</p>

<h3>2. How did the DNA code originate?</h3>

<p>Again not the area of evolution. Evolution works via Natural selection on existing life, or even on the precursor which is not considered alive RNA. It is likely that DNA originated from RNA as DNA is simply a more stable double-helix over RNA&#8217;s single. But we don&#8217;t know, RNA/DNA is not fossilized as it decays too quickly, and it is unlikely that any primitive DNA/RNA transition will be found. There have been recent experiments that have shown XNA an even more stable triple-helix that never evolved on earth from the life we have today. The reason is very interesting. Although <a href="http://io9.com/5903221/meet-xna-the-first-synthetic-dna-that-evolves-like-the-real-thing">XNA</a> is less prone to copying errors and mutations it would also take a lot longer to evolve in changes, so it sacrifices its ability to change for stability. Obviously the balance was struck with DNA or XNA simply never formed.</p>

<p>Long answer short, we don&#8217;t know. That doesn&#8217;t mean it can&#8217;t be one of our simply answers rather than adding a complexity of a designer.</p>

<p>See also: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xeno_nucleic_acid">Xeno Nucleic Acid</a>.</p>

<h3>3. How could mutations-accidental copying mistakes create the huge volumes of information in the DNA of living things?</h3>

<p>This is a little misleading, DNA isn&#8217;t a code. It is a strand of molecules; it is only given a code so that we humans can understand it. It is translated by other chemical reactions in the cells that they occupy. But the mutations caused during life and passed on as well as the copying mistakes can add information. As any computer scientists knows if you copy multiple files in the wrong way you can combine them together going from 2 files to one much larger one. This has happened in biological DNA, human’s ancestors the old world apes have one more pair of chromosomes over humans, this was not understood for a long time and then it was found. The ends of chromosomes have these things called telomeres that stop the copying process when a strand is being duplicated; they mark the end of the strand. These have been found in the middle of a pair of human chromosomes, bearing the same markers as two pair in our nearest cousins the chimps. The chromosome pair at some stage fused too form one instead of two. Giving more DNA to the single chromosome and allowing for natural selection to work on a bigger selection of traits.</p>

<p>Not all traits from mutations are negative. There have been people found who have a <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/evolution/library/10/4/l_104_05.html">mutation that makes them immune to the HIV virus</a>, others in a <a href="http://phys.org/news101624600.html">small town in Italy that metabolise cholesterol so well that they never have a heart attack from their cholesterol rich diets</a>.</p>

<p>Others such as <a href="http://discovermagazine.com/2007/apr/the-upside-of-color-blindness/">colour blindness</a> and schizophrenia are being investigated for advantages regardless of the negatives, e.g. colour blind individuals can pick out camouflaged animals where others can&#8217;t.</p>

<p>See also: <a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn14094-bacteria-make-major-evolutionary">New Scientist &#8220;Bacteria make major evolutionary shift in the lab&#8221;</a></p>

<h3>4. Why is natural selection taught as if it explains the origins and diversity of life?</h3>

<p>It does explain the origin of our lives and the diversity of life we see around us. There is evidence in many species of its evolution; we have fossil evolutionary evidence for horses, wales, and of course humans. If you have a better hypothesis that explains all the current evidence and doesn&#8217;t add any extra complicated variables then propose it and it will be tested by other scientists, they will either find evidence for it, or none. If evidence cannot be found then it is un-falsifiable and simply bad science.</p>

<h3>5. How did the biochemical pathways, which involve multiple enzymes working together in sequence originate?</h3>

<p>You go from very simply worded questions to one like this, which seems like you want to throw people off your scent. But regardless, you are describing irreducible complexity inside cells. Which is something that is being actively studied, however evolution has had billions of years to build all of this up we have had only a couple hundred years. So we don&#8217;t know exactly, some of these enzymes and proteins may have evolved simultaneously from earlier simpler proteins and enzymes, in earlier and more primitive cells. This is what we see in extremophiles, but more study is required. Would you abandon your faith if it were discovered how these proteins and enzymes evolved, if not then you can&#8217;t use this argument.</p>

<p>References: <a href="http://www.sciencecodex.com/u_of_minn_researchers_unveil_first_artificial_enzyme_created_by_evolution_in_a_test_tube-105949">Researchers unveil first artificial enzyme created by evolution in a test tube</a></p>

<h3>6. Living things look like they were designed, how do evolutionists know they were not designed?</h3>

<p>Ok so things I guess could look designed&#8230; by a very <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argument_from_poor_design">bad designer</a>. The heart in a human has too few arteries to supply it with enough blood for it be as efficient as it should be for a land animal; it is fine for marine animals. Similar for the placement of spine along the back for an upright walker and the lack of extra sets of teeth for an animal such as us that lives so long, not to mention the laryngeal nerve that I am sure you have heard of, that runs from brain to voice box to allow all animals to control its muscles, except it makes a detour below the heart which is a lot longer than needed for humans, but think about the poor Giraffes where the detour is 18feet.</p>

<p>The universe is really not designed for us, most of it is deadly to us, too close to a star, neutron star, black hole, or galactic core and you will die, the blackness of space at a whopping 2.7Kelvin or -270.45 degrees Celsius (-454.81F) not to mention trillions of wandering asteroids and planets the size of Jupiter ready to wipe us out.</p>

<p>But even if all these design flaws didn&#8217;t exist then so what, it looks designed. Maybe we design things that look like nature because we are a part of it; we can&#8217;t design anything to not look like nature as we have no experience with things that aren&#8217;t part of nature.</p>

<h3>7. How did multi-cellular life originate?</h3>

<p>This is pretty simple. This is like saying how did humans and other animals work out that living and working together in packs, heards or tribes increased our chances for survival. We already see bacterial colonies that are colonies of lots of individual cells of bacteria working and living together, why not pool resources and specialise some bacteria to take in food and others to expel waste?</p>

<h3>8. How did sex originate?</h3>

<p>Interestingly we don&#8217;t know exactly. Again this <a href="http://talkorigins.org/indexcc/CB/CB350.html">probably originated early on in life’s development</a>, as some forms of bacteria don&#8217;t procreate asexually, some procreate with DNA from another party, some are not just binary male and female, but multi-sexed, having up to 7 different sexes, all of which need to come together to make an offspring. But larger than bacterially we are pretty much limited to the binary male and female. Though some switch such as certain fish and amphibians and for example the whip tail lizard and some lie along the gender path such as humans who can be born with both male and female genitalia, although a lot of these are non-functional there have been instances of functioning intersex humans.</p>

<p>The point is binary sexuality is a myth that has been perpetuated due to its prevalence not its truth. Many animals <a href="http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2013/04/accessible-res-snail-sex.html">can reproduce sexually and asexually</a>. Different genders of more than one do show better diversity and thus higher likelihood of passing on successful mutations such as the aforementioned HIV and cholesterol advantages. But obviously higher than two can be difficult to organise for the animals affected so it wasn&#8217;t as successful.</p>

<h3>9. Why are the expected countless millions of transitional fossils missing?</h3>

<p>This is a double whammy misconception; Every fossil ever found is a link between older and newer forms, so every fossil is a <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Transitional_fossils">transitional fossil</a>, your bones according to evolutionary theory are a transitional fossil of your father to your child. If you don&#8217;t have kids then you are an evolutionary dead end. It happens with surnames as it happened with our ancestors such as homo neanderthalis (to some extent, they did interbreed with us a little too).</p>

<p>Many transitional forms have been found that closed parts of the fossil record that were previously accused of having &#8220;gaps&#8221;.<br/>
In fact, in the century-and-a-half since then, we’ve found millions of
evolutionary intermediaries in the fossil record, much more than Darwin
said he could reasonably hope for. The transitional fossils that have
been found (such as <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Tiktaalik" title="Tiktaalik">Tiktaalik</a>,
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Ichthyostega" title="Ichthyostega">Ichthyostega</a>,
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Australopithecus" title="Australopithecus">Australopithecus</a>, <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Homo_habilis" title="Homo habilis">Homo
habilis</a>,
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Archaeopteryx" title="Archaeopteryx">Archaeopteryx</a>,
the <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Microraptor" title="Microraptor">Microraptor</a> and so on) provide clear evidence of transitions, in this case from water to
land and from land to flight. There are three different types of
transitional forms and we have ample examples of each. But creationists
still insist that we’ve never found a single one, because what they
usually ask us to present are impossible parodies which evolution would
neither produce nor permit (such as the
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Crocoduck" title="Crocoduck">Crocoduck</a>).</p>

<p>Evolution doesn&#8217;t dictate we would find fossils at all, that is geology. Fossilization is a very rare process so the fact we have any fossils at all is amazing. The missing fossils you talk of may always be missing, it doesn&#8217;t discredit the theory, it just means we realise our limitations of finding fossils at other records such as genetic evidence.</p>

<p>You say all the missing links are imagined, but that is just plain wrong you can go to your local natural history museum and see replicas of the skulls and sometimes entire skeletons of our ancestors. We have found hundreds of examples of some of these ancestors and the documentation and photographic evidence is in biological textbooks, physical evidence is available at some of the luckier natural history museums and research facilities. As like other fossils they are rare and expensive.</p>

<h3>10. How do &#8220;living Fossils&#8221; remain unchanged over supposed hundreds of millions of years if evolution has changed worms into humans in the same time frame?</h3>

<p>In the same time frame it turned the same worms into lions and elephants and whales and fish. These &#8221;<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Living_fossil">living fossils</a>&#8221; are called that as at least their initial outward appearance appears not to have changed, but new evidence suggests they have. Science changes it views based on what is observed, it is not afraid to admit it is wrong. The most famous &#8220;living fossil&#8221; the coelacanths is a fish that has found a very good niche so has had little selective pressure to change greatly from it hundred million year old ancestor, but it has changed according to recent research. Incidentally genetically its common ancestor with earth worms is the same as humans 782.7 million years ago roughly. So this and other &#8220;living fossils&#8221; simply have found a niche and a stable spot in the food change where any mutation that is beneficial to a changed environment will not help them so it doesn&#8217;t bread true.</p>

<p>References:
* http://timetree.org/index.php?taxon_a=Lumbricina&amp;taxon_b=homo+sapien&amp;submit=Search
* http://timetree.org/index.php?taxon_a=Lumbricina&amp;taxon_b=lion&amp;submit=Search
* http://timetree.org/index.php?found_taxon_a=6391|Lumbricina&amp;found_taxon_b=9783|elephant
* http://timetree.org/index.php?taxon_a=Lumbricina&amp;taxon_b=blue+whale&amp;submit=Search
* http://timetree.org/index.php?found_taxon_a=6391|Lumbricina&amp;found_taxon_b=7894|coelacanths</p>

<h3>11. How did blind chemistry create mind/intelligence, meaning, altruism and morality?</h3>

<p>Blind chemistry didn&#8217;t. Chemistry was probably the start of the precursor to life, but after that natural selection and evolution took over. It evolved in varying traits that where advantageous, such as communally living bacteria, then communally living animals such as schools of fish, then fish that where more cunning may have survived to pass on their DNA and been selected for, and intelligence built. This is why things like octopus can remember how to open jars as they can remember how to hide in certain types of coral and open certain types of shells to get to the tasty molluscs inside.</p>

<p>Morality and altruism is the realm of evolutionary psychologists, a relatively new field that has proposed various methods to answer how these features of our intelligence are advantageous in a community such as the ones humans and other animals form. The same reason piranha do not attack each other during a frenzy is the same reason we will assist our neighbour.</p>

<p>Life is not meaningless; it has whatever meaning you deign to it. If you give your life meaning through charity and altruism then society deems you a good person, if you give it through theft and crime society will punish you through the secular law system. The legal system has been built up by people not wanting others to treat them in such a manner, similar to the Christian golden rule but modified to allow for outliers such as those that may enjoy giving or receiving pain. The better version of the golden rule is &#8220;Do unto others as they would have you do unto them&#8221;.</p>

<p>So although some parts of morality and altruism are evolved others are learnt and passed down from parent to child. There are tribes that believe it is perfectly fine to kill unruly children and that anyone over 30 is not a member of the tribe. This does lead to a kind of moral relativism, but most ethicists will agree that what is moral is what causes the least amount of harm, and not caring for your young or elderly does cause harm to them, whereas caring for them causes in most circumstances almost no harm.</p>

<p>Morals are relative; it is not ok to kill&#8230; unless the person you are killing is threatening you or a loved one’s life. It is not ok to steal&#8230; unless if you don&#8217;t you or a loved one will die. It is not ok to lie&#8230; unless if you do so others will be harmed as I am sure a German harbouring Jews in WW2 would have realised.</p>

<p>References: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_psychology#Principles
http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-nature-nurture-nietzsche-blog/201005/did-morality-evolve</p>

<h3>12. Why is this evolutionary &#8220;just-so&#8221; story telling tolerated?</h3>

<p>This is really a loaded question, these aren&#8217;t just-so stories they are different stories that describe the entirety of our species. Kind of like the 3 blind-men describing an elephant, one grabs the trunk and describes it is a powerful type of snake, another feels the leg and describes a tree, another feels the feathery tale and describes a bird, all are wrong by themselves, but together their picture is of an elephant.</p>

<p>The stories talked about here are just-so as there is a huge pool of humans that these DNA sequences play out. Even in recorded history there were millions of us on the planet, this diversity is what has made us strong as a species. Some of us have blue eyes and thus better vision during the night and overcast winters, others have brown eyes with better vision during the day, this diversity and communal living means we are more likely to survive as a species as a single disease can&#8217;t come through a wipe us out, and different people can have different specialties.</p>

<h3>13. Where are the scientific breakthroughs due to evolution?</h3>

<p>The quote used here is what is called quote mining; Dr Kirschner is actually complaining here that there is little interdisciplinary work with other biologists. Biologists need a grounding in evolution to truly understand and model every experiment they perform.</p>

<p>Norman Borlaug in 1970 was awarded the Nobel Prize for his use of evolutionary theory to create crops that have so far saved possibly billions of lives.</p>

<p>Every year the flu shot that is given out is due to the use of evolutionary theory to determine how influenza strains will change in the coming year, the same is done for new strains of existing vaccinated diseases.</p>

<p>References:
* http://archive.truthout.org/article/missing-links
* http://journal.9med.net/qikan/article.php?id=224499</p>

<h3>14. Science involves experimenting to figure out how things work; how they operate. Why is evolution, a theory about HISTORY, taught as if it is the same as OPERATIONAL science?</h3>

<p>Firstly I don&#8217;t think theory means what you think it means. In science when you pluck an idea out of the air you have a hypothesis, not a theory. When your hypothesis is able to fail a test as in it is falsifiable and you have a lot of evidence backing a hypothesis and you have had your hypothesis tested by others and then you get it test a fair few more times, then and only then can you call it a theory. Looking at the numbers for example for the recently failed faster than light Tau Neutrino hypothesis they did 50,000 tests of their hypothesis before they released a paper for others to attempt to replicate or fail the experiment. They were quickly dismissed as the result couldn&#8217;t be replicated and they re-checked and re-checked their equipment and found the flaw&#8230; literally a loose wire.</p>

<p>Evolution via natural selection has been tested millions of times; errors have been found and corrected. The theory has changed, you may say due to this selective pressure it has evolved.
References: http://www.nature.com/news/flaws-found-in-faster-than-light-neutrino-measurement-1.10099</p>

<h3>15. Why is a fundamentally religious idea, a dogmatic belief system that fails to explain the evidence, taught in science classes?</h3>

<p>Sorry but I think I have shown how it explains the evidence, Darwin’s original hypothesis is testable and falsifiable, if no change where found in species, if a rabbit was found in strata of the pre-Cambrian it would be false and we would have to go back to the drawing board. If no way to transmit changes down from mother to child where discovered then it would be false, remembering that genes where not discovered till well after Darwin’s death, he was vindicated there.</p>

<p>Besides it is science, science isn&#8217;t about the comfortable or reassuring it is about what is true, even though evolution may not be comforting or reassuring to your beliefs it has shown to be true so far. If a better hypothesis comes along that explains the facts better, is tried tested and wins in the battle between scientific ideas then it will be the latest answer. But all evidence points to that not being much off what evolution via natural selection currently is.</p>

<p>I think teaching creation &#8220;theory&#8221; in a science class is the same as teaching the aforementioned phrenology in a neurology class, or teaching the stalk theory of birth in a sex-ed class, it is ludicrous and damaging to our children’s future. I know our kids are bright, they can take the idea of evolution and marvel and the grandeur and luck they have to just be here out of the literally billions upon billions of other DNA combinations that could have happened in their place.</p>

<p>Who is responsible for this pamphlet?
Sydney atheists care of www.sydneyatheists.org have used the design as a commentary on the original under fair use and thus they are responsible.</p>

<p>Although we are atheists, we care about what is true. We would prefer you believed the truth about our origins and believed in a god or gods than believe a falsity such as creation and also believe in God. Literal bible belief carries with it baggage no one wants, and will only lead to fundamentalism of a scale that will lead to war and violence.</p>

<p>We are happy to answer any of your questions via email to contact@sydneyatheist.org or via our Facebook group or page. Alternatively you can contact your local free thought group to see if they can assist you via http://atheist.meetup.com</p>

<p>Further reading: <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Question_Evolution">Rational Wiki</a>, <a href="http://www.proof-of-evolution.com/anti-evolution-drive-by-posting.html">Proof of Evolution.com</a>, <a href="http://blog.timparkinson.net/2011/09/12/answering-the-15-questions/">Answering the 15 questions</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Red State Christianity]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/23/red-state-christianity/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T04:32:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/23/red-state-christianity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Everything Is Terrible has dug up an awful Chrsitian cowboy VHS</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('BQL_q-oJB_g');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BQL_q-oJB_g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('BQL_q-oJB_g-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/BQL_q-oJB_g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQL_q-oJB_g" id="BQL_q-oJB_g" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/BQL_q-oJB_g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQL_q-oJB_g" id="BQL_q-oJB_g-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">EIT! ANSWERS PRAYER!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Religion Week at http://www.everythingisterrible.com</div>
</div>


<p>Steven Pinker in an <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/24/why-are-states-so-red-and-blue/">opinion piece</a> suggested that the reason America is so polically and socially diverse. He argues that Blue states were largely settled by English farmers, while Red states by Scots-Irish herders.</p>

<blockquote><p>Societies that herd livestock in rugged terrain tend to develop a “culture of honor.” Since their wealth has feet and can be stolen in an eye blink, they are forced to deter rustlers by cultivating a hair-trigger for violent retaliation against any trespass or insult that probes their resolve. Farmers can afford to be less belligerent because it is harder to steal their land out from under them, particularly in territories within the reach of law enforcement&#8230; Southerners today continue to manifest a culture of honor which legitimizes violent retaliation</p></blockquote>

<p>Pinker notes that under traditional, rugged societies violent and aggressive men were meant to be civilised by a churchgoing woman.</p>

<blockquote><p>Another cliché of the cowboy movies also had an element of historical truth. As more women moved west, they worked to end the lifestyle of brawling, boozing and whoring they found there, joining forces with the officials in charge of the rowdy settlements. They found a natural ally in the church, with its co-ed membership, norms of temperance and Sunday morning discipline.  By the time the government consolidated its control over the West&#8230; the norms of self-defense through masculine honor, and the restraint of ruffianism by women and church, had taken root.</p></blockquote>

<p>Many Southern Baptists continue with a frontier tradition of distrusting and resenting government (especially federal) laws that restrict personal freedoms, they readily believe that arbitrary and pointless church rules are good for them. It&#8217;s this type of political climate that breeds <a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/01/03/rentier-theology/">strange bedfellows, with the Religious Right co-opting both religion and politics</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anti Vaccine Misinformation Puts NSW Children at Risk]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/20/anti-vax-misinformation/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T03:15:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/20/anti-vax-misinformation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="figure"><a href="http://peopleinwhitecoats.blogspot.com.au/2012/09/vaccines-and-common-sense.html"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/ZombieVaccine.jpg" link="http://peopleinwhitecoats.blogspot.com.au/2012/09/vaccines-and-common-sense.html" title="Vaccines and common sense, People in White Coats" ><p>Vaccines and common sense, People in White Coats</span></a></div>


<p>According to a new study, reported in The Age, <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/national/health/worry-grows-over-safety-of-childhood-jabs-20130519-2juvt.html">53% of Australian parents have concerns about vaccinating their children</a>.</p>

<p>The NSW opposition is considering allowing childcare centres <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-05-19/push-to-ban-unvaccinated-children-from-nsw-preschools/4698786">ban unvaccinated individuals</a>. The opposition states that immunisation rates are lower than in Rwanda and Iran. Looking the stats up, it&#8217;s true. <a href="http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.IMM.MEAS/countries">WHO data on measels immunisation</a> show that 94% of Australian children are immunised, compared to 99% in Iran and 95% in Rwanda. <a href="http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.IMM.IDPT/countries">WHO data on Diptheria, Pertussis and Tetanus immunisation</a> shows 92% of Australian children are immunised, compared to 99% in Iran and 97% in Rwanda. <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/opinion/political-news/rwanda-trounces-australia-at-immunisation-20130529-2nc5n.html">Eritrea and Bangladesh also have higher immunisation rates</a></p>

<p>There were <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/measles.asp">172 cases of measles in NSW in 2012</a>, <a href="http://www.wahs.nsw.gov.au/news/2012/20121004_00.html">requiring the opening of new health centres to distribute the Mesles, Mumps and Rubella vaccine</a>. Rubella is rare, with less than <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/rubella.asp">6 new notifications</a> a month, Mumps spiked to <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/mumps.asp">24 cases in June 2012</a>. Pertussis (Whooping Cough) has trended downwards from around 2,000 new cases being reported in January 2009 to <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/pertussis.asp">less than 200 new cases a month in 2013</a>. Lack of concern about diseases like Whooping Cough may be a byproduct of good public health measures to prevent curtail the disease.</p>

<p>Data from Medicare show that NSW and WA have <a href="http://www.medicareaustralia.gov.au/provider/patients/acir/statistics.jsp">the lowest immunisation rates</a> with 89.3% of WA children 60-63 months of age. There are communities with less than <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-04-11/children-across-australia-not-fully-imunised/4622666">85% of children vaccinated, with 77,000 not fully immunised nationally</a>. Pockets in <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-03-20/anti-vaccination-campaigns-threaten-measles-free-status/4584514">northern NSW and southern QLD are at greatest risk</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Dr MacIntyre says some parts of Australia have a greater risk of a measles outbreak because of lower immunisation rates, such as northern New South Wales and southern Queensland.</p>

<p>Australian Medical Association (AMA) president Steve Hambleton says it is those areas which threaten Australia&#8217;s position.</p>

<p>&#8220;Our [measles] elimination status is under threat because there are pockets of decreasing immunisation of our children,&#8221; he said.</p></blockquote>

<p>Some affluent areas in Sydney also have <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-04-11/low-immunisation-rates-in-affluent-sydney/4622634">lower immunisation rates</a>
Unfortunately fear campaigns like Meryl Dorey&#8217;s Australian Vaccination Network have scared a small number (2%) of parents into rejecting vaccines, and a large proportion of parents feel a concern. Around 8% of parents don&#8217;t fully vaccinate their children, and would benefit from a public health campaign that listens to their concerns and tries to address them.</p>

<p>NSW Health minister Tanya Plibersek has launched a booklet &#8220;Immunisation Myths And Realities&#8221; and advised parents &#8221;<a href="http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/dr-google-cant-be-trusted-with-childs-health/story-e6frg6n6-1226650596663">Dr Google has been a negative influence</a>&#8221;. My opinion is that NSW Health and the AMA should be more proactive in online media, taking out ads on search results for searches like &#8216;vaccination&#8217; to make sure that correct information comes up before the AVN&#8217;s fearmongering, as while &#8220;Dr Google&#8221; may be prone to misinformation, the reality is that more and more parents will turn to it.</p>

<p>In the past it was possible to tell parents &#8220;just trust your GP and do what they say&#8221;. It may be more helpful, in future, to ensure that GPs listen to their patients to maintain high levels of trust in the public health system in an era of consumer focussed medicine and online misinformation campaigns.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
