<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></title>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//"/>
  <updated>2014-02-07T21:40:00+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://nsewell.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curiosity's Pale Blue Dot]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/07/pale-blue-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T20:03:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/07/pale-blue-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The curiosity rover has shot an image of the sky in mars, with Earth appearing as a <a href="images/pale-blue-dot-mars.jpg">tiny speck of light</a>:
<img src="images/pale-blue-dot-mars.jpg"></p>

<p>When you hear about <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2014/02/06/an-open-letter-to-abu-bakr-al-baghdadi-a-young-stranger-six-thousand-miles-and-a-dozen-years-away-2/">four year olds vowing to slaughter their enemies</a> in a war that has claimed the lives of <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-02-06/102c000-children-killed-in-syrian-civil-war3a-un-report/5241448">10,000 children</a> think about how great the bloodshed is over control of such a tiny fraction of such a small planet. Shane Smith <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cOndtUcRXdU&amp;list=PLw613M86o5o5BNP8ls1TNDLLHVEi1Mopg&amp;t=11m18s">notes</a> that at the same time as people are looking at the surface of mars on their smartphones, uneducated Afghan boys are being used in suicide attacks against civilians on Muslim holy days.</p>

<p>It brings to mind one of Carl Sagan&#8217;s most <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p9TIeuBF9Ss">famous speeches</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Look again at that dot. That&#8217;s here. That&#8217;s home. That&#8217;s us. On it everyone you love, everyone you know, everyone you ever heard of, every human being who ever was, lived out their lives. The aggregate of our joy and suffering, thousands of confident religions, ideologies, and economic doctrines, every hunter and forager, every hero and coward, every creator and destroyer of civilization, every king and peasant, every young couple in love, every mother and father, hopeful child, inventor and explorer, every teacher of morals, every corrupt politician, every &#8220;superstar,&#8221; every &#8220;supreme leader,&#8221; every saint and sinner in the history of our species lived there-on a mote of dust suspended in a sunbeam.</p>

<p>The Earth is a very small stage in a vast cosmic arena. Think of the endless cruelties visited by the inhabitants of one corner of this pixel on the scarcely distinguishable inhabitants of some other corner, how frequent their misunderstandings, how eager they are to kill one another, how fervent their hatreds. Think of the rivers of blood spilled by all those generals and emperors so that, in glory and triumph, they could become the momentary masters of a fraction of a dot.</p>

<p>Our posturings, our imagined self-importance, the delusion that we have some privileged position in the Universe, are challenged by this point of pale light. Our planet is a lonely speck in the great enveloping cosmic dark. In our obscurity, in all this vastness, there is no hint that help will come from elsewhere to save us from ourselves.</p>

<p>The Earth is the only world known so far to harbor life. There is nowhere else, at least in the near future, to which our species could migrate. Visit, yes. Settle, not yet. Like it or not, for the moment the Earth is where we make our stand.</p>

<p>It has been said that astronomy is a humbling and character-building experience. There is perhaps no better demonstration of the folly of human conceits than this distant image of our tiny world. To me, it underscores our responsibility to deal more kindly with one another, and to preserve and cherish the pale blue dot, the only home we&#8217;ve ever known.”</p></blockquote>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('p9TIeuBF9Ss');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/p9TIeuBF9Ss&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('p9TIeuBF9Ss-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/p9TIeuBF9Ss/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p9TIeuBF9Ss" id="p9TIeuBF9Ss" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/p9TIeuBF9Ss/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p9TIeuBF9Ss" id="p9TIeuBF9Ss-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">You Are Here: Carl Sagan on the pale blue dot photo [Carl Sagan Tribute Series]</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Like the Carl Sagan Tribute Series on Facebook https://www.facebook.com/milkywaymusings

Follow me on Twitter http://twitter.com/#!/milkywaymusings

Download the MP3 version at http://milkywaymusings.com

Copyright Disclaimer Under Section 107 of the Copyright Act 1976, allowance is made for &#8220;fair use&#8221; for purposes such as criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, scholarship, and research. Fair use is a use permitted by copyright statute that might otherwise be infringing. Non-profit, educational or personal use tips the balance in favor of fair use. All copyrighted materials contained herein belong to their respective copyright holders, I do not claim ownership over any of these materials. I realize no profit, monetary or otherwise, from the exhibition of these videos.

This video is part 10 of my continuing tribute to the late Carl Sagan.

Previous Episode: Darkness http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vEiEwQ7Rf4g
Next Episode: The Story of Everything http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U49i8HYMp2k
Playlist: https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL73E5E40315EA40FE&feature=view_all

Excerpts from Carl Sagan&#8217;s Pale Blue Dot: A Vision of the Human Future in Space and Cosmos.  More specifically, from the chapter titled You Are Here.  I edited together the audio from the audiobook, and added the video from:

- Apocalypse: The Second World War
- BBC&#8217;s Planet Earth
- BBC&#8217;s The Root of All Evil with Richard Dawkins
- BBC&#8217;s Walking with Cavemen
- BBC&#8217;s Wonders of the Solar System with Brian Cox
- Carl Sagan&#8217;s Cosmos
- Discovery&#8217;s Into the Universe with Stephen Hawking

The music is &#8220;The Science of Faith&#8221;, &#8220;La Fleur&#8221; and &#8220;For Love of the Dame&#8221; by Michael Giacchino from the Lost soundtrack.

The Carl Sagan Tribute Series will continue, please subscribe to my channel if you wish to be among the first to see my newest videos.

If you enjoyed this video, read the magnificent book from which it originated: http://www.amazon.com/Pale-Blue-Dot-Vision-Future/dp/0345376595/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&s=books&qid=1278371196&sr=8-1

Also highly recommended, Cosmic Connection: http://www.amazon.com/Carl-Sagans-Cosmic-Connection-Extraterrestrial/dp/0521783038/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_11</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can we Know Anything?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/07/positivism/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T16:47:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/07/positivism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Consider this: your colleague David has been running late to work and needs to buy a new alarm clock. He goes to a clock shop with 100 clocks to find one to buy, but upon inspecting the clocks, he finds that some disagree with each other. About 3% of the clocks have a major discrepancy with the other clocks. Which is a reasonable conclusion?</p>

<ol>
<li>David decides to buy a clock, and trusts that it can tell the time accurately enough</li>
<li>David decides to go to another shop that will have better clocks</li>
<li>David decides not to buy a clock, not trusting the accuracy of any clocks he could buy</li>
<li>David confirms his suspicion that time cannot be measured by anyone (which he had deduced from his study of ancient poetry that describe the gods as making time as a stream that ebbs and flows), and laments the number of poor children duped by the pro-temporalist bias in the media and the public schooling system, that have conspired to push dissenting voices out of the public sphere because of corporate interests and the academic pride of liberal elites in their ivory towers at so-called ivy league universities.</li>
</ol>


<p>I think we all understand that 4 is not a reasonable position, but sophists have for centuries tried to confuse the public by describing scientific uncertainty and scientific doubt as the same thing. I mention the example of clocks because Bill Nye used it as an example of scientific uncertainty in his debate with the young earth creationist Ken Ham. Ham claims that discrepancies between certain forms of radiometric dating mean that nobody can have any trust that the earth is more than 10,000 years old, which is his <em>a priori</em> conclusion derived from selective interpretation of a modern translation of an ancient Hebrew religious text. Nye&#8217;s example is a good one, because nobody objects to the conclusion that time is measurable, and so nobody tries to use the tricks that creationists and flat-earthers will use when discussing science.</p>

<p>In 1864 the founder of the Flat Earth Society, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Rowbotham">Dr Parallax</a>, was finally challenged to perform a public experiment to test his claim of a flat earth. An astronomer predicted that because of the curvature of the earth, only the lantern of a distant lighthouse would be visible. The effect of the curvature of the earth was greater than what the astronomer had predicted, and Parallax observed only half the lantern of the lighthouse, leading him to claim that he won the experiment. The example of Parallax shows the clear danger of an uncharismatic scientist unable to cope with a charlatan.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s very easy to spin certain soundbites in a way that a scientifically illiterate audience won&#8217;t understand. Consider, for instance, the cooling periods that can be found by cherry picking the regions of <a href="http://www.skepticalscience.com/graphics.php?g=47">analysis in global temperatures</a>:
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/climate-skepticalscience.jpg"></p>

<p>Scientists need to be careful in a world of soundbites that they aren&#8217;t completely misrepretented by charlatans. As Carl Sagan <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U8HEwO-2L4w">said</a> &#8220;if we are not able to ask skeptical questions, to interrogate those who tell us that something is true, to be skeptical of those in authority, then we&#8217;re up for grabs, for the next charlatan, political or religious who comes ambling along.&#8221; Unfortunately, with weak scientific education and a media that present false balance, it can be hard for sicentists to demonstrate the <a href="http://skepticalscience.com/Debunking-climate-myths-two-contrasting-case-studies.html">consensus they have on issues</a>. On climate issues, NASA and the NOAA are putting more effort into <a href="http://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/files/NOAA_NASA_2013_Global_Temperatures_Joint_Briefing.pdf">publishing information themselves</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scott Morrison's Moral Barometer]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/04/morrison/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-04T18:57:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/04/morrison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr Marrion Maddox spoke about the <a href="http://www.saintdavids.org.nz/FergusonLectureJune2006.pdf">rise of Christian fundamentalism in Australian politics</a> in 2006:</p>

<blockquote><p>Christian parties have existed in Australia for a long time, but, due to the robust two- party system, have seldom had much direct electoral influence18. The Christian Democratic Party (CDP) and its predecessor (Call to Australia) have been represented in the New South Wales upper house since 1981, but enjoyed their sole, fleeting federal presence for a few months in 1998.</p>

<p>The big news story of the 2004 federal election was the national launch of Adelaide- based minor party Family First (FFP). With one member already in the South Australian upper house, FFP ran federal candidates all over Australia. Despite a small primary vote, elaborate preference deals meant that the party had one Senator elected, Victorian Steve Fielding. Most of the candidates were members of one denomination, the Assemblies of God. Others, such as Fielding, came from related Pentecostal traditions. A few identified with other traditions, such as Catholic. Despite these connections, the party emphatically portrayed itself as a ‘family values’ party, rejecting suggestions that it is a ‘Christian party’. Party events sometimes resemble church functions, and vice versa20, but the party’s website scrupulously avoids religious references, leading even other Christian parties to allege duplicity on FFP’s part21. The media image of FFP as a Christian party has persisted, despite official denials. For example, on the Sunday morning after the election, when it appeared FFP might have the balance of power in the Senate, veteran television journalist Laurie Oakes proposed that FFP’s success marked ‘the arrival of the religious right in Australian politics’.</p>

<p>However, despite the huge media fascination it generated, FFP was only ever a sideshow in Australian religious right politics. Far more significant was the positioning of the Liberal Party increasingly towards the religious right, which, as I document in detail in my book God Under Howard: The Rise of the Religious Right in Australian Politics23 , had been underway since the formation of the federal Liberal Party’s socially conservative, ambiguously-Christian Lyons Forum pressure group in the early 1990s.  Religious priming (known journalistically as the ‘dog-whistle’ strategy) reached its peak in the lead-up to the 2004 campaign.</p>

<p>Here, too, the Assemblies of God featured prominently. While Adelaide’s Paradise Church was the launching pad for FFP, its Sydney counterpart, Hillsong, became associated with the Liberal Party. Not only did John Howard, his Liberal deputy Peter Costello and other senior Liberals address the church, but Hillsong has claimed Liberal Member for Mitchell Alan Cadman, Young Liberals president Alex Hawke and former NSW Liberal Party director Scott Morrison as members.</p></blockquote>

<p>Nick Bryant notes that Morrison was mentored by Brian Houston himself, which is where he <a href="http://www.themonthly.com.au/issue/2012/february/1328593883/nick-bryant/so-who-bloody-hell-are-you">bases his ethical foundation</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Morrison is now a Pentecostal and thus part of the most rapidly growing denomination in the land. He worships at an American-style mega-church called Shirelive in his constituency, where the gospel of prosperity is preached in an auditorium that can accommodate over 1000 evangelicals. With its water baptisms and designer-shirt pastors, Shirelive has close ties with the better-known Hillsong community. The founder of Hillsong, Harley Davidson–riding pastor Brian Houston, is one of Morrison’s mentors. In Who’s Who Morrison lists the church as his number one hobby, and his maiden speech reads in part like a personal testimony delivered on the last night of a church retreat. It included passages from Jeremiah and also the Book of Joel: “Your old men will dream dreams, your young men will see visions.”</p>

<p>A test of his faith came during the period when he and his wife were trying to start a family. It involved repeated courses of IVF treatment and “14 years of bitter disappointments”, but Scott and Jenny were buoyed by their sense of the providential. “God remembered her faithfulness,” recalled Morrison during his maiden speech, as he paid tribute to his wife, “and blessed us with our miracle child, Abbey Rose.” The couple now have two daughters.</p>

<p>While his faith animates his politics, he is on the record as saying “the Bible is not a policy handbook, and I get very worried when people try to treat it like one”. Critics would say that is self-evident from his heartless response to asylum seekers. “I wonder how you can claim to be a serious Christian and take these positions,” said one former colleague. Supporters, however, claim he has pursued a faith-based policy. “He’s a very ethical and moral man,” says a fellow Liberal. “Stopping the boats is ethical and moral.” In his response to December’s boat people tragedy off Java, he advocated a ‘tough love’ policy, which he claimed had the safety of boat people at its heart. After all, for Morrison the Pacific Solution was not only efficient but righteous since it crushed the evil of people smuggling. Church friends might even have seen shades of Wilberforce in his efforts to eradicate such a nefarious trade. To his critics, however, his attacks on the government, which resumed 48 hours after the overloaded boat capsized, offered yet more proof of his harrying opportunism: this was more about political point-scoring than finding a workable solution.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shaun Micallef's Year in Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/03/micallef/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T20:40:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/03/micallef</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2013 - The Year In Review Part 1</p>

<p>Liquid error: undefined method `[]&#8217; for nil:NilClass</p>

<p>2013 - The Year In Review Part 2</p>

<p>Liquid error: undefined method `[]&#8217; for nil:NilClass</p>

<p>2013 - The Year In Review Part 3</p>

<p>Liquid error: undefined method `[]&#8217; for nil:NilClass</p>

<p>2013 - The Year In Review Part 4</p>

<p>Liquid error: undefined method `[]&#8217; for nil:NilClass</p>

<p>What a year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crocodiles in Slow Motion]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/03/crocs/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T20:17:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/02/03/crocs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Superbowl ads this year seem completely underwhelming, all the good ones have already been &#8216;leaked&#8217; on youtube. This ad for tourism in the Northern Territory shits on them all, watch it in HD:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('AsouteXHNZY');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/AsouteXHNZY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('AsouteXHNZY-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/AsouteXHNZY/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AsouteXHNZY" id="AsouteXHNZY" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/AsouteXHNZY/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AsouteXHNZY" id="AsouteXHNZY-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Fishing for Crocodiles - Slow Motion</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Thanks to http://www.crocosauruscove.com in Darwin, Australia. You can feed crocodiles, swim with crocodiles, and get really up close to them. Feeding them using a fishing rod is a really unique experience, as you can see they jump pretty high out the water. I didn&#8217;t know they could actually jump completely out of water.

The slow motion gives you really good detail in the crocodiles movement. Something you rarely see.

On a technical side of things.

This was all filmed using a Sony fs700 with a 18-200mm 3.5-5f lens. Shot at 480 frames a second. I borrowed the camera from Sony to test and love it&#8217;s ability to capture slow motion. If you&#8217;re going to shoot slow motion it&#8217;s the cheapest camera for an indie cinematographer. 

I wasn&#8217;t paid to say any of this, Sony just wanted some footage. Maybe I&#8217;ll buy the camera soon.

http://pro.sony.com/bbsc/ssr/product-NEXFS700U/

I&#8217;m on Facebook
http://www.facebook.com/allandx

I&#8217;m on Twitter
http://www.twitter.com/daxon

I&#8217;m on Instagram
http://www.instagram.com/daxon

Thanks</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Media Still Pushing Debunked Gerson Therapy]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/30/gerson/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T01:44:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/30/gerson</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jessica Ainscough is working though a list of patsies, finding her way
into being reported (with the barest of skepticism) by the <a href="http://www.donotlink.com/dd9">Sydney Morning Herald</a>. I wrote about her
unfortunate dependance on quackery in
<a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/24/coffee-enema/">June</a>, and her <a href="http://scienceblogs.com/insolence/2013/10/17/sharyn-ainscough-dies-tragically-because-she-followed-the-example-of-her-daughter-the-wellness-warrior/">mother has since passed away</a>.
Orac notes that as Ainscough’s mother was dying, she claimed that the
tumours were “healing reactions” and there was an underlying “copper
toxicity” supposedly treatable with chelation therapy:</p>

<blockquote><p>How many times have we heard cancer quacks say this, that the cancer
is not the problem but rather a “symptom” of the “real” problem or a
“protective reaction” to the real problem?</p></blockquote>

<p>As I noted in June, Ainscough invented “psychic pollution”</p>

<blockquote><p>our negative thoughts also contribute to pollution on our planet. This
is called ‘psychic pollution.’ This fact has been proven: what we
think and feel has a direct impact on the world around us</p></blockquote>

<p>There are many benefits to encouraging cancer patients to seek
professional counselling services when dealing with the side effects of
radiation and chemotherapy, as well as depression resulting from their
diagnosis. Unfortunately, many quacks try to adopt the language of
pop-psychology and tell people with terminal cancer that their
depression is the <em>cause</em> of their terminal condition, and they need to
force themselves to think positively in order to be cured. Not only will
terminal patients go to the grabe believing that they have some
spiritual or mental deficiency that causes their condition, but quacks
are given an easy excuse for the failures of treatments on patients
believed to be too “weak” or “faithless”.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Media Manipulation]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/28/media-manipulation/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T04:36:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/28/media-manipulation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following the shooting of Gabrielle Giffords, a large number of left
leaning media outlets criticised the right wing media’s hype and
extremism. Dan Lyons took <a href="http://www.fakesteve.net/2011/01/my-talk-with-a-left-wing-hack.html">them to task</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The problem began when news became tied to profits. The networks at
one time used to run news as a loss leader, subsidized by
entertainment. When that changed, and news started chasing ratings
(and dollars), the problem began. When dollars started to dry up,
things only got worse. Networks became desperate and resorted to
making the news more like entertainment.</p>

<p>The Internet made things worse, in two ways. First, the Internet
exacerbated the decline in revenues, and heightened the desperation in
the news business. Trust me, I’m in a position to know, because I’m in
the business of seeing just how far I can make news people bend in
order to keep getting my advertising dollars. That influence is
stronger now than it has ever been. The TV networks and magazines and
newspapers are desperate and terrified. Stuff that 10 years ago they
would have thrown back in our face they now do willingly — in fact,
they don’t even wait for us to suggest it. They suggest it themselves.</p>

<p>But second, and more important, the Internet created an outlet for
competing and often crazy voices. It gave birth to a new kind of
“news.” Despite what the new-media pundits claim, the much-celebrated
“citizen journalism” was all too often just noisy crap and propaganda.</p></blockquote>

<p>Most of the news is written by interns that only get hired if they drive
enough clicks to their linkbait articles:</p>

<blockquote><p>It’s garbage precisely because online news sites are not primarily
created to report news. They’re created to make money. Problem is,
it’s nearly impossible to make money doing what they do. So they
resort to ever more desperate tricks.</p>

<p>Why is so much online “news” reported in slideshow format? To gin up
clicks. Not because it is a better way to consume news, because,
please. Why is HuffPo so crowded with sensationalistic tabloid junk
about celebrity boobs and fluffy “lists” of “the deadliest ice
creams.” (And just about everyone else, too. )</p></blockquote>

<p>Ryan Holiday gave a keynote at TNW about how bad glorified blog
journalism is, and how easy it is to exploit media into running
“controversial” linkbait stories, like Sasha Grey in an American Apparel
ad campaign.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('ZN9r1-ImSQc');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ZN9r1-ImSQc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('ZN9r1-ImSQc-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ZN9r1-ImSQc/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZN9r1-ImSQc" id="ZN9r1-ImSQc" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ZN9r1-ImSQc/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZN9r1-ImSQc" id="ZN9r1-ImSQc-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Keynote Ryan Holiday at TNW Conference Europe 2013</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Join our upcoming The Next Web Conferences:
TNW Conference Latin America 2013 (August): http://tnw.to/j0eLe
TNW Conference USA 2013 (October): http://tnw.to/q40m</div>
</div>


<p>Tim Ferris has <a href="http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2012/07/18/ryan-holiday/">more details</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tecnoutopianism]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/28/technoutopianism/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T01:36:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/28/technoutopianism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was going to write a post on Ivy League universities backing Massive
Open Online Courses though edX and other providers, and started thinking
back to the discussion of the OLPC project in 2007. Widespread media
coverage showed Kofi Annan holding a prototype laptop with a hand crank
and repeated the claim that the device would eventually be available for
$100. The hand crank and the $100 price tag were unachievable, and major
glitches in the first version of the laptops dampened the hype
surrounding the project.</p>

<p>Vaclav Smil, professor emeritus of environment and geography at the
University of Manitoba commented on the media’s tendency to see technology as a <a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2013/11/vaclav-smil-wired/">magic solution to intractable problems</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>So the answers are not technological but political: better economic
policies, better education, better trade policies.</strong></p>

<p>Right. Today, as you know, everything is “innovation.” We have
problems, and people are looking for fairy-tale solutions—innovation
like manna from heaven falling on the Israelites and saving them from
the desert. It’s like, “Let’s not reform the education system, the tax
system. Let’s not improve our dysfunctional government. Just wait for
this innovation manna from a little group of people in Silicon Valley,
preferably of Indian origin.”</p>

<p>You people at WIRED—you’re the guilty ones! You support these people,
you write about them, you elevate them onto the cover! You really
messed it up. I tell you, you pushed this on the American public,
right? And people believe it now.</p></blockquote>

<p>Smil notes that the idea of efficiency gains in every sector is “Moore’s
curse”</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>You call this Moore’s curse—the idea that if we’re innovative
enough, everything can have yearly efficiency gains.</strong></p>

<p>It’s a categorical mistake. You just cannot increase the efficiency of
power plants like that. You have your combustion machines—the best one
in the lab now is about 40 percent efficient. In the field they’re
about 15 or 20 percent efficient. Well, you can’t quintuple it,
because that would be 100 percent efficient. Impossible, right? There
are limits. It’s not a microchip.</p>

<p>The same thing is true in agriculture. You cannot increase the
efficiency of photosynthesis. We improve the performance of farms by
irrigating them and fertilizing them to provide all these nutrients.
But we cannot keep on doubling the yield every two years. Moore’s law
doesn’t apply to plants.</p></blockquote>

<p>Benjamin Bratton made similar talks in a <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/dec/30/we-need-to-talk-about-ted">TEDx talk about technological utopianism overlooking the difficult problems in philosophy and economics</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The key rhetorical device for TED talks is a combination of epiphany
and personal testimony (an “epiphimony” if you like ) through which
the speaker shares a personal journey of insight and realisation, its
triumphs and tribulations.</p>

<p>What is it that the TED audience hopes to get from this? A vicarious
insight, a fleeting moment of wonder, an inkling that maybe it’s all
going to work out after all? A spiritual buzz?</p>

<p>I’m sorry but this fails to meet the challenges that we are supposedly
here to confront. These are complicated and difficult and are not
given to tidy just-so solutions. They don’t care about anyone’s
experience of optimism. Given the stakes, making our best and
brightest waste their time – and the audience’s time – dancing like
infomercial hosts is too high a price. It is cynical.</p>

<p>Also, it just doesn’t work.</p>

<p>Recently there was a bit of a dust up when TEDGlobal sent out a note
to TEDx organisers asking them not to not book speakers whose work
spans the paranormal, the conspiratorial, new age “quantum
neuroenergy”, etc: what is called woo. Instead of these placebos, TEDx
should instead curate talks that are imaginative but grounded in
reality. In fairness, they took some heat, so their gesture should be
acknowledged. A lot of people take TED very seriously, and might lend
credence to specious ideas if stamped with TED credentials. “No” to
placebo science and medicine.</p>

<p>But … the corollaries of placebo science and placebo medicine are
placebo politics and placebo innovation. On this point, TED has a long
way to go.</p>

<p>Perhaps the pinnacle of placebo politics and innovation was featured
at TEDx San Diego in 2011. You’re familiar I assume with Kony2012, the
social media campaign to stop war crimes in central Africa? So what
happened here? Evangelical surfer bro goes to help kids in Africa. He
makes a campy video explaining genocide to the cast of Glee. The world
finds his public epiphany to be shallow to the point of self-delusion.
The complex geopolitics of central Africa are left undisturbed. Kony’s
still there. The end.</p>

<p>You see, when inspiration becomes manipulation, inspiration becomes
obfuscation. If you are not cynical you should be sceptical. You
should be as sceptical of placebo politics as you are placebo
medicine.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Map Shows the Harm of the Anti-Vaccine Movement]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/26/anti-vax/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-26T23:54:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/26/anti-vax</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new map by the <a href="http://www.cfr.org/interactives/GH_Vaccine_Map/#map">Council on Foreign Relations</a> shows
the rising number of vaccine preventable diseases in first world
contries. After Andrew Wakefield took out a <a href="http://briandeer.com/wakefield/vaccine-patent.htm">patent on a single Measels vaccine</a> he falsified a study that appeared to show that appeared to show that the Measels, Mumps and Rubella triple antigen was unsafe for children, proposing his own patented vaccine as a “safer” alternative. Even after Wakefield’s paper has been retracted for innacuracy, and he was struck off the medical register for <a href="http://briandeer.com/mmr-lancet.htm">“dishonest”, “unethical” and “callous”</a> behaviour, anti-vaccine hysteria continues to spread thoughout the world. The drop in MMR vaccination rates in Wales to below 80% has caused a widespread measels outbreak, leaving parents of infected teenagers feeling betrayed by the lies of the anti-vaccine movement:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('VpA7Cv_4oVo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VpA7Cv_4oVo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('VpA7Cv_4oVo-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VpA7Cv_4oVo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VpA7Cv_4oVo" id="VpA7Cv_4oVo" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VpA7Cv_4oVo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VpA7Cv_4oVo" id="VpA7Cv_4oVo-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Wakefield MMR fraud comes home to roost in Wales</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Australian ABC Lateline programme looks at the early-2013 outbreak of measles in Wales UK. 
A recent measles fatality is likely linked to the Andrew Wakefield MMR fraud which led to a baseless reduction in uptake of the MMR vaccine. It&#8217;s apparent that now fear of the demonstrable harm of measles outweighs the fallacious fear of MMR.
Notifications equal 800 since November 2012 - approximately 7 times that for the entire year of 2012.
The vast majority of parents now accept that the &#8220;callous&#8221; and deregistered Wakefield is a charlatan and a fraud.</div>
</div>


<p>Australian ABC Lateline programme looks at the early-2013 outbreak of
measles in Wales UK. A recent measles fatality is likely linked to the
Andrew Wakefield MMR fraud which led to a baseless reduction in uptake
of the MMR vaccine. It’s apparent that now fear of the demonstrable harm
of measles outweighs the fallacious fear of MMR. Notifications equal 800
since November 2012 - approximately 7 times that for the entire year of
2012. The vast majority of parents now accept that the “callous” and
deregistered Wakefield is a charlatan and a fraud.</p>

<p>Interestingly, Wakefield is only the latest in a long line of cranks
opposed to the vaccination of children. I recently came across a talk by <a href="http://www.gresham.ac.uk/lectures-and-events/from-jenner-to-wakefield-the-long-shadow-of-the-anti-vaccination-movement">Professor Gareth Williams</a>
on the history of the anti-vaccine movement, going right back to Jenner
himself. Some doctors opposed cowpox vaccination as smallpox cases were
a large portion of their business, but most interestingly many people found religious arguments against vaccination. Theologians in France and England argued that ”<a href="http://abob.libs.uga.edu/bobk/whitem10.html">diseases are sent by Providence for the punishment of sin</a>” and suggested that
Job’s <a href="https://net.bible.org/#!bible/Job+2:4">boils and ulcers</a> were a
result of cowpox vaccination by Satan. One of the most wacko opponents of the Jennerian society wrote that smallpox helped to <a href="http://pds.lib.harvard.edu/pds/view/6059511?n=32&amp;imagesize=1200&amp;jp2Res=.25&amp;printThumbnails=no">lower the size of poor families</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>why is it not remembered that in the populous parts of the Metropolis,
where the abundance of children exceed the means of providing food,
and raiment for them, this pestilential disease is considered as a
merciful provision on the part of Providence, to lessen the burthen of
a poor man’s family ?</p></blockquote>

<p>Interestingly, while most doctors (Wakefield excluded) would never seek
to harm their patients to increase their own business, many pastors
coninue to teach that children should not be vaccinated against
infectious diseases. Measels outbreaks have been observed in areas with
low vaccination rates, commonly correlated with <a href="http://freethoughtblogs.com/butterfliesandwheels/2013/09/vaccines-undermine-divine-providence/">high numbers of evangelical megachurches</a>.  Unfortunately, a number of churches order their congregation to eschew medical treatment in favour of prayer, which <a href="http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2014/01/17/idaho-republican-opposes-law-aimed-at-stopping-faith-healing-child-deaths/">Republican lawmakers protect as “religious freedom”</a>, even after a spate of preventable deaths.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pia Waugh on Technology's new Citizinship at TEDx]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/07/pia-ted/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T11:34:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/07/pia-ted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pia Waugh is the former president of Linux Australia, and she gave a great talk at a TEDx event in Canberra:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('iqjM_HU0WSw');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/iqjM_HU0WSw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('iqjM_HU0WSw-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/iqjM_HU0WSw/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqjM_HU0WSw" id="iqjM_HU0WSw" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/iqjM_HU0WSw/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqjM_HU0WSw" id="iqjM_HU0WSw-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">The new citizenship: Pia Waugh at TEDxCanberraWomen</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Pia Waugh is an open government and open data advocate, working to enable greater transparency, democratic engagement, citizen-centric design, and pragmatic innovation in the public sector and beyond. She believes that tech culture has a huge role to play in achieving better policy planning, outcomes, public engagement and a better public service.

In the spirit of ideas worth spreading, TEDx is a program of local, self-organized events that bring people together to share a TED-like experience. At a TEDx event, TEDTalks video and live speakers combine to spark deep discussion and connection in a small group. These local, self-organized events are branded TEDx, where x = independently organized TED event. The TED Conference provides general guidance for the TEDx program, but individual TEDx events are self-organized.* (*Subject to certain rules and regulations)</div>
</div>


<p>A few great points
* Inverting William Gibson&#8217;s view: &#8220;The future is here, and it <strong>is</strong> widely distributed&#8221;
* There is a global shift in power from the West to the East, and from traditional centralised power structures to users.
* The ability to see different perspectives over the same medium challenges the idea of a single source of truth.
* The freedom of the users comes directly from the freedom of the tools they use.
* Technologists have the abilitiy to route around a damaged system, but they have a moral responsibility to represent those that can&#8217;t.
* Internet users are among only a third of the world, and so every internet user has the power to effect the world in positive ways.
* Pia on Hipsters: Billie Brag quote &#8220;Cynicism is the perfect enemy of progress.&#8221;
* If we don&#8217;t work to shape the future, someone else is going to shape it for us.
* The future is not just being determned in traditional ways.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lonely Quest for Facts on Genetically Modified Crops]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/07/gmo-pseudoscience/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T01:36:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/01/07/gmo-pseudoscience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a great article in the New York Times about how politicians and
the public in Hawaii are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/05/us/on-hawaii-a-lonely-quest-for-facts-about-gmos.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=2&amp;">refusing to listen to scientists about how Genetically Modified organisms are safe to eat</a>.
It links to a great graph from boingboing pointing out the fallacy of
<a href="http://boingboing.net/2013/01/01/correlation-between-autism-dia.html">confusing corellation with causation</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/organic-autism.png" title="A facile corellation shown between organic food sales and autism diagnoses" alt="image" /></p>

<p>Science Magazine is one of the bastions of reason, with Nobel lauriets
signing an open letter denouncing the <a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/341/6152/1320.full">destruction of test
crops</a></p>

<blockquote><p>New technologies often evoke rumors of hazard. These generally fade
with time when, as in this case, no real hazards emerge. But the
anti-GMO fever still burns brightly, fanned by electronic gossip and
well-organized fear-mongering that profits some individuals and
organizations. We, and the thousands of other scientists who have
signed the statement of protest, stand together in staunch opposition
to the violent destruction of required tests on valuable advances such
as Golden Rice that have the potential to save millions of
impoverished fellow humans from needless suffering and death.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others, such as the co-Founder of Greenpeace, Dr. Patrick Moore, have
spoken out against the group’s increasingly hysterical <a href="http://www.allowgoldenricenow.org/moral-compass">opposition to GM crops like Golden Rice</a>:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('8MCtVqmCoI8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/8MCtVqmCoI8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('8MCtVqmCoI8-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/8MCtVqmCoI8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8MCtVqmCoI8" id="8MCtVqmCoI8" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/8MCtVqmCoI8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8MCtVqmCoI8" id="8MCtVqmCoI8-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Allow Golden Rice Now!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >The Allow Golden Rice Society video summarizing the campaign to prevent 2 million deaths per year due to Vitamin A deficiency</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Moralising Effect of the Disgust Reflex]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/12/31/disgust/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T03:55:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/12/31/disgust</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>David Pizarro</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('5YL3LT1ZvOM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5YL3LT1ZvOM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('5YL3LT1ZvOM-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/5YL3LT1ZvOM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YL3LT1ZvOM" id="5YL3LT1ZvOM" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/5YL3LT1ZvOM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YL3LT1ZvOM" id="5YL3LT1ZvOM-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">David Pizarro: The strange politics of disgust</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >What does a disgusting image have to do with how you vote? Equipped with surveys and experiments, psychologist David Pizarro demonstrates a correlation between sensitivity to disgusting cues &#8211; a photo of feces, an unpleasant odor &#8211; and moral and political conservatism.

TEDTalks is a daily video podcast of the best talks and performances from the TED Conference, where the world&#8217;s leading thinkers and doers give the talk of their lives in 18 minutes (or less). Look for talks on Technology, Entertainment and Design &#8211; plus science, business, global issues, the arts and much more.
Find closed captions and translated subtitles in many languages at http://www.ted.com/translate

Follow TED news on Twitter: http://www.twitter.com/tednews
Like TED on Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/TED

Subscribe to our channel: http://www.youtube.com/user/TEDtalksDirector</div>
</div>


<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mHhSYyvI-5k&amp;list=PLB4uoi02B2hPwxZsIP3yPmBGKxwHZ3USu&amp;index=1">Sex, Death and the Meaning of Life</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maximum Sentence for Abusive Fundamentalist Parents]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/11/04/williams-max-sentence/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-04T12:52:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/11/04/williams-max-sentence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Larry and Carri Williams adopted two</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('CNgzn47aP9g');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CNgzn47aP9g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('CNgzn47aP9g-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CNgzn47aP9g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CNgzn47aP9g" id="CNgzn47aP9g" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CNgzn47aP9g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CNgzn47aP9g" id="CNgzn47aP9g-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">The Religious Right Loves Child Spanking</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >The religious right loves to insist on corporal punishment for children and infants, even when extreme forms kill children. Glenn Beck recommends pushing children around just for the sake of it, and plenty cite the book of proverbs to whip children. More info:

Dane County pastor that recommended using rods on 2 month old infants
http://www.wkow.com/Global/story.asp?S=14291185

Parents of adopted Ethiopian girl Hana convicted of manslaughter
http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2416514/Hana-Williams-Washington-adoptive-parents-Larry-Carri-Williams-GUILTY-manslaughter.html</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Phil Zuckerman on the Basis for a Civil Society]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/11/01/zuckerman/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T00:13:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/11/01/zuckerman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Phil Zuckerman recently took part in a debate with David Marshall on whether religion or secularism is a better basis for a civil society. After <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/phil-zuckerman/adventure-in-christian-in_b_4124618.html">initially refusing to post the video online</a> because they thought Zuckerman won, the church caved and the <a href="http://vimeo.com/77532575">video is up</a>.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('u_QDJ7DOD_Y');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/u_QDJ7DOD_Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('u_QDJ7DOD_Y-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/u_QDJ7DOD_Y/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u_QDJ7DOD_Y" id="u_QDJ7DOD_Y" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/u_QDJ7DOD_Y/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u_QDJ7DOD_Y" id="u_QDJ7DOD_Y-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">The Great Debate: Marshall vs. Zuckerman (Christianity vs. Secular Humanism)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Does Christianity or secular humanism provide a better foundation for civil society? That is the question that is going to addressed between two scholars, Dr. David Marshall and Dr. Phillip Zuckerman, a Christian and an atheist.

David Marshall is the founder and director of the Kuai Mu Institute for Christianity and World Cultures, and the author of four books, including The Truth Behind the New Atheism: Responding to the Emerging Challenges to God and Christianity (Harvest House Publishers).

Phil Zuckerman is a professor of sociology and secular studies at Pitzer College in Claremont, CA. He is the author most recently of Faith No More: Why People Reject Religion (Oxford University Press, 2011) and Society Without God (NYU Press, 2008).</div>
</div>


<p>Zuckerman stuck to the facts about why largely secular post-Chrsitian societies around the world are doing better on most indicators than the most religious societies, while Marshall presented weak anecdotes of individual conversion experiences and straw men about how communists and vikings are bad people. The pastor of the church said &#8220;It just didn&#8217;t go the way we wanted it to go. We were not represented well.&#8221;</p>

<p>Zuckerman has noted that many European societies that score well on social indicators also have <a href="http://www.scribd.com/doc/170356660/Phil-Zuckerman">low rates of Chrsitian belief</a>. Only 18% of Swedes believe in heaven, 10% believe in hell and 3% believe that the Bible is the literal word of God, among the lowest rates in the world. In Denmark, women&#8217;s labour force participation doubled in the &#8217;70s and &#8217;80s, rapidly changing the model of femininity valued by young women. Social changes like these supported by neoliberal governments, including the banning of prosletyzing in schools, and the provision of free healthcare to all have quickly caused generational decline in religion as the state Lutheran church struggles to market itself.</p>

<p>Zuckerman eloquently criticised the bible belt states for high rates of divorce, teen pregnancy, sexual assault, diabetes, child abuse, unemployment and murder. He has a long history of criticising the political hypocrisy of the white evangelical power base, that claims evolution is wrong, but <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/phil-zuckerman/why-evangelicals-hate-jes_b_830237.html">tend to support policies that could be described as &#8220;Social Darwinism.&#8221;</a></p>

<blockquote><p>The results from a recent poll <a href="http://www.pewforum.org/Politics-and-Elections/Tea-Party-and-Religion.aspx">published by the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life</a> reveal what social scientists have known for a long time: White Evangelical Christians are the group least likely to support politicians or policies that reflect the actual teachings of Jesus.</p></blockquote>

<p>Zuckerman has an excellent analysis of the <a href="http://www.edge.org/conversation/why-the-gods-are-not-winning">global decline of faith</a> on Edge.org. One interesting fact about the general decline of Chrstianity in America is how gender plays a factor in mixed faith households:</p>

<blockquote><p>Rather than Amerofaith becoming deeply patriarchal as Longman thinks, it is increasingly feminine. Women church goers greatly outnumber men, who find church too dull. Here&#8217;s the kicker. Children tend to pick up their beliefs from their fathers. So, despite a vibrant evangelical youth cohort, young Americans taken as a whole are the least religious and most culturally tolerant age group in the nation.</p></blockquote>

<p>He notes that the well resourced churches are consolidating believers rather than expanding the faithful</p>

<blockquote><p>Even the megachurch phenomenon is illusory. A spiritual cross of sports stadiums with theme parks, hi-tech churches are a desperate effort to pull in and satisfy a mass-media jaded audience for whom the old sit in the pews and listen to the standard sermon and sing some old time hymns does not cut it anymore. Rather than boosting church membership, megachurches are merely consolidating it.</p></blockquote>

<p>While Zuckerman notes that he was well remunerated for travelling to take part in the professionally recorded debate, the decision of the church to initially refuse to publish the video demonstrates that content matters more than its presentation. The trend of religion being on the nose for the last hundred years will continue as churches struggle to cover up their mistakes in an age of social media, no matter how well they learn to speak with &#8216;Gen Y&#8217;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bishop of Bling Exposing Resentment of Catholicism]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/25/bishop-bling/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T09:27:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/25/bishop-bling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The pope has <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-10-23/pope-banishes-germany27s-bling-bishop-from-diocese/5041880">banished the &#8220;Bishop of Bling&#8221;</a> Franz-Peter Tebartz-van Elst over allegations of lying.</p>

<p>Franz-Peter Tebartz-van Elst announced that his diocean centre would cost 5.5 million euros in 2010, but the architect <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz-Peter_Tebartz-van_Elst">admitted that the true cost was known to be much higher from the start</a>, with plans for extravagant addons like half a million euros for art and 20,000 for a bathtub causing the project to blow out to 32 million euros. This came at a time when his staff were facing funding cuts because of a savings plan instituted a principle of austerity in the church.</p>

<p>The pope has <a href="http://michaeloloughlin.religionnews.com/2013/10/23/popes-financial-reforms/">instituted financial reforms</a> in the Vatican to encourage transparency and accountability, and to prevent money laundering. German dioceses are chafing under the new plans, which would reveal to their donors just how well-off they are.</p>

<p>As reported in the Religion News Service, German dioceses are among the world&#8217;s welthiest, and the diocese of Cologne is <a href="http://www.religionnews.com/2013/10/23/bishops-suspension-symptom-german-catholic-churchs-wealth/">richer than the Vatican</a>. By law, Germans registered as Catholics must give 8-10% of their tax revenue to the church, which gave the church $7.1 US billion in 2012. Even as over 100,000 members leave the church every year following child sex abuse scandals, the dioceses still have enormous asset reserves.</p>

<p>While the new Argentinian pope travells on a bus or in a donated 20 year old Renault his obstinate German subordinantes refuse to give up their BMWs and Audis. The previous pope took up a yearly collection of <a href="https://opentabernacle.wordpress.com/2011/05/08/popes-personal-income-200-million-annually/">$200 million US</a>, which will certainly guarantee him a comfortable life in retirement, while the new pope has opted to live in a single room in a guesthouse rather than his papal apartment.</p>

<blockquote><p>“The German Catholic Church is one of the country’s wealthiest and largest organizations and its top officials expect a certain lifestyle,” said Carsten Frerk, who has published two books on the German churches’ wealth and what he describes as their opaque financing. “But they are wary of the extent of their wealth becoming broadly known because it might lead to fewer donations.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Francis has commented that he <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/10/01/pope-francis-interview_n_4023659.html?utm_hp_ref=religion">dislikes careerist priests</a>, stating “It also happens to me that when I meet a clericalist, I suddenly become anti-clerical. Clericalism should not have anything to do with Christianity.”</p>

<p>Francis had stated in September that the Catholic Church was <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-24166434">too focussed on sexual issues</a> like homosexuality, abortion and contraception, and they must increase their focus on the poor and marginalised. This has apparently had little effect in the US, where the US Conference of Catholic Bishops <a href="http://www.dailykos.com/story/2013/10/18/1248662/-Shutdown-losers-include-Catholic-Bishops">campaigned for Republicans to introduce religious priviliges</a> into the &#8216;must pass&#8217; resolution to end the government shutdown and avert a US government default. The shutdown cost 800,000 jobs and left poor families without food stamps for weeks, and resulted in the Republican party hitting the lowest approval rating of any political party recorded by Gallup. The government shutdown over Obamacare appears to be a <a href="http://thecontributor.com/religion/how-catholic-bishops-pushed-shutdown-%E2%80%93-and-even-default-%E2%80%93-over-birth-control">long-planned offensive from the USCCB</a>, with their opposition to Obamacare <a href="http://publicreligion.org/2012/08/as-catholics-go-so-goes-the-nation/">parroted by the Romney campaign</a>.</p>

<p>http://churchandstate.org.uk/2013/10/at-any-cost-how-catholic-bishops-pushed-for-a-shutdown-and-even-a-default-over-birth-control/</p>

<p>has had issues from the US, where his statement that the Catholics had</p>

<p>http://www.faithinpubliclife.org/newsroom/press/faith-leaders-challenge-pro-life-representatives-to-end-shutdown/
http://www.religionnews.com/2013/10/08/religious-groups-feel-the-pinch-of-government-shutdown/</p>

<p>PRRI</p>

<p>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887324755104579072722223166570.html</p>

<p>http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/on-faith/wp/2013/10/04/why-gop-opposition-to-obamacare-will-hurt-hispanic-outreach/</p>

<p>http://publicreligion.org/research/2011/08/generations-at-odds/
http://publicreligion.org/research/2013/03/march-2013-religion-politics-tracking-survey/</p>

<p>In Victoria, local communities are devastated that the Uniting Church is selling off between <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-10-17/730-anglican-church-story/5029694">$32 million</a> and <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-10-11/uniting-church-puts-properties-up-for-sale-to-clear-debts/5015754">$100 million</a> worth of church properties to cover debts accumulated by the failure of Acacia College. The Church is considering selling <a href="http://www.heraldsun.com.au/leader/north/ivanhoe-east-church-on-the-market-as-uniting-church-liquidates-properties/story-fnglenug-1226741089815">56 properties</a> after they had had run up $10 million dollars in debt because of legal issues with the developer, and <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-10-18/catholic-church-considers-buying-acacia-college/4321504">unexpected infrastructure costs</a>.</p>

<p>While megachurches like Hillsong make <a href="www.heraldsun.com.au/money/money-matters/tax-office-push-for-charity-monitoring/story-fn312ws8-1225896551630">over $50 million dollars a year in tax-free profits</a>, paying their leaders more than $1.5 million a year, most small churches founded on volunteerism and support for charities have their supporter base dying off, with none of the flashy showmanship that attracts rich idiots into the Pentecostal churches.</p>

<p>Many of the parishioners were shocked to find that the churches they had been volunteering in and donating to for years, and for some, decades, were soon to be sold off. This is not the first time that local churches have been asked to bear the brunt of financial losses after a central church body loses millions. The Sydney Anglican church lost over $100 million by <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/national/millions-wiped-out-by-church-gambles-20090609-c29m.html">borrowing money to invest in shares before the GFC in 2009</a>, leading it to ask parishioners to take part in a planned but now unfunded evangelical sabotage of the Bible Society&#8217;s Jesus All About Life campaign. In February the Los Angeles Catholic diocese, after having paid $660 million dollars to settle more than 500 child sexual abuse cases <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/deaconsbench/2013/02/los-angeles-considering-capital-campaign-to-raise-200-million/">asked their parishioners for $200 million</a> for &#8220;repair and upkeep of our parish churches and schools.&#8221; This is after they had already managed to misappropriate $115 million from a grave maintenance fund <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/wwjtd/2013/02/the-los-angeles-diocese-found-some-new-funds/">into paying off child sexual assault victims</a>, without the knowledge or consent of the donors.</p>

<p>Most religionists would be completely shocked to find that the religion they&#8217;ve been trying to follow is completely different to the religion that their leaders use to gain money and power.</p>

<h3>Wider resentment of Prosperity Theology</h3>

<p>While in Germany the revelation of lying, selfish preachers is a scandal, in the US it&#8217;s nothing new. Peter Popoff was making $4 million a year when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Popoff">James Randi exposed him as a fraud</a>, and Bobby Tilton may have made as much as $80 million a year when he was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Tilton">found to be dumping the prayer requests his ministry took donations for</a>. The new Reality TV show Preachers of LA shows the glitzy and glamorous lives of Ferrari and Bentley driving pastors who fully embrace Prosperity Theology. Bishop Ron Gibson, with whom he had a child out of wedlock, <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/10406467/Meet-the-real-bishops-of-bling-the-Californian-preachers-of-prosperity-theology.html">boasts that fancy cars are not just for materialistic rappers</a></p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;P Diddy and Jay-Z - they&#8217;re not the only ones who should be driving Ferraris and living in large houses,&#8221; he says to the camera as he compares himself to secular celebrities. To whoops from his congregation, he notes: &#8220;You see my bling, you see my Bentley, you see my glory but you don&#8217;t see my story.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Liquid error: undefined method `[]&#8217; for nil:NilClass</p>

<p>Baptist Pastors have a long history of playing their parishioners for mugs. Mark Barclay, a self proclaimed &#8220;Preacher of Righteousness&#8221; recently asked his followers for $79,000 for a paint job on his private jet, saying &#8221;<a href="http://www.christianpost.com/news/televangelist-asks-followers-for-79k-to-do-paint-job-on-lords-jet-he-bought-last-year-98435/">the airplane does belong to Him [God] and not me and is used for His ministry and not personal use</a>.&#8221; He had the gall to cite Jesus&#8217;s words &#8220;do not store up treasures for yourself&#8221; to justify why his members should &#8220;sow&#8221; offerings for his million dollar jet.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s a growing tide of criticism of prosperity theology. In a statement, Professor Stanley Hauerwas denounced the $1.7 million home of pastor Steve Furtick saying &#8220;It&#8217;s just vulgar. It&#8217;s an offense to the Gospel.&#8221; A number of media outlets are criticising pastors with private jets in <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2220833/Laughing-private-jet--93m-pastor-accused-exploiting-British-worshippers.html">Nigeria</a> and <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/andersonantunes/2013/01/17/the-richest-pastors-in-brazil/">Brazil</a>. A pastor who promised parishioners a miraculous new car if they would donate $52,000 for new blades for his private helicopter has lashed out at the media for publicizing the campaign, but not before widespread denunciation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Dusty Smith takes the piss out of the Preachers of LA</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('WMwLFLbRNu0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/WMwLFLbRNu0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('WMwLFLbRNu0-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/WMwLFLbRNu0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WMwLFLbRNu0" id="WMwLFLbRNu0" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/WMwLFLbRNu0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WMwLFLbRNu0" id="WMwLFLbRNu0-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Preachers Of L.A. - Scummiest Reality Show Ever</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >You gotta see The Oxygen Networks new reality show, Preachers of L.A. It&#8217;s going to be life changing!

The original trailer for this show can e found here. http://youtu.be/Ml8bQDnnkKk

If you like my work, please support it by picking up your awesome Tee&#8217;s from http://www.CultofDusty.com ! Thanks a lot. It really helps.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Masking race politics in the southern strategy]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/16/southern-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T17:19:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/16/southern-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('X_8E3ENrKrQ');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/X_8E3ENrKrQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('X_8E3ENrKrQ-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/X_8E3ENrKrQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X_8E3ENrKrQ" id="X_8E3ENrKrQ" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/X_8E3ENrKrQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X_8E3ENrKrQ" id="X_8E3ENrKrQ-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Exclusive: Lee Atwater&#8217;s Infamous 1981 Interview on the Southern Strategy</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >In 1981, the legendarily brutal campaign consultant Lee Atwater, after a decade as South Carolina&#8217;s most effective Republican operative, was working in Ronald Reagan&#8217;s White House when he was interviewed by Alexander Lamis, a political scientist at Case Western Reserve University. 

In this audio, made public for the first time ever, Atwater lays out how Republicans can win the vote of racists without sounding racist themselves. Listen to the full audio and read Rick Perlstein&#8217;s analysis here: http://tnat.in/ffHKS</div>
</div>


<p>It has become, for liberals and leftists enraged by the way Republicans never suffer the consequences for turning electoral politics into a cesspool, a kind of smoking gun. The late, legendarily brutal campaign consultant Lee Atwater explains how Republicans can win the vote of racists without sounding racist themselves:
 
You start out in 1954 by saying, “Nigger, nigger, nigger.” By 1968 you can’t say “nigger”—that hurts you, backfires. So you say stuff like, uh, forced busing, states’ rights, and all that stuff, and you’re getting so abstract. Now, you’re talking about cutting taxes, and all these things you’re talking about are totally economic things and a byproduct of them is, blacks get hurt worse than whites.… “We want to cut this,” is much more abstract than even the busing thing, uh, and a hell of a lot more abstract than “Nigger, nigger.”
 
Now, the same indefatigable researcher who brought us Mitt Romney’s “47 percent” remarks, James Carter IV, has dug up the entire forty-two-minute interview from which that quote derives. Here, The Nation publishes it in its entirety for the very first time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pat Robertson the Nutritionist Finds Low-Carb Diet Violates God's Principles]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/12/robertson-nutrition/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T19:24:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/12/robertson-nutrition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pat Robertson finds that a low-carb diet is a violation of God&#8217;s principles</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('xttOoQGtCIQ');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/xttOoQGtCIQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('xttOoQGtCIQ-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/xttOoQGtCIQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xttOoQGtCIQ" id="xttOoQGtCIQ" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/xttOoQGtCIQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xttOoQGtCIQ" id="xttOoQGtCIQ-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Robertson: Low-Carb Diet Violates God&#8217;s Principles</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/pat-robertson-reveals-how-low-carb-diets-violate-gods-principles-halal-foods-fund-terrorism
Pat Robertson says a low-carb diet &#8220;violates the principles that God set down&#8221;</div>
</div>


<p>He also believes that Halal meat funds terrorism</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('8d-jIDJzFo4');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/8d-jIDJzFo4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('8d-jIDJzFo4-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/8d-jIDJzFo4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8d-jIDJzFo4" id="8d-jIDJzFo4" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/8d-jIDJzFo4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8d-jIDJzFo4" id="8d-jIDJzFo4-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Robertson: Halal Foods Fund Terrorism</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/pat-robertson-reveals-how-low-carb-diets-violate-gods-principles-halal-foods-fund-terrorism
Pat Robertson claims if you buy halal foods, you are supporting Islamic extremists</div>
</div>


<p>Has a lot in common with this lady</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('6_1SFf8t-ko');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/6_1SFf8t-ko&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('6_1SFf8t-ko-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/6_1SFf8t-ko/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6_1SFf8t-ko" id="6_1SFf8t-ko" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/6_1SFf8t-ko/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6_1SFf8t-ko" id="6_1SFf8t-ko-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">7News - &#8216;Australia&#8217;s Sarah Palin&#8217;</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >FIRST ON 7: Stephanie Banister &#8211; the mother accused of an anti-Muslim contamination scare at a Logan shopping centre &#8211; will stand as a One Nation candidate. Erin Edwards reports.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Phil Plait Outraged at Spherist Bias]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/12/plait-spherist/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T17:40:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/12/plait-spherist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently the LA Times has made waves with news that they <a href="http://www.latimes.com/opinion/opinion-la/la-ol-climate-change-letters-20131008,0,871615.story">censor untrue assertions from their opinion pages</a>. Astronomer Phil Plait writes to the LA Times to complain about their blatant spherist bias, and their failure to <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/bad_astronomy/2013/10/10/an_open_letter_to_the_l_a_times_editors.html">teach the controversy on the flattness of the earth</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Dear L.A. Times Editors:
It has come to my attention that you will no longer be publishing letters to the editor from Flat-Earthers. This is an outrage, and shows your obvious spherist bias.</p>

<p>By taking the stance that the Earth is round, you are going against six thousand years of obvious truth. Look around you! Do you see the world curving down, away from you? Of course not. And the idea that we live on a thin skin of crust outside a giant sea of molten rock is simply ridiculous. If that were true, the ground would be warmer than the air above it! Duh.</p>

<p>The claim of a scientific consensus is another orbist lie. Have you not seen the Global Flattening Petition Project, which is signed by thousands of scientists* who know the true unbent shape of our planet? And don’t forget Geocentrismgate, where scientists’ emails revealed they say “The Moon rises at 8:30 tonight,” showing they clearly have been lying about heliocentrism, too.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tony Abbott Messes With ACT's Marriage Laws]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/11/abbott-marriage-equality/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T18:30:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/11/abbott-marriage-equality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When Tony Abbott was asked about his views on same sex marriage in the leader&#8217;s debate, he replied with this:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;It&#8217;s a very important issue. I know how important an issue it is. It&#8217;s not the only important issue and I&#8217;ve got to say as far as an incoming Coalition government is concerned, the priority will be on things like reducing cost-of-living pressure and increasing job security.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('vj9Btd0l6Cw');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/vj9Btd0l6Cw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('vj9Btd0l6Cw-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/vj9Btd0l6Cw/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vj9Btd0l6Cw" id="vj9Btd0l6Cw" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/vj9Btd0l6Cw/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vj9Btd0l6Cw" id="vj9Btd0l6Cw-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Kevin Rudd and Tony Abbott debate same-sex marriage</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Australian prime minister Kevin Rudd and his election opponent Tony Abbott debate same-sex marriage - with Mr Rudd committing to a bill on the issue within 100 days of re-election.

Read more  http //www.channel4.com/news/australia-election-debate-kevin-rudd-tony-abbott-marriage

Sign up for Snowmail, your daily preview of what is on Channel 4 News, sent straight to your inbox, here  http //mailing.channel4.com/public/snowmail/remotebox.jsp

Missed Channel 4 News? Catch up on the last seven days here  http //www.channel4.com/news/catch-up/

Channel 4 News weather forecast, with Liam Dutton  http //www.channel4.com/weather/

All the latest blog posts from the Channel 4 News on-screen talent  http //blogs.channel4.com/news/</div>
</div>


<p>That must have been a &#8220;non-core&#8221; promise, given that George Brandis is almost straight away <a href="http://www.canberratimes.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/samesex-marriage-law-high-court-challenge-confirmed-20131010-2vaqe.html">working to overrule a law on same sex marriage the ACT wants to bring in</a>.
George Brandis has claimed that the ACT Bill would undermine the &#8216;well-established position&#8217; of &#8216;nationally consistent marriage laws.&#8217; The Tasmanian Law Reform commission suggests that this is possibly not the case, with a history of states passing their own marriage laws, so it&#8217;s unknown if the <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-10-10/report-unable-to-predict-smooth-path-for-gay-marriage-laws/5013934">ACT bill will be found constitutional</a>. Politifact rates Brandis&#8217;s statement <a href="http://www.politifact.com.au/truth-o-meter/statements/2013/oct/11/george-brandis/ACT-same-sex-marriage-equality-brandis/">as half true</a>.</p>

<p>While Abbott noted in the debate that same sex marriage was an &#8220;important&#8221; issue for his lesbian sister, his view on the issue has not &#8220;evolved&#8221; but goes against the majority of the Australian population. Figures from the ABC&#8217;s Vote Compass survey of 422,000 respondents show that the majority of Australians <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-08-29/vote-compass-gay-marriage-euthanasia-abortion/4918494">support same sex marriage, and 70% of those under 34 do</a>. This is in line with previous opinion polls finding that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recognition_of_same-sex_unions_in_Australia#Public_opinion_polls">about 60% of the country now supports same sex marriage</a>.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s an old quote &#8220;every time you hear an ambulance siren, an opponent of gay rights is leaving the world or a supporter is entering it&#8221;. In reality, with NZ and the UK passing gay marriage laws it&#8217;s already a lost argument. The UK law will come into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage_in_the_United_Kingdom">effect in 2014</a>, I don&#8217;t think the Christian lobby can hold the issue back that much longer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Common Cognitive Mistakes and How to Prevent Them]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/06/cognitive-mistakes/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-06T12:00:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/10/06/cognitive-mistakes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good post on the <a href="http://blog.bufferapp.com/thinking-mistakes-8-common-mistakes-in-how-we-think-and-how-to-avoid-them">Buffer blog on cognitive errors</a>. There&#8217;s good discussion of Dan Ariely&#8217;s work on anchoring and pricing, as well as this classic about the conjuction fallacy:</p>

<blockquote><p>In 1983 Kahneman and Tversky tested how illogical human thinking is by describing the following imaginary person:</p>

<blockquote><p>Linda is thirty-one years old, single, outspoken, and very bright. She majored in philosophy. As a student, she was deeply concerned with issues of discrimination and social justice, and also participated in antinuclear demonstrations.</p></blockquote>

<p>The researchers asked people to read this description, and then asked them to answer this question:</p>

<p>Which alternative is more probable?</p>

<ol>
<li>Linda is a bank teller.</li>
<li>Linda is a bank teller and is active in the feminist movement.
Here’s where it can get a bit tricky to understand (at least, it did for me!)—If answer #2 is true, #1 is also true. This means that #2 cannot be the answer to the question of probability.</li>
</ol>


<p>Unfortunately, few of us realize this, because we’re so overcome by the more detailed description of #2. Plus, as the earlier quote pointed out, stereotypes are so deeply ingrained in our minds that subconsciously apply them to others.</p>

<p>Roughly 85% of people chose option #2 as the answer. A simple choice of words can change everything.</p></blockquote>

<p>Adding more detail or extra assumptions can make an event seem more plausible, even though the event necessarily becomes less probable. Kahneman and Tversky tried <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/ji/conjunction_fallacy/">another experiment on probabilities</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Consider a regular six-sided die with four green faces and two red faces.  The die will be rolled 20 times and the sequences of greens (G) and reds (R) will be recorded.  You are asked to select one sequence, from a set of three, and you will win $25 if the sequence you chose appears on successive rolls of the die.  Please check the sequence of greens and reds on which you prefer to bet.</p>

<ol>
<li>RGRRR</li>
<li>GRGRRR</li>
<li>GRRRRR</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>65% of respondents chose option 2 as the most likely bet, as it matches the colours of the 6 sides, even though the shorter sequence 1 requires less correct rolls to complete.</p>

<p>Another example of the conjunction fallacy</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>&#8220;A complete suspension of diplomatic relations between the USA and the Soviet Union, sometime in 1983.&#8221;</li>
<li>&#8220;A Russian invasion of Poland, and a complete suspension of diplomatic relations between the USA and the Soviet Union, sometime in 1983.&#8221;</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Most respondents rate 2 as more likely than 1, even though 2 would necessarily entail 1, and it would be possible to have a complete suspension of diplomatic relations between the USA and USSR without invasion of any country, let alone Poland specifically.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/lg/the_affect_heuristic/">another example</a>, people&#8217;s perception</p>

<blockquote><p>Yamagishi (1997) showed that subjects judged a disease as more dangerous when it was described as killing 1,286 people out of every 10,000, versus a disease that was 24.14% likely to be fatal.  Apparently the mental image of a thousand dead bodies is much more alarming, compared to a single person who&#8217;s more likely to survive than not.</p>

<p>But wait, it gets worse.</p>

<p>Suppose an airport must decide whether to spend money to purchase some new equipment, while critics argue that the money should be spent on other aspects of airport safety.  Slovic et. al. (2002) presented two groups of subjects with the arguments for and against purchasing the equipment, with a response scale ranging from 0 (would not support at all) to 20 (very strong support).  One group saw the measure described as saving 150 lives.  The other group saw the measure described as saving 98% of 150 lives.  The hypothesis motivating the experiment was that saving 150 lives sounds vaguely good—is that a lot? a little?—while saving 98% of something is clearly very good because 98% is so close to the upper bound of the percentage scale.  Lo and behold, saving 150 lives had mean support of 10.4, while saving 98% of 150 lives had mean support of 13.6.</p></blockquote>

<p>If you have the time, consider how you&#8217;d approach a problem like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Hall_problem">Monty Hall problem</a> or this classic problem on breast cancer screening:</p>

<blockquote><p>1% of women at age forty who participate in routine screening have breast cancer.  80% of women with breast cancer will get positive mammographies.  9.6% of women without breast cancer will also get positive mammographies.  A woman in this age group had a positive mammography in a routine screening.  What is the probability that she actually has breast cancer?</p></blockquote>

<p>While most doctors give the intuitive answer of 80%, working though with Baysean logic gives the answer of 7.8%. Yudowsky has a <a href="http://yudkowsky.net/rational/bayes">long explanation</a> of the answer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
