<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></title>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//"/>
  <updated>2013-08-14T02:58:01+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://nsewell.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Failure of the Western Gospel]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/19/failure-of-the-western-gospel/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T12:57:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/19/failure-of-the-western-gospel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Christians in the West have a habit of making all the depictions of biblical figures white. This is painfully evident in The Bible series on the History Channel. The series starts its Eurocentric presentation of Jewish scriptures with Adam and Eve as white supermodels:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/adam-eve.jpg" alt="Adam and Eve as white supermodels" /></p>

<p>At least they figured out that &#8220;forbidden fruit&#8221; is a fig, long believed to be an aphrodisiac in the Middle East. The producers also cast Mohamen Mehdi Ouazanni as Satan, someone <a href="http://www.news.com.au/entertainment/television/barack-obama-lookalike-mohamen-mehdi-ouazanni-cast-as-satan-in-the-bible/story-e6frfmyi-1226600220510">many have commented has a resemblence to Barak Obama</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/satan-obama.jpg" alt="Barack Obama looks like Satan" /></p>

<p>While Jesus is shown as distinctively Causasian, Samson was cast as a black actor leading Reverend Wil Gafney to call the series <a href="http://www.wilgafney.com/2013/03/11/black-samson-white-women-on-the-history-channel">&#8220;a continuation of slave-holding racist exegesis.&#8221;</a> The December 2002 cover of Popular Mechanics featured a <a href="http://www.popularmechanics.com/science/health/forensics/1282186">reconstruction of the faces of males from around the time of Jesus</a>. The New Testament says that Jesus disappeared into crowds, and if Jesus looked like other men of the time this is what he would have looked like:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/black-jesus-face.jpg" alt="Black Jesus by Popular Mechanics" /></p>

<p>The Irish producer Roma Downey chose to cast herself as Mary the mother of Jesus, and chose to give the role of Jesus of Nazareth to a similarly white skinned Portugese actor Diogo Morgado:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/white-jesus.jpg" alt="White Jesus" /></p>

<p>If Jesus ever had hair this long, he&#8217;d probably get it stuck in his vice. Europeans love to show Jesus with long hair, despite Paul&#8217;s teaching in 1 Corinthians 11:14 clearly specifying &#8220;Does not nature itself teach you that if a man has long hair, it is a disgrace for him&#8221;. In fact, many contemporary scholars have noted that the Corinthian church existed at a time when male prostitutes had longer hair than other men to make them stand out as homosexuals. Despite this, modern evangelicals have remoulded Orthodox representations of Jesus into a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_movement">New Age white hippie</a>.</p>

<p>But this isn&#8217;t the only way that Westerners present biblical stories specifically moulded to their target audience, against the grain of what the bible actually says. Western individualists love to read bible passages as written specifically for them, ignoring the original audience and context. For most of the history of Christianity, lay people did not read scriputre themselves, they had the bible read in a corporate context. It wasn&#8217;t until 1455 that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gutenberg_Bible">Johannes Gutenberg mass produced 180 bibles</a> and until 1561 that John Knox demanded universal education.</p>

<p>Now Americans complain that while most <a href="http://global.christianpost.com/news/dr-lamar-vest-on-why-owning-seven-bibles-is-not-enough-70608/">own four to seven bibles they hardly ever get time to read them</a>. Instead they&#8217;ll be encouraged to read the bible just <a href="http://au.christiantoday.com/article/Daily-Bible-reading-best-predictor-of-spiritual-growth/13987.htm">25 words at a time</a>. Not only are Westerners time-poor, they all too often seek a <a href="http://rachelheldevans.com/blog/bible-not-into-you">&#8220;reaffirmation of the individualistic, me-centered, and consumerist tendencies of American religious culture.&#8221;</a> Many megachurches are happy to give them a &#8220;seeker friendly&#8221; doctrine written by and for modern American individualists:</p>

<blockquote><p>Passages that were originally written for groups of people, and intended to be read and applied in a community setting (the nation of Israel, the various early churches, the first followers of Jesus), have been manipulated to communicate a personal, individual message&#8230;</p>

<p>We see this everywhere: in worship set lists that focus exclusively on individual worship, individual sin, and individual connection to God; in desk calendars that turn Jeremiah 29:11 (“For I know the plans I have for you, says the Lord…”)  into a personal promise; in the disproportionate emphasis in our churches on personal Bible study, personal prayer, and one’s “personal walk with God.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Worse, publishers responding to people who like the sound of their own names will &#8220;personalize&#8221; the bible for them, massaging scripture into an ego stoking circlejerk. Isiah 53 no longer reads &#8220;he was pierced for <strong>our</strong> transgressions&#8221; but can be made to say &#8220;he was pierced for <strong>Rachel&#8217;s</strong> transgressions. He was crushed for <strong>Rachel&#8217;s</strong> iniquities.&#8221; The website lets you put in literally any name at all:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/dahmer.jpg" alt="The bible according to Jeffrey Dahmer" /></p>

<h3>It ain&#8217;t in the bible, but it outta be</h3>

<p>This culture is happy to change the bible not only to suit the emotional desires of consumerists but also to make it suit contemporary social and political needs. Often Jesus is not presented as a redeemer saving individuals into a community, but is presented as a &#8220;package deal&#8221; that will provide for individual emotional and physical wants and needs, so long as they conform to the social and political aims of the church of the day.</p>

<p>Making the message &#8220;culturally relevant&#8221; can lead to presenting cultural idiosyncrasies along with religious doctrines until the two become confused. In one study, 10% of Americans thought that <a href="http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2007/0704.balmer.html">Noah&#8217;s wife was Joan of Arc, and two thirds thought Billy Graham preached the Sermon on the Mount</a>. The most popular &#8220;bible verse&#8221; in America the Benjamin Franklin quote is &#8220;God helps those who help themselves.&#8221; When challenged on the whether there is a any substantiation to claimed biblical backing of modern ideas, many Christians will fall back to the old line &#8220;well it ain&#8217;t in the bible, but it outta be&#8221;. Other common platitudes like &#8220;When God closes a door he opens a window&#8221; might give comfort to those struggling with flatulence, but are similarly unscriptural.</p>

<p>Unfortunately many Christians debate back and forward whether the <a href="http://www.myobamayear.com/2013/04/the-good-samaritan/">good Samaritan was a Democrat or a Republican</a>, missing the futitlity of massaging a 2000 year old religious parable into modern political doctrine. And yet this is exactly what politicians do, with to one of the best known quotes of Jesus saying &#8220;the poor you will always have among you&#8221; being frequently <a href="www.smh.com.au/opinion/bible-bashing-the-homeless-abbott-style-20100215-o2tj.html">used to oppose social justice initiatives on financial grounds</a> despite the fact the writers of the gospels place Jesus saying it in the house of <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matt26.6-13;mark14.3-9&amp;version=NET">Simon the leper</a> or with <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=jn12.1-8&amp;version=NET">Lazarus, who he raised from the dead</a>.</p>

<h3>Prosperity theology</h3>

<p>http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2013/06/19/texas-pastor-donate-to-fix-my-helicopter-and-get-a-new-car-from-god/
http://www.christianpost.com/news/televangelist-asks-followers-for-79k-to-do-paint-job-on-lords-jet-he-bought-last-year-98435/</p>

<h3>God as husband</h3>

<p>Ultimately many Christians don&#8217;t base their views of their god on the bible, viewing the bible through the lens of the culture they&#8217;re in, which is why their god&#8217;s actions and character reflect their own personal desires and perferences. When one&#8217;s understanding of the Christian God is grounded in pre-existing cultural and social assumptions, statements like this make sense:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/god-husband.jpg" alt="God as husband" /></p>

<p>This &#8220;deal&#8221; is not the gospel of Christianity, it&#8217;s a <a href="http://ajoyfulvapour.tumblr.com/post/45499852946/this-is-a-load-of-crap-where-is-its-scriptual">load of crap, and a lie, and a load of bollocks</a>. If they don&#8217;t get these stupid ideas from the bible, where do they get them from? There is a widespread cultural assumption that &#8220;everyone knows&#8221; that god wants people to marry &#8220;the one&#8221; for them. Many Christians are happy to play into cultural anxieties about love, sex and singleness to present marriage as part of the &#8220;package deal&#8221; of Christianity. Dagmar Herzog describes the American religious right as pushing a regressive social agenda by painting a rosy picture of marriage, and building on the insecurities of sexual inexperience in youth:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('CYVicYHNrAA');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CYVicYHNrAA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('CYVicYHNrAA-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CYVicYHNrAA/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CYVicYHNrAA" id="CYVicYHNrAA" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/CYVicYHNrAA/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CYVicYHNrAA" id="CYVicYHNrAA-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">&#8216;Soulgasms&#8217; and the War on Masturbation</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Complete videos at: http://fora.tv/2008/11/17/Power__Sex_Americas_War_on_Sexual_Rights

Author Dagmar Herzog examines the efforts of religious conservatives to influence sexual culture in the U.S. during the Bush Administration. Herzog claims widespread increases in religion-themed sex education, therapy, and medical research as examples.

&#8212;&#8211;

Has the conservative agenda come to dominate the national and international conversation on sexual rights?

Obama&#8217;s victory and the vote against abortion bans in Colorado and South Dakota brought some sexual rights back from the edge of a political precipice, but others remain in the balance.

Join scholars, journalists, and policy makers to talk about how we can help the new administration change policies and reframe national and international thinking on sexual rights.

Participants include Dagmar Herzog, author of Sex in Crisis: The New Sexual Revolution and the Future of American Politics and Professor of History, Lynn Paltrow, Executive Director of National Advocates for Pregnant Women, Nation columnist Katha Pollitt, and Faye Wattleton, Director of the Center for the Advancement of Women.

Discussant: Rosalind Petchesky, author of Sexuality, Health and Human Rights and Distinguished Professor of Political Science. Moderated by Michelle Fine, Distinguished Professor of Psychology at the Graduate Center, CUNY - City University of New York

Dagmar Herzog is a Professor of History at the Graduate Center, CUNY, where she focuses on modern European history, the history of sexuality, and the history of the religion. She has written three books, Sex after Fascism: Memory and Morality in Twentieth-Century Germany; Intimacy and Exclusion: Religious Politics in Pre-Revolutionary Bade; and, most recently, Sex in Crisis: The New Sexual Revolution and the Future of American Politics.  In addition to her books, she has edited or co-edited four volumes and has published numerous academic articles on the history of sexuality.</div>
</div>


<p>The Materialistic Western culture is built on functional saviours. Shampoo is sold to people by telling them that unclean hair makes them undesirable, then promising to make them beautiful if they buy more product. Targetting this culture with &#8220;seeker friendly&#8221; material often means presenting a relationship Jesus as a functional saviour, a means to an end for the individual, rather than an end in and of itself. &#8220;The most important relationship you can have &#8211; one that will make you a better husband and father &#8211; is a relationship with God&#8221; reads an altar call in one <a href="http://www.everystudent.com/features/wolves.html">mendacious promise of long lasting and happy marriages</a>. Another promises &#8221;<a href="http://www.everystudent.com/features/marriage.html">hope for a lasting marriage</a>&#8221; if only one accepts Jesus. Others offer Jesus as a way for <a href="http://www.everystudent.com/wires/toxic.html">men</a> and <a href="http://www.everystudent.com/wires/jenniferm.html">women</a> to stop looking at porn. People accepting these altar calls and praying their sinner&#8217;s prayers will never know what they&#8217;ve accepted unless they read the bible to understand what is actually in it, and what &#8220;outta be&#8221;.</p>

<h3>Myths and misinformation pushing shame and intimidation</h3>

<p>The relationships altar call comes after two and a half A4 pages of bullshit about how &#8220;Waiting to have sex with my wife will mean better sex in my marriage.&#8221; It launches into all the standard canards Christians have been told to believe &#8220;the more I bond with other girls, the less I&#8217;ll be able to bond with my future wife. It&#8217;s like a piece of scotch tape &#8211; the more you use it on different surfaces, the less it sticks to things.&#8221; When entire mission strategies are built around ignorance on sex and relationships, Christians will do anything in their power to promote misinformation. Because they are offering Chrsitianity as a solution to problems of their own making.</p>

<p>Abstinance only sex education programs reinforce ignorance in 30% of United States public schools. They <a href="http://www.siecus.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Page.ViewPage&amp;PageID=1199">teach canards like</a> “Condoms can never protect someone from the emotional problems that can result from multiple sexual partners and premature sexual activity.” And “AIDS can be transmitted by skin-to-skin contact.” They discourage the responsible use of barrier methods like condoms, teaching that “The only safe sex is in a marriage relationship where a man and a woman are faithful to each other for life.”</p>

<p>These programs not only promote the idea that premarital sex has risks, but demonises it as permanantly scarring. “If [a girl] has been involved in sexual activity…sexually, she is no longer a virgin, she is no longer pure, unspoiled, fresh&#8221; they teach. They warn that “The consequences of pre-marital sex include “guilt, disappointment, worry, depression, sadness, loneliness, and loss of self-esteem.” They warn 6th grade children &#8220;Going on this ride could change your life forever, result in poverty, heartache, disease, and even DEATH.” It goes on to say that many “will board this ride and come out losers.” The manual goads “did you know that sexual activity outside of the commitment of marriage could put YOUR FUTURE at risk?”</p>

<p>If you don&#8217;t believe that they teach children that they&#8217;ll die, watch this:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('k2h6CrIOrKg');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/k2h6CrIOrKg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('k2h6CrIOrKg-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/k2h6CrIOrKg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k2h6CrIOrKg" id="k2h6CrIOrKg" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/k2h6CrIOrKg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k2h6CrIOrKg" id="k2h6CrIOrKg-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Sex Before Marriage? PREPARE TO DIE!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Kid at 1:40 just had his day ruined.</div>
</div>


<p>These teachings encourage a culture of shame and permanent condemnation. In a survey, when researchers dropped a live cockroach into orange juice, then removed the cockroach and sterilised the juice, <a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com.au/2013/02/the-psychology-of-christian-purity.html">the majority of participants wouldn&#8217;t drink it</a>. Paul Rozin, author of the study also found that <a href="http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2005-10-27/entertainment/0510260352_1_disgusting-paul-rozin-important-part">40% of participants would refuse to eat poo-shaped chocolate, or drink juice from a brand-new bedpan</a>. Even when people know that disgusting looking food is safe to eat, emotionally, many refuse. While many sins that the bible speaks against are presented as mistakes, conservative evangelicals always talk about sexual integrity in terms of purity. They encourage the view that anyone who isn&#8217;t a virgin is permanantly broken, corrupted, contaminated and that they cannot make themselves clean again.</p>

<h3>The overreach and failure of the purity doctrine</h3>

<p>Demonising pre-marital sex as permanantly scarring and unforgivable has created a culture in which people are afraid even to date. &#8220;There is no condom for the human heart&#8221; teach the fear mongers. They preach not only that virginity is the most important gift a girl can give her husband, but that they should be &#8220;emotional virgins&#8221; and not <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2011/09/love-virginity.html">&#8220;give away pieces of their heart.&#8221;</a> This is bullshit. And yet, it has almost lured a <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2012/10/what-i-learned-from-joshua-harris.html">whole generation out of dating until they are sure they can marry</a>. This hooks into the intuition that &#8220;everyone knows&#8221; that God will provide them with &#8220;the one&#8221;, which &#8220;outta be&#8221; in the bible there somewhere. Single Christian women who spend the last decade in the purity culture suddenly find themselves <a href="http://sydneyanglicans.net/life/daytoday/single_christian_female_30">ostracised and isolated as church ministries direct all their 30+ ministries to families</a>.</p>

<p>Many women have given up on wearing purity rings. For some, it&#8217;s because they <a href="http://gracefortheroad.com/2012/02/03/idontwait/">feel complete in their relationship with Jesus, and aren&#8217;t &#8220;waiting&#8221; anymore</a></p>

<blockquote><p>There are a lot of girls out there who don’t know who God is anymore – the God of their youth group years just isn’t working out. Back then, that God said to wait for sex until they are married, until He brings the right man along for a husband. They signed a card and put it on the altar and pledged to wait&#8230;</p>

<p>Some of them have prayed their whole lives for a husband, and he hasn’t shown up. They’ve heard the advice to “be the woman God made you to be, focus on that, and then the husband will come.” They’ve read “Lady in Waiting,” gotten super involved in church and honed their domestic skills.</p>

<p>More than a decade ago, a youth leader handed them a photocopied poem in Sunday School written to them from “God” that said, “The reason you don’t have anyone yet is because you’re not fully satisfied in Me. You have to be satisfied with Me and then when you least expect it, I’ll bring you the person I meant for you.”</p>

<p>&#8230;Many of them – if they’re honest – will tell you that time has passed, and it’s wrecking their view of God.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others have given up on the culture of bullying and intimidation that <a href="http://sexetc.org/info-center/post/why-i-stopped-wearing-a-purity-ring/">accompanies the purity culture</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Originally, when I made the commitment to wait until marriage, I really only saw my ring as a symbol of how personally valuable my virginity was to me. However, after I saw how readily my peers bullied and mocked girls who they thought were sexually active, my ring seemed like more of a constant reminder of how dirty and useless people might think I was if I wasn’t a virgin anymore.</p></blockquote>

<p>For some, it&#8217;s the knowledge that <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1802108/">95% of Americans have sex before marriage</a>, or that <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2768056/">Five years after taking a virginity pledge, 82% of pledgers denied having ever pledged</a>. Others note that even in Southern Baptist churches <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3156853/">70% of engaged Christians quietly have sex before marrying</a>. Many women who hit this inevitable conclusion are finding the courage to speak out about the <a href="http://www.prodigalmagazine.com/the-day-i-turned-in-my-v-card/">deep and long lasting damage of the purity culture</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> I broke a barrier and gave up an idea I’d held onto as a “Good Christian Girl” for a long, long time. If you grew up in American Christian culture, you know that a statement like mine is one of the most life changing, socially desolating, parentally disappointing pronouncements you can make. Especially if you’re a girl.</p>

<p> But I don’t care anymore; I’m done with virginity.</p>

<p> I’m done with that word and that idea. I’m done defining myself, my past and my future, in terms of who’s what has been where, or hasn’t. I’m done with stories for virgins and non-virgins, promises and praises, and sentiments of “restoration” that just push forward bulldozer loads of this horrible twisted shame.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others are speaking out for those who have <a href="http://deeperstory.com/i-am-damaged-goods/">been damaged by the notion that their sexual past is keeping them back from being a Christian</a></p>

<blockquote><p> I was nineteen years old and crazy in love with Jesus when that preacher told an auditorium I was “damaged goods” because of my sexual past. He was making every effort to encourage this crowd of young adults to “stay pure for marriage.” He was passionate, yes, well-intentioned, and he was a good speaker, very convincing indeed.</p>

<p> And he stood up there and shamed me, over and over and over again.</p>

<p> Oh, he didn’t call me up to the front and name me. But he stood up there and talked about me with such disgust, like I couldn’t be in that real-life crowd of young people worshipping in that church. I felt spotlighted and singled out amongst the holy, surely my red face announced my guilt to every one&#8230;</p>

<p> And so here, now, I’ll stand up and say it, the way I wish someone had said it to me fifteen years ago when I was sitting in that packed auditorium with my heart racing, wrists aching, eyes stinging, drowning and silenced by the imposition of shame masquerading as ashes of repentance:</p>

<p> “So, you had sex before you were married.</p>

<p> It’s okay.</p>

<p> Really. It’s okay.</p>

<p> There is no shame in Christ’s love. Let him without sin cast the first stone. You are more than your virginity – or lack thereof – and more than your sexual past.</p></blockquote>

<p>Others who kept their virginity are also <a href="http://www.elizabethesther.com/2013/01/virginity-new-improved.html">pushing back on the purity culture that teaches that non-sexual relationships are as dangerous as sexual ones</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> Yes, I was a virgin on my wedding day. Then again, I was only 20. Yes, remaining a virgin until my wedding day saved me from some romantic heartbreak. Then again, I’ve had other heartbreaks. Yes, chastity is special. Then again, so are lots of virtues. Except, as a 20 year old bride, I thought virginity was extra-extra special and would win me lots of special prizes like: a happily ever after marriage.</p>

<p> It took me a long time to realize I idolized virginity. I kept saying I was just promoting virtue and chastity and purity! Nothing wrong with pushing purity, right? Nothing wrong with Being Good!</p>

<p> Like other Christians, I talked about the “sacrifice” of abstinence. There were princess-themed books about saving our first kiss. Some of us wore purity rings and made pledges to our Daddies not to have sex until we’re married.</p>

<p> Ultimately, we implied that <strong>a woman’s inherent worth and dignity could be measured by whether or not a man has touched her</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>As women who spend their young adult years believing that pre-marital sex is &#8220;not all it&#8217;s cracked up to be&#8221; start hitting struggles in their own &#8220;perfect&#8221; marriages, the church is happy to offer a whole industry of Christian sex advice.</p>

<h3>Race to the bottom</h3>

<p>This gospel offers &#8220;perfect&#8221; sex in a &#8220;perfect&#8221; marriage so long as one accepts the &#8220;package deal&#8221; of White Jesus with the cultural vestments of looking, sounding and voting Christian.</p>

<p>Christian Delusion
http://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/the-christian-delusion-john-w-loftus/1111758093?ean=9781616141684</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do Atheists Believe in One God Less?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/08/one-god-less/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T19:45:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/08/one-god-less</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John Dickson, founder of the Centre for Public Christianity recently <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/religion/articles/2013/07/08/3798272.htm">wrote in ABC religion and ethics</a> that he hates the atheist one-liner &#8220;There have been 10,000 gods through history, you reject 9,999 of them. I just go one god further!&#8221; He writes:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was a well-rehearsed line straight out of the atheist joke book - Dawkins likes to tell it, too. It got the laugh a witticism deserves. Simon replied laconically, &#8220;Is that meant to be an argument, Fitz?&#8221; Apparently, it was. &#8220;I&#8217;ve put this to a lot of believers over the years,&#8221; FitzSimons said with gusto, &#8220;and none of them has been able to reply.&#8221; I was surprised to hear that. So let me give it a go.</p>

<p>&#8220;Atheists just go one god further&#8221; is an aphorism regularly offered but rarely thought through. The idea it asks us to consider is something like this: when Christians reflect on why they reject Zeus, Ra, Isis, Vishnu et al., they will come to see the good sense of the atheist who simply adds one more deity to the rubbish bin. The arguments Christians employ against other gods, so the logic goes, come back to bite the Christian god as well. It is cute but silly.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Rubbish bin usually has the words &#8220;Don&#8217;t litter my mind.&#8221;</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/dickson.jpg" alt="Don't Litter my Mind" /></p>

<blockquote><p>For one thing, believers in any particular religion do not reject the other gods in toto. They deny the manifestations and stories of the other deities, but not necessarily their substance. A Christian may reject the elaborations and add-on characteristics of, say, Ra or Vishnu, but they happily acknowledge the wisdom of the ancient Egyptians and Indians in positing the existence of a powerful Intelligence which orders the universe.</p>

<p>There is, in other words, an irreducible shared conviction among most worshipers: the rational order of the universe is best explained by the existence of an almighty Mind (or Minds) behind it all. This is why the apostle Paul in Athens (Acts 17) can happily quote a line from a hymn to Zeus in his argument about God: &#8220;We are his offspring.&#8221; Paul did not think the stories about Zeus were true, but he agreed with the idea of divine power and intelligence which belief in Zeus embodied. Fitz and others are simply misguided to liken a Christian&#8217;s rejection of particular versions of divinity with the atheist&#8217;s denial of divinity altogether.</p></blockquote>

<p>Paul of Tarsus quotes Aratus and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epimenides_paradox">Epimenides the Cretan</a> in Acts 17:28 and Titus 1:12.</p>

<blockquote><p>An analogy highlights the error. In choosing to marry my wife, it is true that I rejected all other potential spouses (not that there were that many). Does this mean I have rejected the idea at the core of other people&#8217;s marriages? Of course not. But imagine a zealous celibate, who rejected marriage altogether and tried to use my own decision to marry one person as an argument against matrimony itself: &#8220;When you consider why you rejected other women in favour of her, then you will see the good sense of rejecting marriage altogether.&#8221;</p>

<p>I hardly need to point out that the difference between committed marriage and deliberate celibacy is not one of degree. Rejecting particular partners is nothing like rejecting the idea of partnership altogether. The analogy isn&#8217;t perfect but it makes one point clear: &#8220;we atheists just go one god further&#8221; is no more compelling than &#8220;we celibates just go one partner further.&#8221;</p>

<p>A believer&#8217;s denial of particular manifestations of the divine offers no support whatsoever for the atheist&#8217;s rejection of divinity itself. One-liners like this from the 101 Jokes for Atheists book should indeed be the object of laughter.</p></blockquote>

<p>The reason why people make these jokes is not because of the number of deities in the world, but how far reason and science has taken us away from the superstition that created them.</p>

<p>If you believe that Christianity is true and other religions are false, ask yourself a few questions:</p>

<p>Is the <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=josh10.10-15&amp;version=NET">book of Joshua</a> any less wrong about heliocentrism than the belief that Ra drives a chariot of fire across the sky? If Christian views on cosmology, inspired by a literal reading of the book of Joshua weren&#8217;t threatened by heliocentrism, then why did Catholic inquisitors force Galileo to recant his scientific theories and die under house arrest?</p>

<p>If Mithraism is false, why did Justin Martyr and Tertullian see a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_Christ_in_comparative_mythology">similarity between Mithraic initiation ceremonies and Christian Eucharist</a>?</p>

<p>Why does the Ancient Egyptian idea of eternal damnation in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_of_Fire">lake of fire</a> for those whose hearts are too heavy with sin predate the Chrisitan idea of salvation from eternal punishment in a lake of molten sulfur? Why do the 42 Negative Confessions of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maat">Maat</a> pre-date <a href="http://www.religioustolerance.org/chr_10cl.htm">the 10 commandments</a>? Why does Job&#8217;s <a href="http://bookofjob.org/act2.htm">Oath of Innocence</a>(Job 31) sound like a mirror immage of the negative confession?</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/maat-feather2.jpg" alt="Ancient Egyptian depiction of the weighing of a soul" /></p>

<p>If Osiris is a made up god, then why does Yahweh introduce Jesus as &#8220;This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.&#8221;(<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matt17.5&amp;version=NET">Matt 17:5</a>) when Osiris is introduced as &#8221;<a href="http://www.egyptorigins.org/osirisandjesusII.htm">I say by Nut, the brilliant, the great: This is my son, my first-born, opener of my womb; this is my beloved, with whom I am pleased</a>.&#8221;</p>

<p>If there is only one God, Yahweh, why does he insist in the first commandment, &#8221;<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=ex20&amp;version=NET">You shall have no other gods before me</a>&#8221; ? Did Judaism evolve from a polytheistic Caananite religion? Why does the Torah use the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetragrammaton">tetragrammaton</a> YHWH interchangably with the older Caananite word for the leader of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_(deity">polytheistic pantheon, El</a>)? If El is not a real god, then why do the Jewish people (Yiśrāʾ ēl, those who wrestle with god) use the same word for their god?</p>

<p>Why does Psalm 82:1 say &#8221;<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=ps82.1&amp;version=NET">God stands in the assembly of El, in the midst of the gods he renders judgment</a>&#8220;(NET bible) if the polytheistic El (with his divine assembly) is made up?</p>

<p>Was the miracle of Noah dividing the waters of the Sea of Reeds inspired by Egyptian stories of magic. The fictional magician <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djadjaemankh">Djadjaemankh</a> was rumoured to be able to fold a body of water in half. The story starts with the pharaoh <a href="http://www.thekeep.org/~kunoichi/kunoichi/themestream/egypt_magic.html">Snefru being bored</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;&#8230;His majesty said to him: [&#8216;I have gone through all the rooms] of the palace in search of relaxation and found none.&#8217; Djadjaemankh said to him: &#8216;May your majesty proceed to the lake of the palace. Fill a boat with all the beautiful girls of your palace. Your majesty&#8217;s heart will be refreshed by seeing them row, a rowing up and down. As you observe the fine nesting places of your lake, as you observe its beautiful fields and shores, your heart will be refreshed by it.&#8217;</p>

<p>&#8220;Said his majesty: &#8216;Indeed, I shall go boating! Let there be brought to me twenty oars of ebony plated with gold, their handles of sandalwood plated with electrum. Let there be brought to me twenty women with the shapeliest bodies, breasts, and braids, who have not yet given birth. Also let there be brought to me twenty nets and give these nets to these women in place of their clothes!&#8217; All was done as his majesty commanded.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Wanting a beautiful maiden brought to him also has some parallels with King David, but that could just be that it makes sense to cast ancient kings as creeps. While the king is making his heart glad perving on the beautiful virgins, they stop:</p>

<blockquote><p>And so they row to and fro and Sneferu&#8217;s heart is gladdened when he sees the girls row. Then it happens that the stroke maiden goes through her braids with her fingers and a hair pendant in the shape of a fish, made of malachite, falls into the water of the lake. The stroke maiden becomes silent in shock and grief and stops specifying the clock. Her complete line of rowers becomes silent, too, and they all stop rowing.</p></blockquote>

<p>Snefru wants to make the stroke maiden happy and offers her a new fish pendant, but she refuses, demanding the recovery of the original. The story goes on with magic division of the lake:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Djadjaemankh utters a secret spell which makes the waters of the lake move, so that one half side of the lake now rests on the other half. The water which had been 12 cubits in height becomes now 24 cubits at one side, whilst the other side is dry now. Djadjaemankh enters the lake&#8217;s ground and picks up the lost fish-pendant, which was lying on a pot-shard. He brings the amulet back to the stroke maiden and then removes the waters magically back to their original positions.</p></blockquote>

<p>Does this sound at all like Moses dividing water with magic powers, walking on dry ground, and then letting the water flow back again? The birth story of Moses being protected in an ark of bullrushes has similarities to the birth narrative of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sargon_of_Akkad">Sargon</a>.</p>

<p>The burden of proof on Christian believers is not just to prove that their deity exists, but also that the claims they make about their god are substantially different to older polytheistic deities now dismissed as unscientific myths.</p>

<p>Aron Ra gives further examples of the myths similar to the Torah myths:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('FLviKiEuj30');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/FLviKiEuj30&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('FLviKiEuj30-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/FLviKiEuj30/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLviKiEuj30" id="FLviKiEuj30" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/FLviKiEuj30/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLviKiEuj30" id="FLviKiEuj30-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">the Evolution of Genesis</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >This is my lecture on the origins of Biblical fables, presented for the Secular Student Alliance in the University of North Texas at Denton on 2013/04/11. I was running late. It was a crowded classroom, and there was no time or available outlets to set the camera up any better, but at least you should be able to hear what is being said.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Church Teaching Against Women from St. Augustine to Pat Robertson]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/06/biblical-mysoginy/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-06T14:52:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/07/06/biblical-mysoginy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whether it&#8217;s saying that it&#8217;s God&#8217;s will that women get pregnant from rape, or that women can&#8217;t get pregnant from &#8221;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rape_and_pregnancy_controversies_in_United_States_elections,_2012">legitimate rape</a>&#8221; because women can &#8220;shut that whole thing down&#8221;, Republican senators seem to be living on another planet when they talk about women. One street preacher, proud to be a virgin, declares that women at a Take Back The Night march on <a href="http://www.digitaljournal.com/article/348898">his campus deserve to be raped</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/deserve-rape.jpg" alt="You Deserve Rape sign" /></p>

<p>While his pro rape trolling is crazy by modern standards, it&#8217;s sadly not far outside Christian tradition for much of the last 2000 years.
Dr Valerie Tarico has compiled a list of <a href="http://awaypoint.wordpress.com/2013/07/01/mysogynistquoteschurchfathers/">vile quotes from church fathers thoughout history teaching their flock to hate women</a></p>

<blockquote><p>What with diatribes about entertainers who <a href="http://www.leftfootforward.org/2013/06/daily-mail-columnist-says-rihannas-fashion-sense-invites-rape/">invite rape</a>
and moms who are <a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/psysociety/2013/06/03/fox-news-fact-check-is-it-bad-for-lower-income-kids-if-mom-has-a-job-outside-the-home/">destroying America</a>
by supporting their families &#8230; with ignorant arguments about
<a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/xx_factor/2013/06/18/rep_mike_burgess_of_texas_suggests_banning_abortion_because_fetuses_masturbate.html">fetuses that masturbate</a>,
and females who might as well <a href="http://www.lifesitenews.com/news/contracepting-america-the-real-war-on-women">if they use contraception</a>,
and fetal personhood that trumps the personhood of females &#8230; . it’s
tempting to think that Christian conservatives, have reached some new
pinnacle of hating women and sexuality. But the sad reality is that even
the media’s most unabashed misogynists like Michelle Bachman, Michael
Burgess, Lou Dobbs or Juan Williams are actually tame compared to their
ideological ancestors, which include some of the biggest names in
Christian history.</p>

<p>In past centuries, men who were hailed as Church Fathers, Patriarchs,
Doctors, and even Saints boldly expressed their view that females are
inferior and loathsome; and they explained at length why God shared
their perspective. Lest we fall into the <em>conservative</em> trap of thinking
that the past was somehow better than the nasty messes we face today,
it’s worth pondering some of the lovely tidbits that the Church has
thought fit to preserve and promote in the centuries since Christianity
was founded. Here are some of the most savory. They come from three
waves of religious leaders: “Fathers” of the Catholic Church, Protestant
Reformers, and American patriarchs who inherited the mantle of both.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Church Doctors and Fathers</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Woman is a temple built over a sewer.
<strong>–</strong><em>Tertullian, “the father of Latin Christianity” (c160-225)</em></p></li>
<li><p>In pain shall you bring forth children, woman, and you shall turn to
your husband and he shall rule over you. And do you not know that
you are Eve? God’s sentence hangs still over all your sex and His
punishment weighs down upon you. You are the devil’s gateway; you
are she who first violated the forbidden tree and broke the law of
God. It was you who coaxed your way around him whom the devil had
not the force to attack. With what ease you shattered that image of
God: Man! Because of the death you merited, even the Son of God had
to die… <strong>Woman, you are the gate to hell</strong>.
<strong>–</strong><em>Tertullian, “the father of Latin Christianity” (c160-225)</em></p></li>
<li><p>[Women&#8217;s] very consciousness of their own nature must evoke feelings
of shame.–<em>Saint Clement of Alexandria, Christian theologian (c150-215) Pedagogues II, 33, 2</em></p></li>
<li><p>Nor are the women to smear their faces with the ensnaring devices of
wily cunning&#8230; The Instructor [Christ] orders them to go forth
“in becoming apparel, and adorn themselves with shamefacedness and
sobriety, subject to their own husbands.”
–<em>Saint Clement of Alexandria, Christian theologian (c150-215), <a href="http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/clement-instructor-book3.html">The Instructor</a></em></p></li>
<li><p>For it is improper for a woman to speak in an assembly, no matter
what she says,
even if she says admirable things, or even saintly things, that is
of little
consequence, since they come from the mouth of a woman.
<em><strong>–</strong>Origen (d. 258), </em>Fragments on First Corinthians<em>, 74</em></p></li>
<li><p>Woman does not possess the image of God in herself but only when
taken together
 with the male who is her head, so that the whole substance is one
image. But
 when she is assigned the role as helpmate, a function that pertains
to her
 alone, then she is not the image of God. But as far as the man is
concerned, he
 is by himself alone the image of God just as fully and completely
as when he and
 the woman are joined together into one. –<em>Saint Augustine, Bishop
of Hippo Regius (354-430)</em></p></li>
<li><p>What is the difference whether it is in a wife or a mother, it is
still Eve the temptress that we must beware of in any woman… I fail
to see what use woman can be to man, if one excludes the function of
bearing children. <em>–Saint Augustine, Bishop of Hippo Regius (354 –
430)</em></p></li>
<li><p>To embrace a woman is to embrace a sack of manure. - Odo of Cluny stated</p></li>
<li><p>Woman is a misbegotten man and has a faulty and defective nature in
comparison to his. Therefore she is unsure in herself. What she
cannot get, she seeks to obtain through lying and diabolical
deceptions. And so, to put it briefly, one must be on one’s guard
with every woman, as if she were a poisonous snake and the horned
devil. … Thus in evil and perverse doings woman is cleverer, that
is, slyer, than man. Her feelings drive woman toward every evil,
just as reason impels man toward all good. <em>–Saint Albertus Magnus,
Dominican theologian, 13th century</em></p></li>
<li><p>As regards the individual nature, woman is defective and
misbegotten, for the active force in the male seed tends to the
production of a perfect likeness in the masculine sex; while the
production of woman comes from a defect in the active force or from
some material indisposition, or even from some external influence.
<em>–Thomas Aquinas, Doctor of the Church, 13th century, Summa Theologica</em></p></li>
<li><p>All witchcraft comes from carnal lust, which is in women insatiable. - <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malleus_Maleficarum">Malleus Maleficarum</a>, 1486</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Protestant Reformers</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>The word and works of God is quite clear, that women were made
either to be wives or prostitutes. –<em>Martin Luther, Works 12.94</em></p></li>
<li><p>Men have broad and large chests, and small narrow hips, and more
understanding than women, who have but small and narrow breasts, and
broad hips, to the end they should remain at home, sit still, keep
house, and bear and bring up children. –<em>Martin Luther, Table Talk</em></p></li>
<li><p>No gown worse becomes a woman than the desire to be wise. -<em>Martin Luther</em></p></li>
<li><p>Even though they grow weary and wear themselves out with child-bearing, it does not matter; let them go on bearing children till they die, that is what they are there for. <em>Martin Luther, Works 20.84</em></p></li>
<li><p>God created Adam master and lord of living creatures, but Eve spoilt all, when she persuaded him to set himself above God&#8217;s will. &#8216;Tis you women, with your tricks and artifices, that lead men into error. -<em>Martin Luther</em></p></li>
<li><p>We may well lie with what seems to be a woman of flesh and blood, and yet all the time it is only a devil in the shape of a woman. -<em>Martin Luther</em></p></li>
<li><p>“If a woman grows weary and at last dies from childbearing, it matters not. Let her only die from bearing; she is there to do it.” —<em>Martin Luther</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Thus the woman, who had perversely exceeded her proper bounds, is
forced back to her own position. She had, indeed, previously been
subject to her husband, but that was a liberal and gentle
subjection; now, however, she is cast into servitude.<strong>–</strong><em>John
Calvin, Reformer (1509-1564), Commentary on Genesis, p. 172.</em></p></li>
<li><p>Do not any longer contend for mastery, for power, money, or praise.
Be content to be a private, insignificant person, known and loved by
God and me&#8230; . of what importance is your character to mankind,
if you was buried just now Or if you had never lived, what loss
would it be to the cause of God.<strong>–</strong><em>John Wesley, founder of
Methodist movement (1703-1791), <a href="http://wesley.nnu.edu/john-wesley/the-letters-of-john-wesley/wesleys-letters-1774/">letter to his wife</a>,
July 15, 1774</em></p></li>
</ul>


<h3>American Patriarchs (Puritan, Mormon, Baptist, Evangelical)</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Even as the church must fear Christ Jesus, so must the wives also
fear their husbands. And this inward fear must be shewed by an
outward meekness and lowliness in her speeches and carriage to her
husband&#8230; . For if there be not fear and reverence in the
inferior, there can be no sound nor constant honor yielded to the
superior. –<em>John Dod, A Plaine and Familiar Exposition of the Ten
Commandements</em>, <em>Puritan guidebook first published in 1603</em>**</p></li>
<li><p>The second duty of the wife is constant obedience and subjection.
–<em>John Dod, A Plaine and Familiar Exposition of the Ten
Commandements</em>, <em>Puritan guidebook first published in 1603</em>**</p></li>
<li><p>The root of masculine is stronger, and of feminine weaker. The sun
is a governing planet to certain planets, while the moon borrows her
light from the sun, and is less or weaker. <em>–Joseph Smith, founder
of LDS movement (1805-1844), History of the Church, V, p. 211</em></p></li>
<li><p>Women are made to be led, and counseled, and directed&#8230; . And if
I am not a good man, I have no just right in this Church to a wife
or wives, or the power to propagate my species. What then should be
done with me? Make a eunuch of me, and stop my propagation. <em>–Heber
C. Kimball, venerated early LDS apostle (1801-1868), JD 5:29</em></p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Modern mysogninists</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>A wife is to submit graciously to the servant leadership of her
husband, even as the church willingly submits to the headship of
Christ. <em>–Official Faith and Message Statement of Southern Baptist
Convention, Summer 1998, (15.7 million members)</em></p></li>
<li><p>The feminist agenda is not about equal rights for women. It is about
a socialist, anti-family political movement that encourages women to
leave their husbands, kill their children, practice witchcraft,
destroy capitalism and become lesbians. — <em>Pat Robertson, Southern
Baptist leader (1930-), <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1992/08/26/us/robertson-letter-attacks-feminists.html">fundraising
letter</a>
July 1992</em></p></li>
<li><p>The Holiness of God is not evidenced in women when they are brash,
brassy, boisterous, brazen, head-strong, strong-willed,
loud-mouthed, overly-talkative, having to have the last word,
challenging, controlling, manipulative, critical, conceited,
arrogant, aggressive, assertive, strident, interruptive,
undisciplined, insubordinate, disruptive, dominating, domineering,
or clamoring for power. Rather, women accept God’s holy order and
character by being humbly and unobtrusively respectful and receptive
in functional subordination to God, church leadership, and husbands.
<em>–James Fowler, Women in the Church, 1999</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Women will be saved by going back to that role that God has chosen
for them. Ladies, if the hair on the back of your neck stands up it
is because you are fighting your role in the scripture. <em>–<a href="http://community.feministing.com/2010/06/23/mark-driscoll-misogyny-and-masculinity/">Mark Driscoll</a>,
founder of Mars Hill nondenominational mega-church franchise.
(1970-), <a href="http://lineout.thestranger.com/2008/04/everclear_to_play_mars_hill_church">sermon 2008</a></em></p></li>
</ul>


<p>Michael and Debi Pearl are advocates of extreme physical discipline and female submission. Their book to train up a child encourages physical violence against childen as young as 6 months to &#8220;break their spirit.&#8221; Michael advocates that fathers have fun disciplining hitting their children:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('R12CVm9WvNE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/R12CVm9WvNE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('R12CVm9WvNE-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/R12CVm9WvNE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R12CVm9WvNE" id="R12CVm9WvNE" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/R12CVm9WvNE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R12CVm9WvNE" id="R12CVm9WvNE-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Christain love and censorship from child abuser Michael Pearl.</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >A video about a child abusing neanderthal, I cut out the speech to jump right to the action. Make sure you watch the original as themudbrooker has said more then anyone else could about this man&#8217;s blatant disregard for copyright law. This man&#8217;s books have lead to the beating deaths of children, lets show this clown the internet doesn&#8217;t accept his shit.

The original video:
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GNv61rb7TNc


TheMudbrooker&#8217;s Channel
http://www.youtube.com/user/TheMudbrooker

Everything is terrible. Check it out it has hilarious content.
http://www.everythingisterrible.com/


17 U.S.C. § 107

Notwithstanding the provisions of sections 17 U.S.C. § 106 and 17 U.S.C. § 106A, the fair use of a copyrighted work, including such use by reproduction in copies or phonorecords or by any other means specified by that section, for purposes such as criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, This falls under this act, I will send counter claims.</div>
</div>


<p>Debi Pearl has published a long exposition of her Christian version of Stockholm Syndrome called <a href="http://eaandfaith.blogspot.com.au/2008/04/debi-pearls-created-to-be-helpmate.html">Created to be his helpmeet</a>. It encourages women in abusive relationships to submit to violent partners:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Page 263: “Lady, you were created to give glory to God. When God puts you in
subjection to a man whom he knows is going to cause you to suffer, it is with
the understanding that <strong>you are obeying God by enduring the wrongful suffering</strong>.
And when you suffer wrongfully, as unto the Lord, you bring great glory to God
in heaven.”</p></li>
<li><p>Page 263: “Has your husband reviled and threatened you? You are exhorted to respond as Jesus did. When he was reviled and threatened, he suffered by
committing himself to a higher judge who is righteous. You must commit yourself
to the one who placed you under your husband’s command. Your husband will answer
to God, and you must answer to God for how you respond to your husband, even
when he causes you to suffer.”</p></li>
<li><p>Page 264: “You can freely call your husband “lord” when you know that you are addressing the one who put him in charge and asked you to suffer at your
husband’s hands just as our Lord suffered at the hands of unjust authorities… I
know that this must be an amazing doctrine to many of you. Nonetheless, it is no
less radical than Jesus was radical, and it is God’s way.”</p></li>
<li><p>Page 265: “For the eyes of the Lord see all that take place. His ears are open to your prayers when you obey him and obey your husband. And then comes the
promise: if you are following God, no harm will come to you by doing what is
good… You will receive a blessing when you suffer for righteousness’ sake, that
is, when you obey God by obeying your husband and not returning evil for evil.
You will be happy, so don’t be afraid or troubled by the things you must
endure.”</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Dr Tarico concludes:</p>

<blockquote><p>Why has the main current of Christianity produced a steady diet of
misogyny for over 2000 years? The answer may lay partly in human biology
and culture. But it also lies in the Iron Age texts of the Bible itself.
The Judeo-Christian tradition of building up men by tearing down women
goes all the way back to the most ancient parts of the biblical
collection, to the opening pages of Genesis, and continues unabated
through the New Testament. (I’ve written elsewhere about <a href="http://awaypoint.wordpress.com/2012/03/09/15-bible-texts-reveal-why-gods-own-party-is-at-war-with-women/">15 of those Bible verses</a>
because they partly explain the conservative assault on women.) As Mr.
Driscoll <a href="http://lineout.thestranger.com/2008/04/everclear_to_play_mars_hill_church">likes to</a>
remind his followers, “Every single book in your Bible is written by a
man.”</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You can heal cancer naturally with coffee enemas, but only if they're organic]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/24/coffee-enema/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-24T21:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/24/coffee-enema</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No, wait, you can&#8217;t. Jessica Ainscough, a self proclaimed &#8220;wellness warrior&#8221; has recently complained that she felt &#8220;dirty&#8221; after eating a vegan burger that wasn&#8217;t 100% organic. The burger was billed by the not-for-profit vegetarian cafe as &#8220;cancer fighting rather than cancer causing.&#8221; Ainscough later rang the cafe to check up on some of their claims, but not whether any of the claimed miraculous healing properties had any empirical basis, but rather if their food was 100% organic. The revelation that her burger and juice weren&#8217;t purely organic made her feel like such a dirty, dirty woman that <a href="http://www.thewellnesswarrior.com.au/2013/06/beware-of-organic-cafes-that-lie-to-us/">she needed detoxifying</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>I felt dirty. <strong>I felt like I needed to give my insides about 10 showers</strong>. I was so shocked that I just hung up the phone, but I wish I’d told her that her since her “cancer fighting” burger contains pesticides it is actually cancer causing.</p></blockquote>

<p>Emphasis hers. The poor woman is very slowly dying of a rare type of cancer, epithelioid sarcoma, which tends to show up in young patients. Unfortunately, with no paletable treatment options available, the woman has chosen to believe in the claimed &#8220;natural healing power&#8221; of miracle diets to avoid acknowledging her fate. The yellow journalism of the Daily Tele <a href="http://www.news.com.au/entertainment/restaurants-bars/jess-ainscough-claims-8216organic8217-cafe-misled-with-veggie-burger/story-fn93ypt9-1226668814935">repeats this bunk untramelled</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The holistic health coach, who was in Byron Bay last week, follows a strict organic diet after overcoming cancer without using modern medicine.</p></blockquote>

<p>She follows <a href="http://skepdic.com/gersontherapy.html">Gerson Therapy</a>, a debunked therapy that claims to be able to cure cancer by following a diet and &#8220;cleansing&#8221; unknown &#8220;toxins&#8221; from the body by coffee enemas. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerson_therapy#Gerson_Therapy">diet and enemas</a> are not proven to be effective in any <a href="http://www.cancer.org/treatment/treatmentsandsideeffects/complementaryandalternativemedicine/dietandnutrition/gerson-therapy">large scale peer reviewed studies</a>, and coffee enemas have been linked to the <a href="http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/pdq/cam/gerson/patient/Page2#Section_28">deaths of three people in the US</a>. Most notably, the advocates of these therapies often take over $10,000 a time from dying patients, telling them to <a href="https://www.google.com.au/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CCoQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.theaustralian.com.au%2Fnews%2Ffeatures%2Fholding-out-for-a-miracle%2Fstory-e6frg8h6-1226476739168&amp;ei=p00KUoqiLMnwlAXdhIDwCg&amp;usg=AFQjCNHKviBCjXOnTlzqfpGUgo78qY3pOA&amp;sig2=MDGCuS_q5Zjj4x_uM45gKg&amp;bvm=bv.50500085,d.dGI">give up conventional treatments and pain medication</a> while they die. They are part of a growing number of natropaths encouraging people to die without conventional medicine, and they have a growing number of adherants:</p>

<blockquote><p>Last year Perth mother-of-four Gemma Bond staged her own public renunciation of conventional medicine after being diagnosed with ovarian and uterine cancer. After agreeing to a hysterectomy on her doctor&#8217;s recommendation, Bond declined all further treatment in favour of a regime of coffee enemas, ozone therapy, intravenous vitamins and supplements</p></blockquote>

<p>Last year there was an investigation by the West Australian government into the deaths of 20 cancer patients.</p>

<blockquote><p>Evelyn Vicker details how roughly 20 terminal cancer patients paid as much as $40,000 each to be subjected to an experimental treatment advertised on the internet and administered in Darwin and Perth in 2004-05. All of them were told to abandon conventional medical treatment, including painkillers; all were seduced by a claimed 95 per cent success rate; all of them died, many in agony.</p></blockquote>

<p>The coroner&#8217;s report recommended criminal proceedings against the doctor that <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-07-04/coroner-finds-against-alternative-cancer-therapy/4110182">promoted the therapy</a>, that include DMSO. The industrial solvent dimethyl sulfoxide is commonly claimed to be a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimethyl_sulfoxide">fake cancer cure</a>. The 281 page coroner&#8217;s report is <a href="http://www.safetyandquality.health.wa.gov.au/docs/mortality_review/inquest_finding/Operation_Lantana_finding.pdf">available online</a>, detailing how the patients died:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sartori lacked clinical skills and was unable to provide proper medical care while the treatment was occurring. Patients are at risk of suffering serious harm or dying due to the questionable clinical care received under his instruction. Those promoting the treatment claim it is “natural” and “safe”. Sartori’s form of this treatment is neither. It requires high doses of industrially manufactured substances and is manifestly unsafe, as are a number of other purportedly ‘natural’ products.</p></blockquote>

<p>Ainscough describes how her <a href="http://dolly.ninemsn.com.au/girltalk/realityreads/8399381/im-healing-myself-from-cancer-naturally">treatment supposedly works</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>This research led me to Gerson Therapy which ensures you have a perfectly balanced diet for optimum health, assisting your body to flush out nasties whilst feeding it with all the goodness it needs to flourish.</p>

<p>The therapy involves drinking 13 fresh organic veggie juices per day (yes that’s one an hour, every hour of my waking day), five coffee enemas per day and a basic organic whole food plant-based diet with additional supplements.</p></blockquote>

<p>There aren&#8217;t many jobs in which someone could have five or <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Health/florida-couple-addicted-coffee-enemas/story?id=18433235#.UchQKUE-cT8">more coffee enemas a day</a>. And while drinking juices may not be harmful, there is <a href="http://skepdic.com/gersontherapy.html">no evidence that the treatment works in the ways it says it does</a>, but is unfortunately continuing to exploit desperate people.</p>

<p>She goes on to invent &#8221;<a href="http://www.thewellnesswarrior.com.au/2013/06/how-your-thoughts-can-help-clean-up-the-planet/">psychic pollution</a>&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><p>Did you know that pollution on our planet is not only caused by greenhouse gases, littering and chemical waste but also by our negative thoughts?
Yes, you did read that last sentence correctly; our negative thoughts also contribute to pollution on our planet. This is called ‘psychic pollution.’
This fact has been proven: what we think and feel has a direct impact on the world around us.</p></blockquote>

<p>[Citation needed]</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('HhGuXCuDb1U');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HhGuXCuDb1U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('HhGuXCuDb1U-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/HhGuXCuDb1U/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HhGuXCuDb1U" id="HhGuXCuDb1U" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/HhGuXCuDb1U/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HhGuXCuDb1U" id="HhGuXCuDb1U-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Tim Minchin&#8217;s Storm the Animated Movie</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >In the confines of a London dinner party, comedian Tim Minchin argues with a hippy named Storm. While Storm herself may not be converted, audiences from London to LA have been won over by Tim&#8217;s wordplay and the timely message of the film in a society where science and reason are portrayed as the enemy of belief.

Written and performed by Tim Minchin @timminchin. Directed by DC Turner @dcturner. Produced by Tracy King @tkingdoll. www.stormmovie.net

Italian subtitles by www.comedysubs.org
English subtitles by Jason Livingston
Russian subtitles by Denis Olshin</div>
</div>


<p>If you want to see Ainscough talk about putting a tube in her butt, she describes the process <a href="http://healthtalkstv.com/detoxification/jess-ainscough-the-coffee-enema/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[when-culture-wars-kill]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/20/when-culture-wars-kill/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T10:51:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/20/when-culture-wars-kill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>http://www.exgaywatch.com/2013/06/is-the-end-of-exodus-near/
http://www.exgaywatch.com/2013/06/hardliners-pre-emptively-spin-expose-of-survivors-of-ex-gay-abuse/</p>

<p>http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry/
http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2013/06/35755/
http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2013/06/35664/</p>

<p>http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2013/06/35751/</p>

<p>http://www.exgaywatch.com/2011/07/exodus-says-ex-gay-boot-camps-dont-exist-survivors-say-otherwise/</p>

<p>http://www.theage.com.au/victoria/when-faith-and-sexuality-collide-20130413-2hskc.html#
&#8220;I know of a church where one of the pastors recommended to a guy that he go and see a female prostitute because he couldn&#8217;t comprehend that this guy could not be attracted to or enjoy sex with a woman&#8221;</p>

<p>Chambers
http://www.boxturtlebulletin.com/2010/03/04/20825“the majority of people that I have met, and I would say the majority meaning 99.9% of them, have not experienced a change in their orientation or have gotten to a place where they could say that they could never be tempted or are not tempted in some way or experience some level of same-sex attraction.”</p>

<p>In advance of the Exodus Freedom Conference in Irvine, California, and of
the airing of Lisa Ling’s <em>Our America</em> tomorrow night, in which he is
confronted by “ex-gay” survivors, Alan Chambers <a href="http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry/">has issued a long
apology</a> to the
LGBTQ community on Exodus’s website. While much more work obviously
remains to be done to make sure that Exodus is truly serious about never
again destroying the lives and families of LGBTQ people in the name of
faith, the apology is striking in that there is little to no
equivocation. I’m going to excerpt most of it, bolding parts that I feel
important, and we will have more commentary on this in the coming days:</p>

<blockquote><p>Recently, I have begun thinking again about how to apologize to the
people that have been hurt by Exodus International through an
experience or by a message. I have heard many firsthand stories from
people called ex-gay survivors. Stories of people who went to Exodus
affiliated ministries or ministers for help only to experience more
trauma. I have heard stories of shame, sexual misconduct, and false
hope. In every case that has been brought to my attention, there has
been swift action resulting in the removal of these leaders and/or
their organizations. But rarely was there an apology or a public
acknowledgement by me.</p>

<p>And then there is the trauma that I have caused. <strong>There were several
years that I conveniently omitted my ongoing same-sex attractions.</strong> I
was afraid to share them as readily and easily as I do today. They
brought me tremendous shame and I hid them in the hopes they would go
away. <strong>Looking back, it seems so odd that I thought I could do
something to make them stop. Today, however, I accept these feelings
as parts of my life that will likely always be there.</strong> The days of
feeling shame over being human in that way are long over, and I feel
free simply accepting myself as my wife and family does. As my friends
do. As God does.</p>

<p>Never in a million years would I intentionally hurt another person.
<strong>Yet, here I sit having hurt so many by failing to acknowledge the
pain some affiliated with Exodus International caused, and by failing
to share the whole truth about my own story. My good intentions matter
very little and fail to diminish the pain and hurt others have
experienced on my watch.</strong> The good that we have done at Exodus is
overshadowed by all of this.</p>

<p>Friends and critics alike have said it’s not enough to simply change
our message or website. I agree. I cannot simply move on and pretend
that I have always been the friend that I long to be today. <strong>I
understand why I am distrusted and why Exodus is hated.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Please know that I am deeply sorry. I am sorry for the pain and hurt
many of you have experienced. I am sorry that some of you spent years
working through the shame and guilt you felt when your attractions
didn’t change. I am sorry we promoted sexual orientation change
efforts and reparative theories about sexual orientation that
stigmatized parents. I am sorry that there were times I didn’t stand
up to people publicly “on my side” who called you names like
sodomite—or worse. I am sorry that I, knowing some of you so well,
failed to share publicly that the gay and lesbian people I know were
every bit as capable of being amazing parents as the straight people
that I know. I am sorry that when I celebrated a person coming to
Christ and surrendering their sexuality to Him that I callously
celebrated the end of relationships that broke your heart. I am sorry
that I have communicated that you and your families are less than me
and mine.</strong></p>

<p>More than anything, I am sorry that so many have interpreted this
religious rejection by Christians as God’s rejection. I am profoundly
sorry that many have walked away from their faith and that some have
chosen to end their lives. For the rest of my life I will proclaim
nothing but the whole truth of the Gospel, one of grace, mercy and
open invitation to all to enter into an inseverable relationship with
almighty God.</p>

<p>I cannot apologize for my deeply held biblical beliefs about the
boundaries I see in scripture surrounding sex, but I will exercise my
beliefs with great care and respect for those who do not share them. I
cannot apologize for my beliefs about marriage. <strong>But I do not have
any desire to fight you on your beliefs or the rights that you seek.
My beliefs about these things will never again interfere with God’s
command to love my neighbor as I love myself.</strong></p>

<p><strong>You have never been my enemy. I am very sorry that I have been
yours.</strong> I hope the changes in my own life, as well as the ones we
announce tonight regarding Exodus International, will bring
resolution, and show that I am serious in both my regret and my offer
of friendship. I pledge that future endeavors will be focused on peace
and common good.</p>

<p>Moving forward, we will serve in our pluralistic culture by hosting
thoughtful and safe conversations about gender and sexuality, while
partnering with others to reduce fear, inspire hope, and cultivate
human flourishing.</p></blockquote>

<p>Words are words, but words matter in that they are a start. We anxiously
await the announcements regarding Exodus’s future that Alan mentioned,
and we hope that Exodus’s “future” is that there won’t be one. That
would seem to be the only surefire way to stop the bleeding.</p>

<p>Lisa Ling’s special on Exodus airs tomorrow night at 10 EDT on the OWN
network.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are You a Racist?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/12/are-you-a-racist/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-12T11:08:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/12/are-you-a-racist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A team of Harvard psychologists recently completed a study showing a correlation between religious belief and performance on the well-known Cognitive Reflection Test The CRT goes like this; consider these simple maths quesions:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>A bat and a ball cost $1.10 in total.  The bat costs $1.00 more than the ball.  How much does the ball cost?</li>
<li>If it takes five machines five minutes to make five widgets, how long does it take 100 machines to make 100 widgets?</li>
<li>In a lake, there is a patch of lily pads.  Every day, the patch doubles in size.  If it takes 48 days for the patch to cover the entire lake, how long would it take for the patch to cover half of the lake?</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>You may have confidence in your answers. The answers are below these optical illusions, that show how you interpret the world may be mistaken:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/illusion-Zollner.png" alt="Zollner Illusion" /></p>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z%C3%B6llner_illusion">Zöllner illusion</a> demonstrates that while lines actually run in parallel, they look wonky when a pattern makes you believe that they aren&#8217;t straight.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/illusion-pisa789.jpg" alt="Double Leaning Tower of Pisa Illusion" /></p>

<p>Both of these images are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leaning_tower_illusion">exactly the same</a>. Try covering one of them with your hand. When you see both images along side each other, your mind automatically assumes that the one on the right must come from a different angle.</p>

<p><strong>Answers</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>You would expect the ball to cost $0.10 if the bat cost $1.00, but the bat costs $1.00 <em>more</em> than the ball, giving the correct answer of <strong>$0.05</strong></li>
<li>While the intuitive answer is 100 minutes, it takes five machines five minutes to produce one widget each, so it takes 100 machines five minutes to produce one widget each (100 widgets).</li>
<li>The intuitive answer is half the days (24), the correct answer is 47 (because the patch doubles each day).</li>
</ol>


<p>These aren&#8217;t difficult questions, but many people get the answers wrong when they don&#8217;t think the problem though methodically, relying on intuition instead of slow, methodical, rational thought. More religious people <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/matthew-hutson/what-kind-of-thinker-beli_b_2759701.html">tend to get more of the answers wrong</a>, trusting their intuition more than less religious participants.</p>

<p>David Hume said &#8220;reason is the slave of the passions&#8221; and modern neuroscience backs the claim up.
Daniel Kahneman has noted differences in the way that people <a href="http://edge.org/conversation/the-marvels-and-flaws-of-intuitive-thinking">process information quickly and intuitively, compared to how they think slowly and methodically</a>.</p>

<p>In 2008 Transport for London received international recognition on the Gruen Transfer for this ad about recognition of cyclists:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('Ahg6qcgoay4');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ahg6qcgoay4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('Ahg6qcgoay4-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Ahg6qcgoay4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ahg6qcgoay4" id="Ahg6qcgoay4" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Ahg6qcgoay4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ahg6qcgoay4" id="Ahg6qcgoay4-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Test Your Awareness: Do The Test</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >How many passes does the team in white make? Test your awareness and Do the Test! TFL cycling safetly advert! Count the number of passes the White team makes. Do you see the Moonwalking bear?</div>
</div>


<p>Very often we can fail to spot things that we&#8217;re not looking out for. Today <em>Scientific American</em> published an article on selective attention, where people can fail to notice the things &#8221;<a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=your-hidden-censor-what-your-mind-will-not-let-you-see&amp;page=1">your mind will not let you see</a>.&#8221; In one study white women were asked to concentrate on a ball-tossing video, then asked if they noticed a black man or a white man in the middle. One group primed on a task aimed at finding a &#8220;a suitable neighbor or co-worker&#8221; were equally likely to see both men. Another group primed on looking for a friend or date noticed the white man more than twice as often as the black man.</p>

<p>Many societies that have multicultural workplaces don&#8217;t have as many mixed ethnicity marriages, meaning that many people may be more subconsiously accustomed to seeing people of other races in a distant setting but not as accustomed to them being friends or family. In several studies where participants <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/108/13/E46.full">were given a shot of oxytocin</a>, the participants showed increased trust and co-operation with their in-group, while maintaining the same level of trust with their out-group. In <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/108/4/1262.full">one study</a>, participants performed an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Implicit_Association_Test">implicit association test</a>, where participants are timed in their categorisation of images of faces by grouping them with words that have positive or negative emotions. We often perceive visual information quickly, while rationally processing it takes longer. The Scientific American article mentions a similar study:</p>

<blockquote><p>On some trials of their experiment, one eye saw a neutral picture like a lamp, and the other eye saw a bloody scene of violence. On other trials, one eye saw a neutral picture and the other saw an erotic nude picture. The subjects’ conscious experiences of the pictures flipped back and forth, but the scenes of sex and violence were more likely to be the first ones seen, and they occupied consciousness much longer than the boring neutral images. Several studies have now confirmed that dangerous things like snakes, angry men, and snarling dogs can break through our concentration and intrude on consciousness. Dirty words and naughty pictures have the same effects&#8230; If it gets your heart racing it will get your attention.</p></blockquote>

<p>Make sure you don&#8217;t get distracted when considering the beautiful dolphins on this bottle:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/dolphinsex.jpg" alt="Dolphin Illusion" /></p>

<p>In a hunter-gatherer context, humans would need to interrupt their slow thinking processes to quickly react to a predator that suddenly appears, leaving us with sex and violence being distracting and intensely engaging in ways that reflective modes of thought aren&#8217;t. Why else would there be so much sex and violence on HBO shows like <em>Game of Thrones</em>?</p>

<p>The article goes on with this clincher:</p>

<blockquote><p>There is something particularly disquieting about this brand of bias, because there is a power asymmetry. The unconscious screener shapes what the conscious “you” gets to see, but the conscious “you” doesn’t have veto power over that decision. Of course, you could try to shift your attention or change your goals once you are aware of them, but by then it may be too late. The unconscious always has a head start.</p></blockquote>

<p>Jonathan Haidt likens fast and slow thinking to an <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/news/opinion/the-mind-has-an-elephant-of-its-own/2006/07/25/1153816179991.html?page=fullpage">emotional elephant with a rational rider</a>. The rider likes to think that he is in control, but really, the much larger elephant has most of the say in what direction the pair takes. In <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/files/emotional_dog_and_rational_tail.pdf">The Emotional Dog and its Rational Tail</a> Haidt states &#8220;moral reasoning is usually a post-hoc construction, generated after a judgment has been reached.&#8221; We assume that we are in control of our decisions, and yet psychology and behavioral economics shows that most of our rational decisions are a &#8220;slave&#8221; to the snap emotional judgements we make.</p>

<p>Consider Eddie McGuire&#8217;s <a href="http://theconversation.com/racism-in-the-afl-eddie-mcguire-and-the-media-prove-theres-still-a-long-way-to-go-14838">likening of Adam Goodes to King Kong</a> after nearly a week of condemning racially villifying remarks about Aboriginal AFL players. This doesn&#8217;t just highlight Eddie McGuire&#8217;s stupidity but points to the wider problem of people allowing racial stereotypes to colour their sentiments of people, while denying to themselves and others that any bias exists. Even people sincerely opposed to racism can act in <a href="http://theconversation.com/are-you-racist-you-may-be-without-even-knowing-it-10826">ways that express biases without knowing it</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Here’s an example of how this kind of thing can occur, from a <a href="http://socialjudgments.com/docs/Uhlmann%20and%20Cohen%202005.pdf">2005 American study</a>.
In this study, participants were asked to choose the better applicant
for the job of police chief. There were two candidates. One was “street
wise” while the other had more formal education. One was male, one was
female. Some experimental subjects were given the choice between a male
street wise applicant and a female formally educated applicant, while
some got the options reversed, with the female applicant being the
street wise one.</p>

<p>Here’s the interesting finding – both groups tended to pick the male
applicant as the better qualified. They justified this choice by
reference to the qualification the female lacked&#8230;</p>

<p>It looked as though they were making a judgement based on what qualifications they thought were required for police chief. They weren’t really: they were making a judgement based on gender, and justifying it, based on a confabulated theory about what qualifications were required for police chief.</p></blockquote>

<p>Similarly, when right of centre voters criticise Gillard in an excessively personal way (&#8220;Ju-liar&#8221;), a confabulatory process may mask mysoginistic attitudes as a justified criticism of her character and agenda. Worse, a tribal grouping of people who agree with each other&#8217;s politics encourages <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_cognition">cultural cognition</a>, with their own biases being confirmed by mostly talking with people who agree. Worse still is when they believe that their group is <a href="http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Sherif/chap7.htm">pitted against other groups, rather than a part of a political system that has the whole country&#8217;s interests at heart</a>. This will mean going beyong the current 24 hour news cycle driven vituperative personality politics and trying to find bipartisan unity in policy based discourse.</p>

<p>Many figures like Haidt <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/jonathan_haidt_how_common_threats_can_make_common_political_ground.html">want the media to stop feeding into a cycle of partisanship on critical issues</a> like US spending on prison systems, which has liberals denouncing the incaceration rates of ethnic minorities, conservatives concerned at <a href="http://www.rightoncrime.com/the-conservative-case-for-reform/what-conservatives-are-saying/">prisons expenditure risking the bankruptcy of several US states</a> and both concerned at <a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/01/03/rentier-theology/">bribery of the judiciary to raise sentences to increase demand for prison builders</a>.</p>

<p>If smart people can become more aware of their own biases, then they may be more likely to see the things that their subconsious may otherwise ignore, like successful people from racial minorities (or moonwalking bears). Then racism and sexism won&#8217;t be as much of a concern.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('j2odOu0Oguo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/j2odOu0Oguo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('j2odOu0Oguo-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/j2odOu0Oguo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j2odOu0Oguo" id="j2odOu0Oguo" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/j2odOu0Oguo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j2odOu0Oguo" id="j2odOu0Oguo-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Community Clip - Troy & Jeff talk racism/football</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" ></div>
</div>


<p>Online media has the potential to diversify the sources of information that people receive, as well as the potential to propagate <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kP4A6SbRdzM&amp;t=4m37s">extreme crank theories</a>. My belief is that if enough people are able to have a committment to consider the evidence rather than interpret facts though their own filter, then the good will outweigh the bad and most people will benefit from a rational discussion on important issues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fundie Ladies Fashion Advice]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/04/fundie-ladies-fashion/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T02:41:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/04/fundie-ladies-fashion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.stufffundieslike.com/2013/06/a-dress-code">Stuff Fundies Like</a>, the Victory Faith Bible KJV1611 Baptist Church Dress Code for Ladies’ (sic). Yes, there are a huge number of typo&#8217;s (couldn&#8217;t refuse). As the old quote attributed to <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Miriam_A._Ferguson">Miriam A. Ferguson</a> goes, &#8220;If the King&#8217;s English was good enough for Jesus Christ, it&#8217;s good enough for the children of Texas!&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><h4>That which pertaineth to a man</h4>

<p>Ladies’ must abstain from all appearance of evil. That means our ladies’ here at VFBKJV1611 Baptist Church should not where pants or shorts.</p></blockquote>

<p>When your church&#8217;s abbreviated name is a mouthfull, you know the commitee that designed it did a good job listening to every one of the paritioners&#8217;.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Tops</h4>

<p>Blouses and dresses must reach the colorbone and be buttoned all the way up. If the buttons gap open at the bust, ladies’ should go up a size or use safety pins to avoid having their <strong>braziers</strong> showing, which can be very tempting to our young men and therefore inappropriate. Blouses should be full and not darted, which means there should be no ungodly emphasis on the waistline or underbust. Arms should be no shorter than the elbow. Sheer materials should be avoidable, but if you must wear a sheer blouse, also wear a <strong>skin-collared brazier</strong> and a full slip to conceal <strong>you’re nakedness</strong>. Tee shirts, tank tops and other immodest tops are not acceptable.</p></blockquote>

<p>I need to add a new favourite Christian pick up line &#8220;Your brazier gets my brazier going.&#8221; A great one to slip in after &#8220;nice bible&#8221; and &#8220;I&#8217;ve been reading Numbers and I realised I don&#8217;t have yours.&#8221;</p>

<p>By way of explanation: Bra is short for Brassiere, pronounced &#8220;/brəˈzɪər/&#8221; in the US, leading to word completion suggesting &#8220;brazier.&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><h4>Skirts</h4>

<p>Skirts should be at least 3 inches below the knee so that you can sit, kneel and otherwise move around without expositing your knee. Your skirt should also be at least a-line and preferably circle or very full to avoid drawring unnecessary attention to your legs. The waist should hit at your natural waist (low waistts are not acceptable) and be gathered to avoid unnecessary attention to the hips. Your skirt should have no slits. Kick pleats should not be necessary if your skirt is properly full. All <strong>ladies’ should where a slip</strong> with their skirts to avoid immodest exposure that could lead to lustful thoughts.</p></blockquote>

<p>Girls, why stop at the knee length skirts? Why not go to a <a href="http://thefbomb.org/2009/11/corduroy-skirts-are-a-sin/">full length corduroy skirt</a>?</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/corduroy.jpg" alt="Corduroy Skirts are a Sin" /></p>

<blockquote><h4>Culottes</h4>

<p>Box pleat culottes are required for outdoors activities, but <strong>we ask that our ladies’ not where them to services</strong>. Culottes should follow the same rules as skirts and reach at least 3 inches below the knee and be sufficiently full that <strong>we do not see the shape of your legs</strong>. Also, if you canot do it modestly in culottes, you should rethink doing it at all. It may just <strong>not be a ladylike actvitiy</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>And if your daughter starts looking too butch, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zyKw4yKfWOU">tell her off</a></p>

<blockquote><h4>Legs</h4>

<p>We know you have them. We do not want to see them. Please wear nylons or tights to conceal the flesh of your legs. Closed-toed shows are not mandatory, but we do ask our ladies’ to consider the fleshly desires of our gentlemen and dress accordingly. Heels that excessively “bunch up” the calf are nightclub attire, not church attire. Bobby socks and canvas tennis shoes are acceptable for certain functions. Please ask Mrs. Pastor for more information.</p></blockquote>

<p>And so the ladies&#8217; all know that the other ladies&#8217; have legs, which the men never, ever see.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Hair</h4>

<p>The KJV1611 says long hair is a glory. We request that our ladies’ <strong>discuss their hair with their husbands or fathers</strong> to determine the most appropriate hair length for godly glory. Hair should be a natural color (no red, pink or blue, please!) and cut in a flattering, modest manner that does not bring undue attention to our godly ladies heads.</p></blockquote>

<p>What the hell is a woman&#8217;s father doing giving you fashion advice? What would a man know about hair other than &#8220;I&#8217;m sure it looks <strong><em>fine</em></strong>.&#8221; At least they&#8217;re not asking <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2012/06/27/the-ugly-side-of-modesty/">grandpa for advice</a>.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Makeup and jewelry</h4>

<p>Ladies, if the barn needs painting, paint it, but <strong>avoid whoriehs excessiveness</strong>. Lipstick should be natural-colored, and leave the false eyelashes at home! Jewelry should be limited to (one) wedding ring and (one) engagement rink. GOD Himself tells us that peircings are a sign of slaves, not godly women, so skip them!</p></blockquote>

<p>Most any modern Christian would interpret biblical references to slavery as part of a bygone era. <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2013/03/doug-wilsons-race-problem.html">Not so in the wonky world of parochial Southern Christianity</a></p>

<blockquote><h4>Bodies</h4>

<p>We understand that ladies come in all shapes and sizes. That said, ladies who are thin should consider the effect of their vanity on their soles. Ladies who are bigger need to <strong>worry about their husbands’ soles and maybe lose some weight</strong> so their husbands are not tempted to stray. The rest of you ladies need to wear looser-fitting clothes to conceal your hips and other lady areas. We recommend jumpers since these offer the best coverage of (we apologize for our course language) curves.</p></blockquote>

<p>Yeah your husband&#8217;s shoes will wear out if he insists on <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2013/03/15/christian-pastor-i-carry-my-wife-around-the-house-every-day-to-show-her-whos-boss/">carrying you around the house to show you who&#8217;s boss</a></p>

<blockquote><h4>Other</h4>

<p>Any other concerns not already mentioned can be discussed with our godly pastor or any of the deacons, who would be happy to set up a private appointment to discuss your modesty needs or <strong>evaluate a particular outfit</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Something tells me most of these evaluations are not initated by the women themselves.</p>

<blockquote><h4>Visitors</h4>

<p>We understand that nonmebers may arrive wearing inappropriate clothing. Although we are always happy to welcome new people, we do feel it is important to emphasize modesty to protect our men from lustful thoughts. If you notice a visitor lady who is wearing a tight skirt, pants or a low-cut blouse, please let her know we love her as a sister, and <strong>offer her one of our spare sweaters</strong> (they are located in the church foyer’s coat rack) to wear over her top or place over her bottom half while she is sitting.</p></blockquote>

<p>Yes, because nothing will make a young woman in normal, socially acceptable knee length shorts feel comfortable than being told she has to put a borrowed sweater over her legs in a condescending &#8220;we just want the best for you&#8221; manner.</p>

<blockquote><p>We appreciate all our sisters’ in Christ taking the time to keep our church modest! Let us know if there is any way we can support you in this endeavor. </p>

<p>Please sign and date this document to signify your agreement to the dress code.</p></blockquote>

<p>The best part is many right wing Independent Fundamentalist Baptist churches support the <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/English-only_movement">English Only movement</a> and are opposed to immigration reform. Just have a look at some of the &#8221;<a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/teabonics-ridiculous-misspelled-tea-party-protest-signs-gallery-1.1918">Teabonics</a>&#8221; on <a href="http://politicalhumor.about.com/od/funnypictures/ig/Funny-Protest-Signs/">these protest signs</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-only-lanoguage.jpg" alt="protest-only-lanoguage.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-crestwood.jpg" alt="protest-crestwood.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-respect-are-country.jpg" alt="protest-respect-are-country.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-thank-you-fox-infromed.jpg" alt="protest-thank-you-fox-infromed.jpg" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-silent.jpg" alt="protest-silent.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-no-amnety.jpg" alt="protest-no-amnety.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-extremey-amesty.jpg" alt="protest-extremey-amesty.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-20-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-20-jpg.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-illiterate-protester.jpg" alt="protest-illiterate-protester.jpg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-18-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-18-jpg.jpg" /></p>

<p>Apparently Illegals are bad, but dressing like Popeye is fantastic.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-22-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-22-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-27-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-27-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-28-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-28-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/gal-teabonics-29-jpg.jpg" alt="gal-teabonics-29-jpg.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-birth-certifict.jpg" alt="protest-birth-certifict.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-computer.jpg" alt="protest-computer.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-gay-marridged.jpg" alt="protest-gay-marridged.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-homescholers-for-perry.jpg" alt="protest-homescholers-for-perry.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-mitt-fix-washinton.jpg" alt="protest-mitt-fix-washinton.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-morans.jpg" alt="protest-morans.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-obama-read-the-consitution.jpg" alt="protest-obama-read-the-consitution.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-teachchildren.jpg" alt="protest-teachchildren.jpg" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/protest-teabagging-jesus-democracy.jpg" alt="protest-teabagging-jesus-democracy.jpg" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creationism is Stupid!]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/01/creationism-is-stupid/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-01T17:18:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/06/01/creationism-is-stupid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My latest video, <a href="http://youtu.be/PaimSZ2JDY0">Creationism is Stupid!</a></p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('PaimSZ2JDY0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/PaimSZ2JDY0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('PaimSZ2JDY0-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/PaimSZ2JDY0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PaimSZ2JDY0" id="PaimSZ2JDY0" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/PaimSZ2JDY0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PaimSZ2JDY0" id="PaimSZ2JDY0-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Creationism is Stupid!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Ken Ham, Kent Hovind and the banana man Ray Comfort give their most convincing presentation as to why the earth was definitely created 2000 years after the Sumerians invented glue.</div>
</div>


<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/evolution-sin.jpg" alt="Evolution Causes Sin" /></p>

<p>And here&#8217;s a car powered by fossil fuels driven by a fossil fool:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/evolution-fossils.jpg" alt="Evolution is a Fairy Tale, Apparently" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Evolution is True]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/31/why-evolution-is-true/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-31T19:03:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/31/why-evolution-is-true</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Answering Creation Ministries&#8217;s Questions</h3>

<p>Creation Ministries International run a &#8220;Question Evolution&#8221; campaign, handing out a pamphlet that asks 15 supposedly &#8220;unanswerable&#8221; questions about evolution. This article by <a href="http://www.morganstorey.com/">Morgan Storey</a>, seeks to answer all their questions, with references to find more information. You will have to do some research on your own, that is what science is about: doing the leg work to find out for yourself, nothing is handed to you on a silver platter or in a pretty leather bound book.</p>

<h3>15 questions for &#8220;Evolutionists&#8221; answered.</h3>

<p>Firstly we are not evolutionists; there are people who accept evolution and those that reject it. It would be like saying <a href="http://www.philvaz.com/apologetics/p67.htm">gravityists</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germ_theory_of_disease">germists</a>.</p>

<h3>1. How did life originate?</h3>

<p>A good question to be sure, but not actually an answer for the theory of evolution. As answering how the stars accreted isn&#8217;t an answer for the theory of gravity.</p>

<p>But to answer this, the current field that studies this is a field somewhere between chemistry and biology called abiogenesis. It studies how biological chemicals can form in different environments. Famous experiments such as the Miller-Urey experiment have shown that biological chemicals can form. More recent experiments of this nature have shown more complex biological chemicals forming such as proteins and long chain acid molecules similar to the precursor to DNA, RNA.</p>

<p>There is no definitive answer for how life originated on earth, it is very difficult for this kind of life to have survived till now for us to study it and primitive life would more than likely have not left fossils and even if they did due to subduction these fossils would no longer be accessible, or may have been destroyed by as the earth they were embedded in subducted back into the magma of the mantle.</p>

<h3>2. How did the DNA code originate?</h3>

<p>Again not the area of evolution. Evolution works via Natural selection on existing life, or even on the precursor which is not considered alive RNA. It is likely that DNA originated from RNA as DNA is simply a more stable double-helix over RNA&#8217;s single. But we don&#8217;t know, RNA/DNA is not fossilized as it decays too quickly, and it is unlikely that any primitive DNA/RNA transition will be found. There have been recent experiments that have shown XNA an even more stable triple-helix that never evolved on earth from the life we have today. The reason is very interesting. Although <a href="http://io9.com/5903221/meet-xna-the-first-synthetic-dna-that-evolves-like-the-real-thing">XNA</a> is less prone to copying errors and mutations it would also take a lot longer to evolve in changes, so it sacrifices its ability to change for stability. Obviously the balance was struck with DNA or XNA simply never formed.</p>

<p>Long answer short, we don&#8217;t know. That doesn&#8217;t mean it can&#8217;t be one of our simply answers rather than adding a complexity of a designer.</p>

<p>See also: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xeno_nucleic_acid">Xeno Nucleic Acid</a>.</p>

<h3>3. How could mutations-accidental copying mistakes create the huge volumes of information in the DNA of living things?</h3>

<p>This is a little misleading, DNA isn&#8217;t a code. It is a strand of molecules; it is only given a code so that we humans can understand it. It is translated by other chemical reactions in the cells that they occupy. But the mutations caused during life and passed on as well as the copying mistakes can add information. As any computer scientists knows if you copy multiple files in the wrong way you can combine them together going from 2 files to one much larger one. This has happened in biological DNA, human’s ancestors the old world apes have one more pair of chromosomes over humans, this was not understood for a long time and then it was found. The ends of chromosomes have these things called telomeres that stop the copying process when a strand is being duplicated; they mark the end of the strand. These have been found in the middle of a pair of human chromosomes, bearing the same markers as two pair in our nearest cousins the chimps. The chromosome pair at some stage fused too form one instead of two. Giving more DNA to the single chromosome and allowing for natural selection to work on a bigger selection of traits.</p>

<p>Not all traits from mutations are negative. There have been people found who have a <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/evolution/library/10/4/l_104_05.html">mutation that makes them immune to the HIV virus</a>, others in a <a href="http://phys.org/news101624600.html">small town in Italy that metabolise cholesterol so well that they never have a heart attack from their cholesterol rich diets</a>.</p>

<p>Others such as <a href="http://discovermagazine.com/2007/apr/the-upside-of-color-blindness/">colour blindness</a> and schizophrenia are being investigated for advantages regardless of the negatives, e.g. colour blind individuals can pick out camouflaged animals where others can&#8217;t.</p>

<p>See also: <a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn14094-bacteria-make-major-evolutionary">New Scientist &#8220;Bacteria make major evolutionary shift in the lab&#8221;</a></p>

<h3>4. Why is natural selection taught as if it explains the origins and diversity of life?</h3>

<p>It does explain the origin of our lives and the diversity of life we see around us. There is evidence in many species of its evolution; we have fossil evolutionary evidence for horses, wales, and of course humans. If you have a better hypothesis that explains all the current evidence and doesn&#8217;t add any extra complicated variables then propose it and it will be tested by other scientists, they will either find evidence for it, or none. If evidence cannot be found then it is un-falsifiable and simply bad science.</p>

<h3>5. How did the biochemical pathways, which involve multiple enzymes working together in sequence originate?</h3>

<p>You go from very simply worded questions to one like this, which seems like you want to throw people off your scent. But regardless, you are describing irreducible complexity inside cells. Which is something that is being actively studied, however evolution has had billions of years to build all of this up we have had only a couple hundred years. So we don&#8217;t know exactly, some of these enzymes and proteins may have evolved simultaneously from earlier simpler proteins and enzymes, in earlier and more primitive cells. This is what we see in extremophiles, but more study is required. Would you abandon your faith if it were discovered how these proteins and enzymes evolved, if not then you can&#8217;t use this argument.</p>

<p>References: <a href="http://www.sciencecodex.com/u_of_minn_researchers_unveil_first_artificial_enzyme_created_by_evolution_in_a_test_tube-105949">Researchers unveil first artificial enzyme created by evolution in a test tube</a></p>

<h3>6. Living things look like they were designed, how do evolutionists know they were not designed?</h3>

<p>Ok so things I guess could look designed&#8230; by a very <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argument_from_poor_design">bad designer</a>. The heart in a human has too few arteries to supply it with enough blood for it be as efficient as it should be for a land animal; it is fine for marine animals. Similar for the placement of spine along the back for an upright walker and the lack of extra sets of teeth for an animal such as us that lives so long, not to mention the laryngeal nerve that I am sure you have heard of, that runs from brain to voice box to allow all animals to control its muscles, except it makes a detour below the heart which is a lot longer than needed for humans, but think about the poor Giraffes where the detour is 18feet.</p>

<p>The universe is really not designed for us, most of it is deadly to us, too close to a star, neutron star, black hole, or galactic core and you will die, the blackness of space at a whopping 2.7Kelvin or -270.45 degrees Celsius (-454.81F) not to mention trillions of wandering asteroids and planets the size of Jupiter ready to wipe us out.</p>

<p>But even if all these design flaws didn&#8217;t exist then so what, it looks designed. Maybe we design things that look like nature because we are a part of it; we can&#8217;t design anything to not look like nature as we have no experience with things that aren&#8217;t part of nature.</p>

<h3>7. How did multi-cellular life originate?</h3>

<p>This is pretty simple. This is like saying how did humans and other animals work out that living and working together in packs, heards or tribes increased our chances for survival. We already see bacterial colonies that are colonies of lots of individual cells of bacteria working and living together, why not pool resources and specialise some bacteria to take in food and others to expel waste?</p>

<h3>8. How did sex originate?</h3>

<p>Interestingly we don&#8217;t know exactly. Again this <a href="http://talkorigins.org/indexcc/CB/CB350.html">probably originated early on in life’s development</a>, as some forms of bacteria don&#8217;t procreate asexually, some procreate with DNA from another party, some are not just binary male and female, but multi-sexed, having up to 7 different sexes, all of which need to come together to make an offspring. But larger than bacterially we are pretty much limited to the binary male and female. Though some switch such as certain fish and amphibians and for example the whip tail lizard and some lie along the gender path such as humans who can be born with both male and female genitalia, although a lot of these are non-functional there have been instances of functioning intersex humans.</p>

<p>The point is binary sexuality is a myth that has been perpetuated due to its prevalence not its truth. Many animals <a href="http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2013/04/accessible-res-snail-sex.html">can reproduce sexually and asexually</a>. Different genders of more than one do show better diversity and thus higher likelihood of passing on successful mutations such as the aforementioned HIV and cholesterol advantages. But obviously higher than two can be difficult to organise for the animals affected so it wasn&#8217;t as successful.</p>

<h3>9. Why are the expected countless millions of transitional fossils missing?</h3>

<p>This is a double whammy misconception; Every fossil ever found is a link between older and newer forms, so every fossil is a <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Transitional_fossils">transitional fossil</a>, your bones according to evolutionary theory are a transitional fossil of your father to your child. If you don&#8217;t have kids then you are an evolutionary dead end. It happens with surnames as it happened with our ancestors such as homo neanderthalis (to some extent, they did interbreed with us a little too).</p>

<p>Many transitional forms have been found that closed parts of the fossil record that were previously accused of having &#8220;gaps&#8221;.<br/>
In fact, in the century-and-a-half since then, we’ve found millions of
evolutionary intermediaries in the fossil record, much more than Darwin
said he could reasonably hope for. The transitional fossils that have
been found (such as <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Tiktaalik" title="Tiktaalik">Tiktaalik</a>,
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Ichthyostega" title="Ichthyostega">Ichthyostega</a>,
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Australopithecus" title="Australopithecus">Australopithecus</a>, <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Homo_habilis" title="Homo habilis">Homo
habilis</a>,
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Archaeopteryx" title="Archaeopteryx">Archaeopteryx</a>,
the <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Microraptor" title="Microraptor">Microraptor</a> and so on) provide clear evidence of transitions, in this case from water to
land and from land to flight. There are three different types of
transitional forms and we have ample examples of each. But creationists
still insist that we’ve never found a single one, because what they
usually ask us to present are impossible parodies which evolution would
neither produce nor permit (such as the
<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Crocoduck" title="Crocoduck">Crocoduck</a>).</p>

<p>Evolution doesn&#8217;t dictate we would find fossils at all, that is geology. Fossilization is a very rare process so the fact we have any fossils at all is amazing. The missing fossils you talk of may always be missing, it doesn&#8217;t discredit the theory, it just means we realise our limitations of finding fossils at other records such as genetic evidence.</p>

<p>You say all the missing links are imagined, but that is just plain wrong you can go to your local natural history museum and see replicas of the skulls and sometimes entire skeletons of our ancestors. We have found hundreds of examples of some of these ancestors and the documentation and photographic evidence is in biological textbooks, physical evidence is available at some of the luckier natural history museums and research facilities. As like other fossils they are rare and expensive.</p>

<h3>10. How do &#8220;living Fossils&#8221; remain unchanged over supposed hundreds of millions of years if evolution has changed worms into humans in the same time frame?</h3>

<p>In the same time frame it turned the same worms into lions and elephants and whales and fish. These &#8221;<a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Living_fossil">living fossils</a>&#8221; are called that as at least their initial outward appearance appears not to have changed, but new evidence suggests they have. Science changes it views based on what is observed, it is not afraid to admit it is wrong. The most famous &#8220;living fossil&#8221; the coelacanths is a fish that has found a very good niche so has had little selective pressure to change greatly from it hundred million year old ancestor, but it has changed according to recent research. Incidentally genetically its common ancestor with earth worms is the same as humans 782.7 million years ago roughly. So this and other &#8220;living fossils&#8221; simply have found a niche and a stable spot in the food change where any mutation that is beneficial to a changed environment will not help them so it doesn&#8217;t bread true.</p>

<p>References:
* http://timetree.org/index.php?taxon_a=Lumbricina&amp;taxon_b=homo+sapien&amp;submit=Search
* http://timetree.org/index.php?taxon_a=Lumbricina&amp;taxon_b=lion&amp;submit=Search
* http://timetree.org/index.php?found_taxon_a=6391|Lumbricina&amp;found_taxon_b=9783|elephant
* http://timetree.org/index.php?taxon_a=Lumbricina&amp;taxon_b=blue+whale&amp;submit=Search
* http://timetree.org/index.php?found_taxon_a=6391|Lumbricina&amp;found_taxon_b=7894|coelacanths</p>

<h3>11. How did blind chemistry create mind/intelligence, meaning, altruism and morality?</h3>

<p>Blind chemistry didn&#8217;t. Chemistry was probably the start of the precursor to life, but after that natural selection and evolution took over. It evolved in varying traits that where advantageous, such as communally living bacteria, then communally living animals such as schools of fish, then fish that where more cunning may have survived to pass on their DNA and been selected for, and intelligence built. This is why things like octopus can remember how to open jars as they can remember how to hide in certain types of coral and open certain types of shells to get to the tasty molluscs inside.</p>

<p>Morality and altruism is the realm of evolutionary psychologists, a relatively new field that has proposed various methods to answer how these features of our intelligence are advantageous in a community such as the ones humans and other animals form. The same reason piranha do not attack each other during a frenzy is the same reason we will assist our neighbour.</p>

<p>Life is not meaningless; it has whatever meaning you deign to it. If you give your life meaning through charity and altruism then society deems you a good person, if you give it through theft and crime society will punish you through the secular law system. The legal system has been built up by people not wanting others to treat them in such a manner, similar to the Christian golden rule but modified to allow for outliers such as those that may enjoy giving or receiving pain. The better version of the golden rule is &#8220;Do unto others as they would have you do unto them&#8221;.</p>

<p>So although some parts of morality and altruism are evolved others are learnt and passed down from parent to child. There are tribes that believe it is perfectly fine to kill unruly children and that anyone over 30 is not a member of the tribe. This does lead to a kind of moral relativism, but most ethicists will agree that what is moral is what causes the least amount of harm, and not caring for your young or elderly does cause harm to them, whereas caring for them causes in most circumstances almost no harm.</p>

<p>Morals are relative; it is not ok to kill&#8230; unless the person you are killing is threatening you or a loved one’s life. It is not ok to steal&#8230; unless if you don&#8217;t you or a loved one will die. It is not ok to lie&#8230; unless if you do so others will be harmed as I am sure a German harbouring Jews in WW2 would have realised.</p>

<p>References: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_psychology#Principles
http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/the-nature-nurture-nietzsche-blog/201005/did-morality-evolve</p>

<h3>12. Why is this evolutionary &#8220;just-so&#8221; story telling tolerated?</h3>

<p>This is really a loaded question, these aren&#8217;t just-so stories they are different stories that describe the entirety of our species. Kind of like the 3 blind-men describing an elephant, one grabs the trunk and describes it is a powerful type of snake, another feels the leg and describes a tree, another feels the feathery tale and describes a bird, all are wrong by themselves, but together their picture is of an elephant.</p>

<p>The stories talked about here are just-so as there is a huge pool of humans that these DNA sequences play out. Even in recorded history there were millions of us on the planet, this diversity is what has made us strong as a species. Some of us have blue eyes and thus better vision during the night and overcast winters, others have brown eyes with better vision during the day, this diversity and communal living means we are more likely to survive as a species as a single disease can&#8217;t come through a wipe us out, and different people can have different specialties.</p>

<h3>13. Where are the scientific breakthroughs due to evolution?</h3>

<p>The quote used here is what is called quote mining; Dr Kirschner is actually complaining here that there is little interdisciplinary work with other biologists. Biologists need a grounding in evolution to truly understand and model every experiment they perform.</p>

<p>Norman Borlaug in 1970 was awarded the Nobel Prize for his use of evolutionary theory to create crops that have so far saved possibly billions of lives.</p>

<p>Every year the flu shot that is given out is due to the use of evolutionary theory to determine how influenza strains will change in the coming year, the same is done for new strains of existing vaccinated diseases.</p>

<p>References:
* http://archive.truthout.org/article/missing-links
* http://journal.9med.net/qikan/article.php?id=224499</p>

<h3>14. Science involves experimenting to figure out how things work; how they operate. Why is evolution, a theory about HISTORY, taught as if it is the same as OPERATIONAL science?</h3>

<p>Firstly I don&#8217;t think theory means what you think it means. In science when you pluck an idea out of the air you have a hypothesis, not a theory. When your hypothesis is able to fail a test as in it is falsifiable and you have a lot of evidence backing a hypothesis and you have had your hypothesis tested by others and then you get it test a fair few more times, then and only then can you call it a theory. Looking at the numbers for example for the recently failed faster than light Tau Neutrino hypothesis they did 50,000 tests of their hypothesis before they released a paper for others to attempt to replicate or fail the experiment. They were quickly dismissed as the result couldn&#8217;t be replicated and they re-checked and re-checked their equipment and found the flaw&#8230; literally a loose wire.</p>

<p>Evolution via natural selection has been tested millions of times; errors have been found and corrected. The theory has changed, you may say due to this selective pressure it has evolved.
References: http://www.nature.com/news/flaws-found-in-faster-than-light-neutrino-measurement-1.10099</p>

<h3>15. Why is a fundamentally religious idea, a dogmatic belief system that fails to explain the evidence, taught in science classes?</h3>

<p>Sorry but I think I have shown how it explains the evidence, Darwin’s original hypothesis is testable and falsifiable, if no change where found in species, if a rabbit was found in strata of the pre-Cambrian it would be false and we would have to go back to the drawing board. If no way to transmit changes down from mother to child where discovered then it would be false, remembering that genes where not discovered till well after Darwin’s death, he was vindicated there.</p>

<p>Besides it is science, science isn&#8217;t about the comfortable or reassuring it is about what is true, even though evolution may not be comforting or reassuring to your beliefs it has shown to be true so far. If a better hypothesis comes along that explains the facts better, is tried tested and wins in the battle between scientific ideas then it will be the latest answer. But all evidence points to that not being much off what evolution via natural selection currently is.</p>

<p>I think teaching creation &#8220;theory&#8221; in a science class is the same as teaching the aforementioned phrenology in a neurology class, or teaching the stalk theory of birth in a sex-ed class, it is ludicrous and damaging to our children’s future. I know our kids are bright, they can take the idea of evolution and marvel and the grandeur and luck they have to just be here out of the literally billions upon billions of other DNA combinations that could have happened in their place.</p>

<p>Who is responsible for this pamphlet?
Sydney atheists care of www.sydneyatheists.org have used the design as a commentary on the original under fair use and thus they are responsible.</p>

<p>Although we are atheists, we care about what is true. We would prefer you believed the truth about our origins and believed in a god or gods than believe a falsity such as creation and also believe in God. Literal bible belief carries with it baggage no one wants, and will only lead to fundamentalism of a scale that will lead to war and violence.</p>

<p>We are happy to answer any of your questions via email to contact@sydneyatheist.org or via our Facebook group or page. Alternatively you can contact your local free thought group to see if they can assist you via http://atheist.meetup.com</p>

<p>Further reading: <a href="http://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Question_Evolution">Rational Wiki</a>, <a href="http://www.proof-of-evolution.com/anti-evolution-drive-by-posting.html">Proof of Evolution.com</a>, <a href="http://blog.timparkinson.net/2011/09/12/answering-the-15-questions/">Answering the 15 questions</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Red State Christianity]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/23/red-state-christianity/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T04:32:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/23/red-state-christianity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Everything Is Terrible has dug up an awful Chrsitian cowboy VHS</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('BQL_q-oJB_g');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BQL_q-oJB_g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('BQL_q-oJB_g-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/BQL_q-oJB_g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQL_q-oJB_g" id="BQL_q-oJB_g" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/BQL_q-oJB_g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQL_q-oJB_g" id="BQL_q-oJB_g-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">EIT! ANSWERS PRAYER!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Religion Week at http://www.everythingisterrible.com</div>
</div>


<p>Steven Pinker in an <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/24/why-are-states-so-red-and-blue/">opinion piece</a> suggested that the reason America is so polically and socially diverse. He argues that Blue states were largely settled by English farmers, while Red states by Scots-Irish herders.</p>

<blockquote><p>Societies that herd livestock in rugged terrain tend to develop a “culture of honor.” Since their wealth has feet and can be stolen in an eye blink, they are forced to deter rustlers by cultivating a hair-trigger for violent retaliation against any trespass or insult that probes their resolve. Farmers can afford to be less belligerent because it is harder to steal their land out from under them, particularly in territories within the reach of law enforcement&#8230; Southerners today continue to manifest a culture of honor which legitimizes violent retaliation</p></blockquote>

<p>Pinker notes that under traditional, rugged societies violent and aggressive men were meant to be civilised by a churchgoing woman.</p>

<blockquote><p>Another cliché of the cowboy movies also had an element of historical truth. As more women moved west, they worked to end the lifestyle of brawling, boozing and whoring they found there, joining forces with the officials in charge of the rowdy settlements. They found a natural ally in the church, with its co-ed membership, norms of temperance and Sunday morning discipline.  By the time the government consolidated its control over the West&#8230; the norms of self-defense through masculine honor, and the restraint of ruffianism by women and church, had taken root.</p></blockquote>

<p>Many Southern Baptists continue with a frontier tradition of distrusting and resenting government (especially federal) laws that restrict personal freedoms, they readily believe that arbitrary and pointless church rules are good for them. It&#8217;s this type of political climate that breeds <a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/01/03/rentier-theology/">strange bedfellows, with the Religious Right co-opting both religion and politics</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anti Vaccine Misinformation Puts NSW Children at Risk]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/20/anti-vax-misinformation/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T03:15:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/05/20/anti-vax-misinformation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to a new study, reported in The Age, <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/national/health/worry-grows-over-safety-of-childhood-jabs-20130519-2juvt.html">53% of Australian parents have concerns about vaccinating their children</a>.</p>

<p>The NSW opposition is considering allowing childcare centres <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-05-19/push-to-ban-unvaccinated-children-from-nsw-preschools/4698786">ban unvaccinated individuals</a>. The opposition states that immunisation rates are lower than in Rwanda and Iran. Looking the stats up, it&#8217;s true. <a href="http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.IMM.MEAS/countries">WHO data on measels immunisation</a> show that 94% of Australian children are immunised, compared to 99% in Iran and 95% in Rwanda. <a href="http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.IMM.IDPT/countries">WHO data on Diptheria, Pertussis and Tetanus immunisation</a> shows 92% of Australian children are immunised, compared to 99% in Iran and 97% in Rwanda. <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/opinion/political-news/rwanda-trounces-australia-at-immunisation-20130529-2nc5n.html">Eritrea and Bangladesh also have higher immunisation rates</a></p>

<p>There were <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/measles.asp">172 cases of measles in NSW in 2012</a>, <a href="http://www.wahs.nsw.gov.au/news/2012/20121004_00.html">requiring the opening of new health centres to distribute the Mesles, Mumps and Rubella vaccine</a>. Rubella is rare, with less than <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/rubella.asp">6 new notifications</a> a month, Mumps spiked to <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/mumps.asp">24 cases in June 2012</a>. Pertussis (Whooping Cough) has trended downwards from around 2,000 new cases being reported in January 2009 to <a href="http://www0.health.nsw.gov.au/data/diseases/pertussis.asp">less than 200 new cases a month in 2013</a>. Lack of concern about diseases like Whooping Cough may be a byproduct of good public health measures to prevent curtail the disease.</p>

<p>Data from Medicare show that NSW and WA have <a href="http://www.medicareaustralia.gov.au/provider/patients/acir/statistics.jsp">the lowest immunisation rates</a> with 89.3% of WA children 60-63 months of age. There are communities with less than <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-04-11/children-across-australia-not-fully-imunised/4622666">85% of children vaccinated, with 77,000 not fully immunised nationally</a>. Pockets in <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-03-20/anti-vaccination-campaigns-threaten-measles-free-status/4584514">northern NSW and southern QLD are at greatest risk</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Dr MacIntyre says some parts of Australia have a greater risk of a measles outbreak because of lower immunisation rates, such as northern New South Wales and southern Queensland.</p>

<p>Australian Medical Association (AMA) president Steve Hambleton says it is those areas which threaten Australia&#8217;s position.</p>

<p>&#8220;Our [measles] elimination status is under threat because there are pockets of decreasing immunisation of our children,&#8221; he said.</p></blockquote>

<p>Some affluent areas in Sydney also have <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-04-11/low-immunisation-rates-in-affluent-sydney/4622634">lower immunisation rates</a>
Unfortunately fear campaigns like Meryl Dorey&#8217;s Australian Vaccination Network have scared a small number (2%) of parents into rejecting vaccines, and a large proportion of parents feel a concern. Around 8% of parents don&#8217;t fully vaccinate their children, and would benefit from a public health campaign that listens to their concerns and tries to address them.</p>

<p>NSW Health minister Tanya Plibersek has launched a booklet &#8220;Immunisation Myths And Realities&#8221; and advised parents &#8221;<a href="http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/dr-google-cant-be-trusted-with-childs-health/story-e6frg6n6-1226650596663">Dr Google has been a negative influence</a>&#8221;. My opinion is that NSW Health and the AMA should be more proactive in online media, taking out ads on search results for searches like &#8216;vaccination&#8217; to make sure that correct information comes up before the AVN&#8217;s fearmongering, as while &#8220;Dr Google&#8221; may be prone to misinformation, the reality is that more and more parents will turn to it.</p>

<p>In the past it was possible to tell parents &#8220;just trust your GP and do what they say&#8221;. It may be more helpful, in future, to ensure that GPs listen to their patients to maintain high levels of trust in the public health system in an era of consumer focussed medicine and online misinformation campaigns.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I'm an atheist]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/04/26/atheist/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-26T23:19:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/04/26/atheist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this month shocking news broke that <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-05-07/women-missing-for-years-found-alive-in-house/4674150">three women who had been adbucted and imprisoned for nine to twelve whole years had escaped</a>. Michelle Knight was kidnapped in 2002 aged 20, Gina DeJesus was 14 when she was kidnapped. Some of the women had childen by their captor, and Michelle Knight reportedly was forced to deliver them in unsanitary conditions, without any training. The women were rescued when a neighbor, who happened to have the day off, heard one of their screams and kicked down part of the door.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('axCn04iXkBg');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/axCn04iXkBg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('axCn04iXkBg-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/axCn04iXkBg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=axCn04iXkBg" id="axCn04iXkBg" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/axCn04iXkBg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=axCn04iXkBg" id="axCn04iXkBg-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Charles Ramsey interview, rescuer of Amanda Berry, Gina DeJesus and Michelle Knight in Cleveland</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >CLEVELAND - After going missing more than 10 years ago, Amanda Berry shouted to a man from a Seymour Avenue house on Monday.
Charles Ramsey and Angel Cordero broke down the door and freed Berry, who was 16 when she disappeared in 2003. Cordero told NewsChannel5&#8217;s Stephanie Ramirez that he recognized Berry from posters and that she was with a 4 or 5-year-old child.

Other victims Michelle Knight and Gina DeJesus.


Read more: http://www.newsnet5.com/dpp/news/local_news/cleveland_metro/cleveland-man-who-found-missing-woman-amanda-berry-i-thought-that-girl-was-dead#ixzz2ScUmj9qm</div>
</div>


<p>The neighbor, Charles Ramsey, had lived next door for a full year and ate together with the captor, with no idea what was happening inside the home. While the media says that he&#8217;s a hero, he insists that anyone else would have done the same thing in the circumstances. What has haunted him, however, was the knowledge that he could have intervened much earlier had he known.</p>

<p>One of the girls, Amanda Berry, had her face all over the news when she was kidnapped in 2003. Berry&#8217;s mother refused to give up hope of finding her daughter alive for 19 months, until she turned to a &#8220;psychic&#8221; who told her &#8221;<a href="http://www.cleveland.com/metro/index.ssf/2013/05/amanda_berry_is_dead_psychic_t.html">She’s not alive, honey</a>.&#8221; The poor woman died in 2006, never knowing that her daughter was alive.</p>

<p>On learning of her niece&#8217;s freedom, Georgina DeJesus&#8217;s aunt proclaimed that the rescue was a miracle, and &#8221;<a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/cheats/2013/05/08/cleveland-women-were-chained.html">God works in mysterious ways</a>&#8221;. One of the more disturbing revelations is that the rapist <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2013/may/08/cleveland-ariel-castro-child-abduction">was a school bus driver investigated by police in 2004 for abduction and endangering children</a> after he kept a boy on his school bus for two hours. Police officers turned up to the abductor&#8217;s home months before he kidnapped DeJesus, but left after nobody answered their knocks on the door. This is much like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kidnapping_of_Jaycee_Lee_Dugard#Missed_opportunities_to_rescue_Dugard">Jaycee Lee Dugard</a> case, where three years before the abducted girl was rescued, a neighbor informed the police there were tents in the abductor&#8217;s backyard with children living in them. Police talked with the abductor for 30 minutes on the property, but never searched it. After Dugard&#8217;s rescue, she was awarded a settlement of $20 million dollars from the Californian government for their mishandling of the case. Many people talk about the rescue of the girls being a miracle, and yet in both cases we see god failing to nudge the police in the right direction years before.</p>

<p>Consider this scenario: if you found a neighbor begging and pleading to escape the house, whould you intervene by kicking down the door straight away? Or if you would wait to let the captor free the girls of his own accord, how long would you wait for? Now consider: if you were God, would you intervene straight away if you heard a captive&#8217;s pleas? Would you choose to violate the captor&#8217;s free will in order to protect the women? If you would intervene straight away, why didn&#8217;t God intervene for Michelle Knight for over 12 years?</p>

<p>William Lane Craig defines God <a href="http://www.skepticink.com/reasonablyfaithless/2013/01/01/arguing-about-ontology/">in this way</a>: “God is, by definition, the greatest being conceivable.” Can you conceive of a God that doesn&#8217;t take 12 years to hear the cry of an abducted girl? Then it would seem that you can conceive of a greater being than the one Dr Craig believes in.</p>

<p>To me, the God of the Old Testament seems like a capricious and vindictive sort of character. Can you imagine a god that doesn&#8217;t endorse <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=deut21.10-14&amp;version=NET">sex slavery for widows</a> or the <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=num31&amp;version=NET">enslavement of 32,000 virgins for the enjoyment of Israelite soldiers as part of their &#8220;booty&#8221;</a>? What about a god that doesn&#8217;t <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/may/30/christian-fundamentalists-plan-teach-genocide">order the slaughter of Amalekite men, women and children</a> (often taught as a <a href="https://intrinsicdignity.wordpress.com/2010/04/19/good-news-club-on-the-slaughter-of-the-amalekites/">lesson in <em>complete</em> obedience</a>)? If you can imagine a deity without any of these bloodthirsty traits then by Dr Craig&#8217;s logic you&#8217;ve disproven the Old Testament god is the one true God.</p>

<p>What if you don&#8217;t like Paul&#8217;s views on <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1pet2.18;tit2.9;eph6.5-8&amp;version=NET">slaves</a>, <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=eph5.22-24&amp;version=NET">women</a> or <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1ti1.8-10;1cor6.9-10;rom1.18-32&amp;version=NET">gays</a>? Simple, just start your own faith tradition to worship your own interpretation of the Christian god. There are between <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian#Demographics">38,000</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Christian_denominations">41,000 Christian denominations</a> in the world, more than the <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=number%20of%20sentences%20in%20the%20bible">33,829 sentences in the KJV</a>. Some of these denominations are the same movement in different countries, but the figures show Christians have a wide diversity of opinion not just on liturgy but on core beliefs like the inspiration of scripture, the divinity of Jesus, the existence of hell, the role (if any) of baptism and any methods of salvation.</p>

<p>Protestants maintain that the only thing necessary for belief is scripture alone (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sola_scriptura">Sola Scriptura</a>).
If Protestantism is true, and a key part of Protestant Christian experience is reading the bible, why
did it take so long to invent a printing press? Why didn&#8217;t Yahweh pop one in at the first council of Nicea in 325 CE when they established biblical cannon?</p>

<p>If Jesus was the incarnation of the Logos of a triune godhead, did he have omniscience to see the future? Could he see that <a href="http://www.errancywiki.com/index.php?title=Legends2">5 different endings to Mark would be added by five different scribes</a>? Why didn&#8217;t he give his disciples an approved, inerrant version of his teachings? If salvation from an eternal torment in conscious pain requires the accurate transmission of scripture, why didn&#8217;t God ensure that the scripture could be accurately copied and transmitted from the very start of the early Church? Couldn&#8217;t that have minimised the number of differences of opinion between denominations?</p>

<p>Even in an age when most Chrisitans do have 4-7 bibles in their home, most don&#8217;t read them. In one study, 10% of Americans thought that <a href="http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2007/0704.balmer.html">Noah&#8217;s wife was Joan of Arc, and two thirds thought Billy Graham preached the Sermon on the Mount</a>. Most people&#8217;s favourite &#8220;bible verse&#8221; was &#8220;God helps those who help themselves.&#8221; Less than half of Americans could name one of the gospels, and only a third could name all four. It&#8217;s this kind of ignorance that leads to one of the best known quotes of Jesus saying &#8220;the poor you will always have among you&#8221; being <a href="www.smh.com.au/opinion/bible-bashing-the-homeless-abbott-style-20100215-o2tj.html">used to oppose aid for the poor</a> despite the fact that Jesus said it in the house of <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matt26.6-13;mark14.3-9&amp;version=NET">Simon the leper</a> while eating with <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=jn12.1-8&amp;version=NET">Lazarus, who he raised from the dead</a>.</p>

<p>Ironically, in a time of rising illiteracy, we also see conservatives demanding belief in <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/exploringourmatrix/2012/06/ken-ham-wants-other-christians-to-be-con-artists-like-he-is.html">young earth creationism</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Baptist_Convention_conservative_resurgence">inerrancy</a> of scripture (not infallability), bordering on &#8221;<a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/peterenns/2012/03/guest-post-the-culture-of-biblical-inerrantism/">biblicalism</a>&#8221;.</p>

<p>If Jesus had omniscience, could he fortell of the <a href="http://debunkingchristianity.blogspot.com.au/2012/11/god-science-and-black-death-plague.html">millions that would die in the Black Plague</a>? Could he fortell that it would take the scientific method centuries after the plague to understand how to stop the spread of disease? He decided to let people know that hell burns eternally at <a href="http://www.lhup.edu/~dsimanek/hell.htm">the boiling point of Sulfur, 444.6 degrees Celcius</a>, but did he tell people how long to boil water for to sterilise surgical tools?</p>

<p>When Republican Senate candidate Richard Mourdock said pregnancy resulting from rape is something “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wl9e-f6nbd4">God intended to happen</a>,” it lead many to ask the question; does that mean the rape is something God intended to happen? Medicine has established the germ theory of disease (still denied by Mary Bakker Eddy&#8217;s Christian Science cult) only from studying dead bodies. If it&#8217;s God&#8217;s will that modern medicine be able to treat sick people so that our Western life expectancies are many times what they were in the dark ages, did God preordain doctors to treat people? And if they needed cadavres to research, did God preordain that the knowledge would be gained from deaths?  If God has given us knowledge and the ability to use logic, why not give us the brains to innovate faster and prevent unnecessary deaths?</p>

<p>Consider how bad medical knowledge was throughout the dark ages. Carl Sagan writes in The Demon Haunted World:</p>

<blockquote><p>Pre-modern medical practice did not save many. Queen
Anne was the last Stuart monarch of Great Britain. In the last seventeen
years of the seventeenth century, she was pregnant eighteen times. Only five
children were born alive. Only one of them survived infancy. He died before
reaching adulthood, and before her coronation in 1702. There seems to be no
evidence of some genetic disorder. She had the best medical care money
could buy.</p></blockquote>

<p>If God could have providentially sent scientists at any point in human history, why wait over a millennium to give humans the germ theory of disease? Why wait until after Queen Anne&#8217;s demise to give humans knowledge of Obstetrics and Gynecology?</p>

<p>Personally, I don&#8217;t find myself able to believe that there is any God capable of influencing the world today. It seems more likely that humans have picked themselves up by their bootstraps, and while religion continues to <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jPDlgq-znrY&amp;list=PL9zmXhEAnxT9hXW_2NJ7ZvdbiMuwSN5Ll&amp;index=6">perpetuate violence and hostility in the third world</a> the West is <a href="http://thegatesnotes.com/Books/Personal/The-Better-Angels-of-Our-Nature">experiencing a period of unprecedented peace and prosperity</a>. In fact, it seems that for most of human history people have been <a href="http://www.utilitarian.net/singer/by/199704--.htm">expanding their circle of empathy</a> from themselves to their families, their churches, their nations and to collections of nations. The future of humanity will be brighter if we can expand this circle to all humans and even other animals and the environment:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('l7AWnfFRc7g');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/l7AWnfFRc7g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('l7AWnfFRc7g-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/l7AWnfFRc7g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7AWnfFRc7g" id="l7AWnfFRc7g" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/l7AWnfFRc7g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7AWnfFRc7g" id="l7AWnfFRc7g-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">RSA Animate - The Empathic Civilisation</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Bestselling author, political adviser and social and ethical prophet Jeremy Rifkin investigates the evolution of empathy and the profound ways that it has shaped our development and our society. Taken from a lecture given by Jeremy Rifkin as part of the RSA&#8217;s free public events programme. 
Watch the full lecture here: http://www.thersa.org/events/video/archive/jeremy-rifkin-the-empathic-civilisation

The RSA is a 258 year-old charity devoted to creating social progress and spreading world-changing ideas. For more information about our research, RSA Animates, free events programme and 27,000 strong fellowship.
Find out more about the RSA at http://www.thersa.org 
Join the RSA on Facebook at http://www.facebook.com/thersaorg
&#8212;&#8212;
Produced and edited by Abi Stephenson, RSA. Animation by Cognitive Media.</div>
</div>


<p>I believe that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tFDJJ1KydgE">promoting human flourishing and the minimisation of suffering rather than any ideology</a> will have the biggest positive impact on humankind. In fact, the pursuit of ideologies can often get in the way of human good. Consider the case of a 22-year-old Salvadoran woman with Lupus having to <a href="http://www.amnesty.org/en/news/el-salvador-must-provide-pregnant-woman-access-life-saving-medical-treatment-2013-04-17">seek approval to abort her brainless foetus from the Salvadoran Supreme Court</a>, after all abortions were banned in 1998. Despite the fact that the foetus will never be conscious, or able to feel pain, Catholic Bishops are campaigning not to let the woman terminate the pregnancy that threatens her life. In my opinion, this is the dangerous product of basing decisions on ideology, not facts.</p>

<p>As a humanist, I believe that the promotion of human welfare should trump ideology, and this is enough to have a worthwhile purpose in life. Robert Green Ingersoll <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Robert_G._Ingersoll">stated it like this</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Reason, observation and experience have taught us that happiness is the only good; that the time to be happy is now, the place to be happy is here and the way to be happy is to make others so. This is enough for us. In this belief we are content to live and die.</p></blockquote>

<p>Already as I write this some people will be asking where they went wrong. Was it that they didn&#8217;t share enough <a href="http://www.ship-of-fools.com/gadgets/food_drink/015.html">testamints</a> or didn&#8217;t buy me the <a href="http://wp.patheos.com/blogs/unreasonablefaith/files/2009/07/armor-of-god-pjs.jpg">Full Armor of God Pyjamas</a> or was it that I acquired critical thinking skills and wrestled with these and other questions? Probably the pyjamas. Of course, Chrsitianity has taught me many <a href="http://christiannymphos.org/2009/07/09/cunnilingus-101/">useful things</a> and I still enjoy reading Song of Songs and Ecclesiastes. I am truly happy that while some sermons have verged on putting me to sleep, no preacher has ever <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xVCQbVcnCwA">punched me in the face</a> or insisted that <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CQSmtNbraGU">I save my kiss until marriage</a>.</p>

<p>Some fundamentalist churches teach to love your neighbor, but hate Hindus, Buddhists, atheists, Muslims, gays, Jews, blacks and anyone suspected of being a feminist. This might make sense in a small street in a leafy suburb, but does it work if you live in an apartment? What happens when your digital neighbours are not just the 10 people you know on your street but the 600 people you know on social media? You&#8217;re going to hear the attitude and opinions of people with differing political, religious and ideological views. And really, when Jesus restated Leviticus 19:34 with the command to love your neighbor as yourself, he did not say love your male neighbor, or love your white neighbor, or love your straight neighbor, or love your beliving neighbor. Don&#8217;t do this:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/unicorn-shun.jpg" alt="Shuun the non-believer!" /></p>

<p>I am happy to publicly state my opinion and I believe that everybody who wants to should be able to question every belief that I hold, attack every doctrine that I maintain and answer every question that I pose. But there&#8217;s a time and a place for this. Until then, why not just be friends?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Damage of the Purity Culture]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/04/02/damage-purity-culture/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-02T11:26:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/04/02/damage-purity-culture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The religious right has been using sex to sell a represive anti-sex agenda, creating the idea of soulgasms, where if Jesus is in the room, couples will have the most amazing orgasms ever, so long as they are married.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;We must fight [lust] with the massive promise of superior happiness. We must swallow up the little flicker of lust’s pleasure in the conflagration of holy satisfaction.” John Piper</p></blockquote>

<p>Many Christians today don&#8217;t present Jesus as a redeemer for all people and all cultures that saves individuals into a community that will have a transformative influence on their life. Instead they present a moralising gospel of American Jesus as the functional saviour that will give someone friends, social status in the Christian subculture, and perfect sex in a perfect marriage so long as they look and sound Christian enough. Rather than empowering countercultural belief in liberation theology of Jesus&#8217;s teachings, it imposes a literalistic rule based adherance to a culture of shame, fear and intimidation of Christendom. It&#8217;s against this context that mission strategies are devised to present Christianity as the solution to singleness, rejection and loneliness.</p>

<p>This has many damaging effects on young people inculcated into the culture. It tells young adults that virginity matters more than chastity, and even if they spend 60 hours a week volunteering for charity, they have no standing in the church if they have ever had sex. It forces young women into the position of having no sexual agency, no ability to consent to sex, but all of the responsibility for &#8220;causing&#8221; lust in men.</p>

<p>Barna has polled the reasons why young adults leave the church (and many leave the faith altogether). Their <a href="http://www.barna.org/teens-next-gen-articles/528-six-reasons-young-christians-leave-church">results show six key categories for why people leave</a>, facts that <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/karl-giberson-phd/creationists-and-young-christians_b_1096839.html">cause consternation for some</a>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Churches seem overprotective.</li>
<li>Teens and 20-somethings&#8217; experience of Christianity is shallow.</li>
<li>Churches come across as antagonistic to science.</li>
<li><strong>Young Christians&#8217; church experiences related to sexuality are often simplistic, judgmental.</strong></li>
<li>They wrestle with the exclusive nature of Christianity.</li>
<li>The church feels unfriendly to those who doubt.</li>
</ol>


<p>Presenting sex inside marriage as always perfect, always effortless and always satisfying as it is in accordance with &#8220;God&#8217;s design&#8221; sets young couples up for a steep learning curve. Those who can&#8217;t wait, like <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1802108/">95% of Americans</a> or <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3156853/">70% of conservative Texan Southern Baptist couples</a> will feel secret shame that they may not even be able to bring before a pastor if they have overstated the significance of sex in relation to other sin. The flipside of this involves pushing abstinence-before-marriage sex education, that misrepresents the risks of unprotected sex in order to suggest that marrital sex is the only &#8220;safe&#8221; form. Studies have found that factual distortions of abstinence-until-marriage campaigns around the benefits of condom use lead teenagers who sign abstinence pledges <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2768056/">to be just as sexual, but less likely to use condoms</a>.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s a stranger niche of homeschooled daughters going to purity balls, to leart to save their first kiss until their wedding day. These girls learn all kinds of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CQSmtNbraGU">creepy ideas about how they need to date their fathers in order to marry the perfect man</a>. Having taken the simplistic black and white answers around sex, they are now pushing out a legalistic agenda to beyond what the bible even remotely supports.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s starting to be pushback.</p>

<h3>DRISCOLL</h3>

<p>On December 21, 1999 George Barna&#8217;s Christian polling firm announced the results of their study on religion and divorce. The uncomfortable reality was that &#8220;born again&#8221; Christians were <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20020616112707/www.barna.org/cgi-bin/PagePressRelease.asp?PressReleaseID=39&amp;Reference=B">significantly more likely to get divorced than atheists and agnostics to get divorced</a> (27% versus 21%). This strongly challenged the naive assumption that &#8220;couples that pray together stay together&#8221; that had been previously unquestioned in White evangelical churches. Significant time and money was spent investing in couples&#8217;s counseling and therapy, and new ranges of &#8220;sexual fulfilment&#8221; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CYVicYHNrAA">seminars, books and courses</a>. Pastors started running &#8220;Bed-in&#8221; competitions, getting married couples to <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/US/sermons-sex-pastors-preach-pro-sex-god-christian/story?id=15433285#.UaD4v0FR8t8">publicly admit that they enjoy having sex</a>. &#8220;Marriage strengthening&#8221; and couple counselling became a focus of many churches, so much so that some pastors started titillating their engaged couples and singles with racy sermons from Song of Songs. Entrepreneurs set up stores with &#8221;<a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18975616">Christian sex toys</a>&#8221; after the market exploded when normal women suddenly found approval for &#8220;marital aids&#8221;.</p>

<p>Mark Driscoll made his career out of packing young people into his churches to hear his sexed up sermons. It&#8217;s a fast way to get <a href="http://nytimes.com/2009/01/11/magazine/11punk-t.html?pagewanted=2">youtube fame after being kicked off God.tv</a> as young people all over the world seek a style of religion that is less suffocating and more understanding of issues being faced by Millenial couples. This started to go off the rails, however, when Driscoll resorted to <a href="https://freedom4captives.wordpress.com/2009/06/21/35-driscoll-your-husbands-appreciate-oral-sex-so-serve-them-well/">proof-texting individual verses of Song of Songs to command women to perform specific sex acts they did not want to</a>. Despite the fact that Proverbs states that the way of a young man with a maid is <a href="http://bibleapps.com/proverbs/30-19.htm">too wonderful to know of</a>, metaphoric portions of a Hebrew love song written more than 2,000 years ago were being forced into a very modern, over-sexed American culture. Demanding a pastor (who&#8217;s not qualified as a sex therapist) to give couples a literal yes and no answer to every sexual question they may have is never a good idea, and often it means imposing the pastor&#8217;s limited, sexist understanding onto other couples.</p>

<p>Driscoll is facing an increasing amount of pushback as people see his personally sexist views pervading his biblical interpretation. Driscoll&#8217;s wife grace interpreted the biblical queen Vashti as being killed for <a href="http://rachelheldevans.com/blog/esther-and-vashti">not being submissive to her husband&#8217;s commands that she prance around naked in front of his drunk guests</a>. More and more people are recognising that Driscoll&#8217;s ideas about marriage are more of a <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2011/12/24/grace-and-mark-driscoll-write-a-how-not-to-book-on-marriage/">how not to guide</a>.</p>

<h3>Damage</h3>

<p>Pushing damage onto women
http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com.au/2012/04/whores-meditation-on-gender-and-bible.html</p>

<p>Ezekiel 23</p>

<p>Ignorance of the size and extent of the purity culture leaves people unable to understand its real effects. Shaming female sexuality can cause <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2011/11/the-purity-culture-and-sexual-dysfunction.html">serious sexual dysfunction well into marriage</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>After a few months, I did start having sexual fantasies. But they were all fantasies of non-consensual sex. Why? Because on some intuitive level that made them safer, less taboo, and less sinful. After all, in these fantasies, I didn’t have a choice. I didn’t have sexual agency. I wasn’t choosing to have sex. I wasn’t active. It wasn’t that I wanted to fantasize about non-consensual sex; rather, as a result of the purity culture and my suppression of my sexuality, this was the only kind of sex I could fantasize about.</p>

<p>When my husband and I began having sex, we found that the only way I could orgasm was to pretend our sex was non-consensual. It was as though imagining and miming being coerced was the only way I could truly let go, detach from myself, and give myself permission to feel sexual pleasure. Being an active sexual agent, even in my thoughts, had been a no-no for so long that this suppression had become hard-wired into my brain. It literally took us years to figure out a way for me to have orgasms without pretending that our sex was non-consensual. I have nothing against people who simply enjoy this sort of sex play or this sort of fantasies, and I’m not saying it’s bad. It’s just that I really wanted to be able to experience orgasm without having to pretend sex was non-consensual.</p>

<p>It’s been some years now, and things have gotten better. I can have orgasms without pretending our sex is non-consensual, and I now have sexual fantasies in which I am an active sexual agent. There are some things I’m still working on, because these sorts of thought patterns don’t go away overnight, but I’m confident that I’m on the right path and have a bright sexual future.</p>

<p>How did this happen to me? It’s simple, really. I spent the first twenty years of my life suppressing every sexual urge, thought, or desire. I literally became essentially asexual. Literally. My sexuality was dead, because I had killed it. I had sacrificed it on the alter of the purity culture in a desire to make myself pure and godly. And yet, I’d always been taught that once I was married I would experience carefree, romping, ecstatic, incredible sex the likes of which I could not imagine. There is a disconnect here. How is one supposed to go from being sexually suppressed and extinguished to being an active and fulfilled sexual being?</p>

<p>I was taught growing up that every sexual thought or desire outside of marriage is sin. Believing this, I spent twenty years working hard to keep from thinking about sex, and I succeeded. I was essentially asexual. And then, with my husband, I was suddenly supposed to think about sex. My mind rebelled. My indoctrination of my own brain had been all too successful. My sexual dysfunction was only natural.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Singleness and loneliness</h3>

<p>http://www.critiquebycreating.com/2011/04/the-most-eligible-christian-bachelor/</p>

<h3>Pushback</h3>

<p>God and boobs Angie Schuller Wyatt</p>

<p>http://www.huffingtonpost.com/angie-schuller-wyatt/how-i-broke-free-from-religion-and-embraced-my-sexuality_b_2839257.html
http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2013/03/11/an-exclusive-excerpt-from-god-and-boobs/
http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2013/03/21/the-author-of-god-and-boobs-responds-to-your-questions
http://www.cnbc.com/id/100522472</p>

<blockquote><p>… Schuller Wyatt was scheduled to appear on the Hour of Power broadcast where her brother Robert “Bobby” Schuller III preaches. But when word got out that Schuller Wyatt had written God and Boobs, she was unceremoniously dumped via email from a church executive who gave no explanation.</p>

<p>“I’m tired of religious bullies dictating to women how we should live our lives. In my work as a pastor, I counseled too many women who felt ashamed of their sexuality and were silenced into submission. I am trying to empower them to feel good about themselves.“</p>

<p>Spiritual leaders have been guilty of teaching women to hide their figures in dumpy clothes, to avoid thinking about sex and to ignore their sexual desires. Whether Protestant or Catholic, most religious rules about sex result in women feeling their sexuality is shameful. Women in my religious circle won’t typically admit to their friends or pastors that they’ve felt this way, but they will tell their counselors. In the privacy of a safe setting, they talk of things like having to endure looks from their pastor that made them feel dirty. Making matters worse is the rampant hypocrisy in religion. The same leaders who set strict boundaries on sexuality are often exposed for exploiting sex in their private lives. When their sins come to light, they’re revealed as consumers of pornography, prostitution and illegal sex-enhancing drugs. Certainly, not all spiritual leaders are guilty of this kind of hypocrisy, but it is prevalent enough to cast a shadow on the world’s prominent religions.
The devout Christian women I know tend to heed their leaders’ advice. Every piece of clothing is viewed through the lens of lust. Will this shirt show too much cleavage? Is my hemline too short? Am I going to cause a man to sin? They end up thinking about their cleavage as much as the men around them do.
I once heard a pastor chide women in his church for wearing tops that were cut too low. If the congregation wasn’t thinking about breasts walking into the building, they were certainly thinking about them as they walked out. I heard nothing else the pastor said that day. I kept thinking to myself: How low it too low? Who is the appointed Cleavage Monitor? Who draws the line between sinner and saint?
Years ago, my brother told me that if a man is going to lust, he’s going to lust. You could put a girl in a potato sack and he’d still become aroused. It’s our own conscience that must resolve the questions of sexual expression and attire.</p>

<p>Enhanced by breasts, hips and figures that curve, a woman’s body is shaped by God. It’s a beautiful piece of art, meant to be alluring and sensual in all the right places. But religious women feel insecure about their curves to the point of layering on their clothes until they’ve covered every inch of their femininity.</p>

<p>This point was driven home by a friend, who told me about a film crew from a local news organization that was reporting on a major Christian women’s conference in her city. She knew about the situation because she worked at the conference behind the scenes. The crew was trying to wrap the shoot, but they couldn’t seem to get the footage they wanted. The hold-up? They needed an interview and couldn’t find a single woman, she was told, who looked like a cute, normal girl and not “a bag lady.”</p>

<p>Are women meant to live this way? Is this what God requires of us? Does God want us to feel shame about our sexuality? Women deserve a shame-free existence. They should explore, adore and adorn their shapes. There’s nothing shameful about a womanly figure that evokes sexual feelings, because women, like men, were designed to have sex. It’s natural. There are ways to embrace our figures, without putting them on display, to celebrate them and keep them sacred.</p></blockquote>

<p>http://wineandmarble.com/purity-guilt/
http://wineandmarble.com/ir-modesty-and-lust/</p>

<p>Still others like Dianne Anderson are speaking out on the damaging nature of denying women sexual agency
http://diannaeanderson.net/?p=1288
When Chrisitans discuss sex,</p>

<blockquote><p>Consent doesn’t enter into the picture, because if enthusiastic, positive consent is discussed, it might end up teaching people that healthy sexual relationships can and do happen outside of a marriage relationship. And then all hell breaks loose!</p></blockquote>

<p>http://rachelheldevans.com/blog/christians-idolize-virginity</p>

<p>http://www.patheos.com/blogs/lovejoyfeminism/2013/02/christian-bloggers-pushing-back-on-virginity.html</p>

<p>Dan Fincke of Cammels with Hammers points out that many <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/camelswithhammers/2011/02/sex-and-apostasy/">parents who themselves lived a life of moderate libertinism are happy to have their children inculcated into a doctrine of asceticism they could never follow</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>When it is actually beneficial in practice for people to reject fundamentalist Christian restrictiveness about sex, they leave the church.  When they are married and raising children, suddenly they endorse a system of values that conveniently allows that only married people can have sex and that their teenage and young adult children cannot.</p>

<p>Religious people of this sort are some of the worst and most blithe and uncondemned species of hypocrites out there.  They condemn the same healthy process of normal sexual development they personally benefited from while considering themselves especially devout and moral people for “repenting” of their ways when all they did was get married and find the church suddenly extremely convenient to their sexual goals of monogamy and their desire that their teenage and young adult children remain chaste.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Condascending and Shaming Gospel Tracts]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/03/31/shaming-tracts/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-31T21:56:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/03/31/shaming-tracts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just came across one of the most condescending, self righteous and judgemental Christian tracts to shame young people about their lives I&#8217;ve ever seen.</p>

<p><img class="center Satisfied, Teen Ager" src="http://nsewell.com//images/teenager1.jpg">
<img class="center Satisfied, Teen Ager" src="http://nsewell.com//images/teenager2.jpg"></p>

<blockquote><p>Within you there is an emptiness - a vacuum. You&#8217;ve tried to find satisfaction. Drinking, smoking, petting, indulging in shameful sex acts has not filled that void. Yet, you seek for greater thrills, you cultivate a deeper love for the pleasures of this world. You&#8217;ve tried to convince yourself that you are happy, but <em>HELL</em> rages within.</p>

<p><em>SOON!</em> you will stand before the almighty God on the judgment day and give an account of every dirty joke, curse word, evil action and neglected opportunity of being saved from all sin.</p>

<p><em>REPENTANCE</em> means confessing all our sins&#8230; <em>REPENTANCE</em> means forsaking all sin, a complete turning away from being a rebel, from ungodly friends, form conformity with the world, from secret sins and habits of the flesh, from filthy books and naked photographs, from dirty stories and unclean jokes, from everything and everybody that would hinder you from being one hundred percent for Jesus Christ&#8230;</p>

<p><em>REPENTANCE</em> means making restitution. In other words, make your back paths straight; make things right with those whom you have wronged. This includes taking back stolen property or paying back stolen money. Restitution involves asking of forgiveness of parents for improper attitudes towards them, disobedience, and disrespect.</p></blockquote>

<p>Of course most tracts aren&#8217;t intended to convert people to Christianity, just to satisfy the &#8216;evangelist&#8217; that they are doing their job by presenting the very worst of Christian judgementalism. Jack Chick&#8217;s <a href="http://www.stufffundieslike.com/2013/02/catholic-bashing/">rabid anti-Catholic sentiment makes this clear</a>:</p>

<p><img class="center JTC Catholic Bashing" src="http://nsewell.com//images/catholic-bash1.gif">
<img class="center JTC Catholic Bashing" src="http://nsewell.com//images/catholic-bash2.jpg">
<img class="center JTC Catholic Bashing" src="http://nsewell.com//images/catholic-bash3.jpg"></p>

<p>Of course, people giving out these tracts don&#8217;t care about how the recipients receive them, they are really only there to give out as many tracts as quickly as possible <a href="http://www.stufffundieslike.com/2012/11/tract-smack-down/">to appease other Christians</a>:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('58pU8WBu0Vc');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/58pU8WBu0Vc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('58pU8WBu0Vc-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/58pU8WBu0Vc/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=58pU8WBu0Vc" id="58pU8WBu0Vc" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/58pU8WBu0Vc/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=58pU8WBu0Vc" id="58pU8WBu0Vc-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Smack Down - tract distribution</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Brother Bernard brings his Marine Corps style to tract distribution. A &#8220;Smack Down&#8221; is a fun way to distribute a lot of tracts in a little time - and get some good exercise as a bonus.

The Bible Baptist Church of DeLand
Pastor James W. Knox

Our web site is http://www.jamesknox.com</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Millenial Marriage Equality Surge]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/03/28/millenial-marriage-eq/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T08:08:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/03/28/millenial-marriage-eq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/hrc-lesbian.jpg" alt="Red bars of the Human Rights Campaign with Lesbian Justice and Liberty" /></p>

<p>This week the US supreme court is assessing the contitutional validity of state laws prohibiting same-sex marriage. There is the potential to overturn California&#8217;s Proposition 8, and possibly the Defence of Marriage Act. A large number of millenials have been following the SCOTUS, with many changing their profile pictures to an equality symbol. Data from Pew Research show that while other demographic groups have relativly unchanged levels of support for same-sex marriage, <a href="http://www.people-press.org/2013/03/20/growing-support-for-gay-marriage-changed-minds-and-changing-demographics/">17% of millenials have changed their minds over the last 3 years</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/pew-gay-marriage.png" alt="Pew Gay Marriage" /></p>

<p>A range of significant Democratic figures have given their support to the campaign, like Hillary Clinton recently joining Barack Obama and Joe Biden. Obama himself stated his views &#8216;evolved&#8217; from discussions with his daughters, subtley refuting the argument that gay marriage is a threat to children. A number of Republican figures like Dick Cheney, Laura Bush, and Colin Powell have already come out in support of gay marriage, and recently another 75 Republicans added their support, including <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/02/republicans-urge-scotus-to-support-gay-marriage.html">former Utah Governor Jon Huntsman and former ebay CEO Meg Whitman</a>. Rob Portman, an original voter for DOMA, also changed his mind after <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2013/03/15/rob-portman-gay-marriage-son/1988375/">his son came out as gay</a>.</p>

<p>Bill O&#8217;Reilly has also <a href="http://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2013/03/27/oreilly_gay_marriage_backers_have_compelling_argument_against_bible_thumpers.html">changed his view, on March 26 of the O&#8217;Reilly Factor</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>MEGYN KELLY, FOX NEWS: I mean, I think the country&#8217;s views on [same-sex marriage] are changing, they&#8217;re changing dramatically.</p>

<p>O&#8217;REILLY: But why are they changing?</p>

<p>KELLY: Well, because I think the same-sex marriage advocates have done a credible job in getting out there and making their case&#8230; I had an interview with Tony Perkins of the Family Research Council. What is it about calling a marriage &#8211; calling a gay union a marriage that offends you. How does it hurt a traditional, or a heterosexual marriage? And I didn&#8217;t hear anything articulated that was particularly persuasive&#8230;</p>

<p>O&#8217;REILLY: …I agree with you 100-percent. <strong>The compelling argument is on the side of homosexuals</strong>. That&#8217;s where the compelling argument is. &#8216;We&#8217;re Americans, we <strong>just want to be treated like everybody else</strong>.&#8217;</p>

<p>That’s a compelling argument. And to deny that, you’ve got to have a very strong argument on the other side. And <strong>the other side hasn’t been able to do anything but thump the Bible</strong>.</p>

<p>KELLY: Their best argument, thus far, has been, &#8216;well, marriage is an institution that for 2,000 has been about a man and a woman creating babies.&#8217;</p>

<p>O&#8217;REILLY: That&#8217;s right.</p>

<p>O&#8217;REILLY: &#8230;I live in New York, New York has [gay marriage], <strong>I&#8217;m fine with it. I want all Americans to be happy</strong>, I do.</p></blockquote>

<p>With opposition to same-sex marriage seemingly in free-fall, extreme Religious Right figures are coming up with explanations for how this has happened. And rather than acknowledge that social media allows millenials to change their minds quickly, and that the demographics of the US are changing, they&#8217;d rather engage in <a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/wnd-our-tiny-tots-are-taught-homosexuality-weve-even-broken-them-thumb-sucking">kooky conspiracy theories about a hidden population control agenda</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>One has to wonder if the bigger motive behind the homosexual agenda isn’t to secretly achieve voluntary population control: Perhaps the ultimate goal is to save the planet from the inevitable destruction of man-made climate change. One could conclude that the sustainability efforts behind Agenda 21 would greatly benefit from same-sex partners who would no longer pollute the planet with the unwanted carbon footprints of tiny feet. Even those diesel-spewing school buses could become a welcomed relic of the past if enough people stopped procreating.</p></blockquote>

<p>The idea that the gay rights movement is a covert conspiracy to destroy capitalism by reducing procreation has been picked up by Matt Hagee:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('Ss5YhmmMLZo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ss5YhmmMLZo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('Ss5YhmmMLZo-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Ss5YhmmMLZo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ss5YhmmMLZo" id="Ss5YhmmMLZo" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Ss5YhmmMLZo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ss5YhmmMLZo" id="Ss5YhmmMLZo-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Matthew Hagee: Gay Marriage &#8220;Is The Death Of Capitalism&#8221;</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/matthew-hagee-gay-marriage-will-be-death-capitalism

Matthew Hagee says gay marriage will result in couples no longer producing future consumers, which will spell the end of capitalism and society.</div>
</div>


<p>Susan Harris continues her theorising, worried about the influence that social media has over millenials:</p>

<blockquote><p>Chances are, if you’ve got a teenager on Facebook, they have been lured by curiosity to at least one of these sites. In addition to social media, well-known gay celebrities in comedy, news and music beat a steady drumbeat of tantalizing homosexual ideology for America’s youth…</p>

<p>Generation Q lives and breathes an intense obsession of their sexuality that is disturbing to outsiders. Insiders include gays, lesbians, bisexuals, transgenders, pansexuals and basically everyone who does not adhere to the archaic idea of a man and woman being attracted to each other, marrying and having children. More importantly, it consists of allies who loudly champion the cause for family and friends already immersed in this destructive culture…</p>

<p>We have reached the point where neither American laws nor accepted cultural norms will protect my rights as a Christian to protect my child from what my faith teaches is sinful and perverse behavior. Americans must not back down in the face of constant intimidation. The first step begins at home: naming the sin and teaching our children to love the sinner but hate the sin. <strong>The LGBT agenda is ensuring that our tiny tots are taught homosexuality before we’ve even broken them of thumb-sucking</strong>. By the time they are teenagers – feeling “different” like millions of teenagers before them – they are being sucked into the LGBTQ lifestyle because their parents and their communities put acceptance of man’s lusts above God’s law.</p>

<p>Our youth are embarking on a lonely, dark path of sexual confusion and its resulting sadness, disease and suicide. There will be no going back. Generation Q may have already slipped through our fingers.</p></blockquote>

<p>Clearly the only sane thing a God-fearing parent can do is to keep their tiny tots holed up in a basement for the first decade of life, away from the corrupting influence of the world.</p>

<p>Behind the claim that gays want to destroy capitalism is the concern that changing social mores and cultural norms, as well as efforts to reduce economic inequality will <a href="http://www.edge.org/3rd_culture/paul07/paul07_index.html">destroy the Religious Right</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[False Prophet Running for Office]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/12/danny-nalliah/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T15:56:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/12/danny-nalliah</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Danny Nalliah, a false prophet running the apostate church &#8220;Catch the Fire Ministries&#8221; has launched his own political party, &#8220;rise up Australia&#8221;. Nalliah&#8217;s church has been <a href="http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/costello-slams-cults-retribution-claims/story-e6frg6of-1111118814587">denounced as a cult by Peter Costello, someone his false prophesy lead him to &#8216;anoint&#8217; as Australia&#8217;s future Prime Minister</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>A FURIOUS Peter Costello has rounded on a Christian cult for suggesting the Victorian bushfires were divine retribution for the state&#8217;s abortion laws, describing it as &#8220;beyond the bounds of decency&#8221;.</p>

<p>Just three weeks ago, the former federal treasurer sent a video message to a special Australia Day prayer meeting organised by Catch the Fire Ministries leader Danny Nalliah.</p>

<p>But he reacted angrily to a statement by Mr Nalliah yesterday recalling a dream concerning the consequences of Victorian abortion legislation that became law last year.</p>

<p>The preacher claimed God&#8217;s &#8220;conditional protection&#8221; had been &#8220;removed from the nation of Australia, particular Victoria, for approving the slaughter of innocent children in the womb&#8221;.</p>

<p>&#8220;To link the death and the suffering of bushfire victims to other political events is appalling, heartless and wrong,&#8221; he said. &#8220;Those who have suffered deserve every support and sympathy. It is beyond the bounds of decency to try to make moral or political points out of such a tragedy.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Nalliah&#8217;s full prophesy <a href="https://signposts02.wordpress.com/2009/02/14/nalliah-prophecy-claims-fall-short/">said this</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“I saw a man firing randomly with a weapon at people on the streets and many were falling dead. I was very disturbed and was crying. Then the scene changed and I saw fire everywhere with flames burning very high and uncontrollably. With this I awoke from my dream with the interpretation as the following words came to me in a flash from the Spirit of God,  ‘My wrath is about to be released upon Australia, in particular Victoria, for approving the slaughter of the innocent children in the womb.  Now, call on My people to repent and pray!’”</p></blockquote>

<p>This is false prophesy; there have been no major mass murders since 1996. If the Victorian bushfires really were God&#8217;s judgement for abortion legislation, then where is the gunman? In reality, <a href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/01/20/rick-perry/">Australian gun control works much better than school prayer</a>.</p>

<p>Nalliah also incorrectly predicted that <a href="http://www.christian-witness.org/blog/2007/11/26/catch-the-fire%E2%80%93sequel/">Howard would win in the 2007 election before stepping aside for Costello to become Prime Minister</a>. He <a href="http://www.crikey.com.au/2007/08/14/costello-gods-own-prime-minister/">likens himself to the prophet Samuel anointing David</a> &#8220;The Lord spoke clearly to me about how Prophet Samuel in the Word of God was sent to anoint David as the future King of Israel&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><p>I thank the Lord that I just had a one to one meeting with Peter Costello [and Howard]&#8230; The Lord had given me a clear prophetic Word for both of them and I thank Him I was able to deliver His Word in addition to praying with both of these Federal Government Leaders&#8230;</p>

<p>I will boldly declare that Prime Minister John Howard will be re-elected in the November election (if the Body of Christ unites in prayer and action) and pass the leadership onto Peter Costello sometime after.</p></blockquote>

<p>Nalliah waters down his prophesy by hedging his bets on whether Christians pray the right way, creating an &#8220;out&#8221; for his faulty prophesy. As Rev Dr Gordon Moyes notes, &#8220;True prophets never give a “conditional” word of prophecy.&#8221; Moyes goes on to note that</p>

<blockquote><p>The majority of patients coming to the psychiatrists I have been responsible for employing in Wesley Mission’s Mental Health Hospitals claim God speaks to them. In other Christian circles and in Christian books, I note some people seek to get their own way by using God speaking to them as almost a way of stopping any questioning of their ideas.</p></blockquote>

<p>The American televangelist Kenneth Copeland confirmed Nalliah’s prophetic anointing of John Howard as Prime Minister, declaring that <a href="http://jmm.aaa.net.au/articles/20588.htm">Howard was “God’s man in Australia”</a>.</p>

<p>The Australian recounts the &#8220;preparation&#8221; (anointing as God&#8217;s elect) that happened with Costello:</p>

<blockquote><p>Mr Nalliah met Mr Costello ahead of the 2007 election to &#8220;prepare&#8221; him for the prime ministership. A church member publicly recounted an episode where &#8220;the spirit of God suddenly moved me to cry out in the loud Aboriginal-like tongue followed by the shouting out several times of &#8216;the honourable Peter Costello, prime minister-elect of Australia&#8217;.&#8221;</p>

<p>And just ahead of an Australia Day prayer meeting, Mr Nalliah announced: &#8220;Our silent prayer is that Peter &#8230; will be here to take the leadership of the party and lead the nation into victory as prime minister.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Nalliah <a href="http://www.christian-witness.org/blog/2007/07/13/pentecostal-disgrace-catch-the-fire-honouring-the-late-frank-houston/">honoured the self-consessed child molester Frank Houston as the greatest influence on his ministry</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The apostle Paul said that when he came to the church at Corinth it wasn’t with wise and persuasive words but it was with a demonstration of the Holy Spirit’s power&#8230; And that’s exactly how I knew Pastor Frank Houston. He was a man who moved in the power of the Holy Ghost. His heart was for real salvations, real healings, and real deliverances. I was fortunate enough to be a guest in his house on numerous occasions.. He was an inspiration not just to me but to many other spiritual sons and daughters throughout this nation.</p>

<p>I love Papa Frank with all my heart. I wish I could give him a big hug.</p></blockquote>

<p>Pastor Bob Cotton goes on to elaborate about his and Nalliah&#8217;s imitation of Houston&#8217;s techniques:</p>

<blockquote><p>I would ring him up sometimes and I’d say, ‘Pastor Frank. This devil - I couldn’t shift it the other day. What do you reckon?’ And he’d start to tell me a few little insights and different things that he’d known in the past, and we’ve seen many people come into freedom&#8230; It’s my honour to stand here today and say Pastor Frank wasn’t just a father in the faith to me, he was one of my closest mates and I love him. I cherish his memory and, like Danny, I wish he were here so I could give him a great big hug tonight because there was nobody quite like [him]</p></blockquote>

<p>Houston was expelled from his denomination for the destructive effect that his sexual abuse had on the church <a href="http://www.christian-witness.org/blog/2007/11/26/cetf-catch-the-fire-a-letter-to-the-editor/">and on victims</a>. By Nalliah&#8217;s own confession, he did not preach with logic and reason, but with signs and wonders. Given Houston&#8217;s history of sexually abusing multiple boys he was clearly not inspired or empowered by the Holy Spirit, and his signs and wonders were faked. Nalliah has learned to perform all of his spurious miracles from his spiritual father, refining the techniques and making even more aggrandised claims of raising three people from the dead.</p>

<p>Now Nalliah is running for office, hoping for a resurgence of Tea Party hysteria to propel an anti-Islamic, climate change denialist agenda into parliament.  Nalliah previously tried to <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/federal-election/gillard-bid-to-win-back-christians-20100805-11krh.html#ixzz2KepvdQfT">smear the Prime Minister for her atheism</a>. This sounds like the hysteria of Tea Party style dominionist rhetoric, claiming that the country was started on Christian values, and the only way to hold up democracy is to have Christian leaders occupying every leadership position.</p>

<blockquote><p>Danny Nalliah&#8230; released a statement giving five reasons not to vote Labor: it would be a vote for the Greens, Prime Minister Julia Gillard is in a de facto relationship, she is childless, she is an atheist, and she refused to take an oath on the Bible.</p></blockquote>

<p>Nalliah&#8217;s politics <a href="http://www.adelaidenow.com.au/news/national/new-political-party-rise-up-australia-wants-muslim-intake-cuts/story-fndo1gb8-1226575716789">have attracted discussion</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Pastor Daniel”, of Catch the Fire Ministries, says a conversation with Jesus that went from 3.40am to 6am one morning prompted his move to Australia.</p>

<p>Since arriving here he has claimed that Victoria’s abortion laws caused the Black Saturday bushfires and that his prayers have brought dead people back to life.</p>

<p>He declared Prime Minister Julia Gillard a heathen “living in sin” and former Greens leader Bob Brown an “openly practising homosexual” and said that he felt sick to the stomach watching them shake hands.</p>

<p>Rise Up Australia will push for cuts to Australia’s “Muslim intake”, for an end to multiculturalism and for protection of Australia’s Judaeo-Christian heritage&#8230;</p>

<p>Climate change skeptic Christopher Monckton spoke at the launch, giving a very graphic description of abortions and leading a round of patriotic cheers.</p></blockquote>

<p>Using abortion as a highly emotional topic as a <a href="http://localhost:4321/blog/2013/01/03/rentier-theology/">smokescreen for an agenda that is factually and morally bankrupt is a common tactic for extreme right wing politics</a>. Nalliah claims to be protecting Australia&#8217;s &#8220;Judeo Christian&#8221; heritage, a classic racist dog whistle. The RUA claim they want &#8220;To promote harmony, freedom and tolerance among Australians; specifically we oppose multiculturalism&#8221;. Great. Nalliah in 2004 called for Christians to <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/content/2004/s1217824.htm">&#8220;pull down Satan&#8217;s strongholds&#8221;, including brothels and gambling places, mosques and temples</a>.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('HjBF4Vt8ccE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HjBF4Vt8ccE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('HjBF4Vt8ccE-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/HjBF4Vt8ccE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HjBF4Vt8ccE" id="HjBF4Vt8ccE" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/HjBF4Vt8ccE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HjBF4Vt8ccE" id="HjBF4Vt8ccE-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Australia&#8217;s newest political party courts controversial speaker</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >The Rise Up Australia Party has launched with the help of Christopher Monckton as it aims to take its head-turning policies to the federal election. See more from 7.30 at http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/</div>
</div>


<p>By claiming Christianity as the inspiration for their extremist politics, Nalliah and Monkton may pick up a small number of votes, but will continue the perception that Chrisitanity is strongly tied to a right wing agenda. If Christians themselves don&#8217;t speak out against this, it will give significant credance to those who want to wipe all religion from public life in Australia.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Should Readers Consider Violence in the Bible?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/10/bible-violence/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-10T16:40:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/10/bible-violence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/bible-gun.jpg" alt="Bible used to justify weapons today" /></p>

<p>Throughout history, the bible has been used as justification for various wars. Dr. Eric Seibert suggests that modern readers <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/peterenns/2013/02/when-the-good-book-is-bad-challenging-the-bibles-violent-portrayals-of-god/">should be mindful of the consequences of</a> a literal interpretation of problematic Old Testament passages:</p>

<blockquote><p>What happens when reading the Bible pushes people away from God rather than leads them closer to God?</p>

<p>If we feel compelled to accept what we read at face value, and are forbidden from asking honest questions about the troublesome texts we encounter, we run the risk of using the Bible in ways that may harm others</p></blockquote>

<p>In many Old Testament passages, Seibert writes, &#8220;lethal violence is condoned and sometimes even celebrated.  Passages like these create significant problems for Christian readers.&#8221; He <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/peterenns/2013/02/when-the-bible-sanctions-violence-must-we/">continues</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>It is extremely dangerous to endorse violent texts like these. Tragically, this kind of approval has often led to future acts of violence against others&#8230;</p>

<p>As Christians, we have a moral obligation to critique the assumption that violence is somehow “virtuous,” in spite of what the Bible suggests on numerous occasions.</p>

<p>Violence is not a virtue. It is not a fruit of the spirit or a mark of discipleship&#8230; There are no moral grounds for slaughtering babies, infants, or toddlers. Yet the Bible justifies their extermination on more than one occasion.</p>

<p>Surely, those of us who follow the prince of Peace, the God of Life, must raise our voices in protest and object. We must say, “This is not right!” Such violence is never justifiable and should never be condoned.</p></blockquote>

<p>Seibert <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/peterenns/2013/02/learning-to-read-the-bible-nonviolently/">suggests that readers engage with violence by trying to empathise with the victims</a>. This would be in line with Jesus&#8217;s teaching on the golden rule.</p>

<p>The question he&#8217;s getting at is whether violence in the Old Testament demonstrates inspiration if it must be resolved with an apparent contradiction with the incarnation of Logos. Working though these issues and understanding the history and interpreting the OT though an NT lens, without interposing modern secular moral standards.</p>

<blockquote><p>Reading this way sensitizes us to the problem of violence in these texts and keeps us from simplistically classifying such moral atrocities as good.</p>

<p>The conquest narrative in Joshua 6-11 reminds us that religious violence is extremely dangerous because it gives divine sanction to behaviors that in any other context would be deemed immoral. Moreover, if one assumes the narrative was intended to bolster the political ambitions of King Josiah, it stands as a sober reminder of the way political leaders sometimes use religion to promote their own agendas.</p></blockquote>

<p>Image by <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/mallard10/4737313420/">Jonathan Mallard</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reinventing History]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/07/reinventing-history/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-07T18:38:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/07/reinventing-history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>There is a funny thing about history. Even though there are countless books waiting to be investigated and read, myriad articles from the times, and an abundance of other evidence, we human beings would <a href="https://mabworld.wordpress.com/2012/02/27/the-fundamentalist-history-they-dont-want-you-to-know/">rather have someone else — one of our contemporaries — tell us what it is</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>As George Orwell opined in <em>Ninteen Eighty Four</em>, &#8220;whoever controls the present controls the past&#8221;.
Even though the US senate in 1797 that &#8221;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Tripoli">the Government of the United States of America is not, in any sense, founded on the Christian religion</a>,&#8221; it&#8217;s become common to hear right wing Christians insist the opposite:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/jesus-constitution.jpg" alt="Jesus giving the US constitution to the founding fathers" /></p>

<p>Demographic changes in the United States mean that white evangelical Christians are a smaller and smaller voting bloc. As the Religious Right attempting to broaden their base to black and latino Christians, they emphasise anti-abortion and anti-gay positions, and try to downplay their history of segregationalist and White Supremacist links. They also try to claim that they have always been against legal access to abortions, despite <a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5502785">evidence to the contrary</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Although various Roman Catholic groups denounced the ruling, and Christianity Today complained that the Roe decision “runs counter to the moral teachings of Christianity through the ages but also to the moral sense of the American people,” the vast majority of evangelical leaders said virtually nothing about it; many of those who did comment actually applauded the decision. W. Barry Garrett of Baptist Press wrote, “Religious liberty, human equality and justice are advanced by the Supreme Court abortion decision.” Indeed, even before the Roe decision, the messengers (delegates) to the 1971 Southern Baptist Convention gathering in St. Louis, Missouri, adopted a resolution that stated, “we call upon Southern Baptists to work for legislation that will allow the possibility of abortion under such conditions as rape, incest, clear evidence of severe fetal deformity, and carefully ascertained evidence of the likelihood of damage to the emotional, mental, and physical health of the mother.” W.A. Criswell, former president of the Southern Baptist Convention and pastor of First Baptist Church in Dallas, Texas, expressed his satisfaction with the Roe v. Wade ruling. “I have always felt that it was only after a child was born and had a life separate from its mother that it became an individual person,” the redoubtable fundamentalist declared, “and it has always, therefore, seemed to me that what is best for the mother and for the future should be allowed.”</p></blockquote>

<p>The Religious Right wants to paint themselves as having always been anti-abortion, and tends to be quiet on their position about racism and civil rights. The Republicans have a history of inviting White Supremicist speakers to the Conservative Political Action Comitee, while at the same time trying to broaden their base to black voters. In fact, one of the biggest issues to galvinise white evangelical voters is opposition to the civil rights movement. Paul Weyrich of the Committee for the Survival of a Free Congress said:</p>

<blockquote><p>“What galvanised the Christian community was not abortion, school prayer, or the ERA. I am living witness to that because I was trying to get those people interested in those issues and I utterly failed. What changed their mind was Jimmy Carter’s intervention against the Christian schools, trying to deny them tax-exempt status on the basis of so-called de-facto segregation.”</p></blockquote>

<p>The religious right is now attempting to get black voters to join an anti-gay campaign, claiming that they were always on the side of civil rights. Matt Barber, the law dean of Liberty University (founded on pro-segregationalist grounds by Jerry Falwell) <a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/matt-barber-whose-idol-backed-segregation-lectures-everyone-else-about-civil-rights-movement">claimed that the gay movement has &#8220;cynically co-opted and hijacked the language of the very, very noble civil rights movement and applied it to their disordered lifestyle.”</a></p>

<p>Next thing they&#8217;ll try and claim that Chrsitians have always been <a href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/lib-edu/education/psd/nation/halifax.htm">against slavery</a>. When the Theistic Evolution crowd convinces more Christians of the scientific truth of evolution (that it is more than &#8220;just a theory&#8221;), they&#8217;ll claim that Christians always thought Genesis was compatible with science. And when the numbers of Americans opposing gay marriage drops they will next claim that they always supported gay rights. <a href="http://www.christianpost.com/news/survey-less-americans-believe-homosexuality-is-a-sin-nations-view-evolving-with-obamas-88141/">44% of Americans believed that homosexuality is a sin in September 2011, dropping to 37% in November 2012</a>, and <a href="http://www.lifeway.com/ArticleView?storeId=10054&amp;article=research-same-sex-marriage-civil-rights-issue-americans-say">64% think same-sex marriage is inevitable</a>. Is it because hollywood is pushing a campaign? Is it because political correctness is popular? Or is it because the media has exposed how, if evangelicals had their way, homosexuality would have the death penalty, like it is now in Uganda?</p>

<p>The more that Christians understand of their own history, the more they&#8217;ll start to realise that many of their key doctrines (like the idea that all of the bible is literally true and without error) are actually <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Baptist_Convention_conservative_resurgence">new inventions</a>.</p>

<p>Image: <a href="http://theamericanjesus.net/?p=3881">Jesus giving the US constitution by Jon McNaughton</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Loony Right's Censorship of Kids' Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/02/kids-book-censorship/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-02T18:40:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/02/kids-book-censorship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Remember when the Chaser took the piss out of the guy who said he &#8216;cured&#8217; his homosexuality by cuddling other men and smacking pillows?</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('9z0_Jzjyi5Y');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9z0_Jzjyi5Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('9z0_Jzjyi5Y-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/9z0_Jzjyi5Y/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9z0_Jzjyi5Y" id="9z0_Jzjyi5Y" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/9z0_Jzjyi5Y/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9z0_Jzjyi5Y" id="9z0_Jzjyi5Y-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Chaser&#8217;s War on everything - Homosexual Cure</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Copyright to Chaser War on Everything, ABC, I didn&#8217;t found this video anymore in the web so I uploaded. Sorry by the low quality.</div>
</div>


<p>This dickhead is now <a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/will-supreme-court-read-most-horrific-children-s-book-all-time">giving testimony to the US supreme court against marriage equality</a>, arguing homosexuality “is not an immutable characteristic&#8221;. His evidence mentions that he has authored a kid&#8217;s book on so-called gay &#8220;reparative therapy&#8221;, called Alfie&#8217;s Home. Here&#8217;s how he presents it:</p>

<blockquote><p>Alfie&#8217;s Home is the story of a boy who struggles with homosexuality well into his teenage years, then transitions naturally into heterosexuality after finding help and experiencing love in his family. This is the first resource of its kind for parents, teachers, students, counselors, clergy and anyone interested in helping children and adults heal their sexual identity.</p></blockquote>

<p>People for the American Way, a liberal advocacy group, call the book &#8221;<a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/will-supreme-court-read-most-horrific-children-s-book-all-time">the most horrifically disturbing children’s book we have ever seen</a>&#8221;. They describe the book:</p>

<blockquote><p> Alfie’s Home was published in 1993 by Cohen’s International Healing Foundation. It starts out with a picture of the protagonist on a boat with his dad.<br/>
 <img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Alfie-cover.jpg" alt="Alfie's Home Cover" />
 But it goes bad fast, going right for the right-wing myth that homosexuality is caused by childhood sexual abuse…<br/>
 <img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Alfie-6-7.jpg" alt="Alfie's Home p6-7" />
 …and by insufficiently attentive parents:<br/>
 <img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Alfie-8-9.jpg" alt="Alfie's Home p8-9" />
 Eventually, Alfie seeks help and takes part in the “touch therapy” advocated by Cohen…<br/>
 <img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Alfie-18-19.jpg" alt="Alfie's Home p18-19" />
 …which leads him to “realize that I’m not gay” and start dating a woman:<br/>
 <img src="http://nsewell.com//images/Alfie-24-25.jpg" alt="Alfie's Home p24-25" /></p></blockquote>

<p>I find it disturbing that they&#8217;re allowed to publish this book. Especially when you consider the list of most commonly challenged books is one where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/And_Tango_Makes_Three">a penguin has two dads</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/tango.jpg" alt="And Tango Makes Three Cover" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/tango2.jpg" alt="And Tango Makes Three page" />
<img src="http://nsewell.com//images/tango3.png" alt="And Tango Makes Three page" /></p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quotes from The Mad Monk to Remind You Why He Shouldn't be PM]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/01/mad-monk-quotes/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T07:02:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2013/02/01/mad-monk-quotes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/abbott.jpg" title="&#34;Tony Abbott&#34;" alt="&#34;Tony Abbott&#34;"></p>

<p>On assylum seekers:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;These people aren’t so much seeking asylum, they’re seeking permanent residency. If they were happy with temporary protection visas, then they might be able to argue better that they were asylum seekers&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-08-22/tony-abbott-blames-carbon-tax-for-uncertainty/4216308">Interview with Leigh Sales, 22nd August 2012</a></p>

<blockquote><p> TONY ABBOTT: Yeah. Don’t forget Jesus drove the traders from the temple as well. Now, I mean, you know&#8230;<br/>
 TONY JONES: What’s the analogy?<br/>
 TONY ABBOTT: &#8230;Jesus didn’t say yes to everyone. I mean Jesus knew that there was a place for everything and it is not necessarily everyone’s place to come to Australia&#8230; Jesus was the best man who ever lived but that doesn’t mean that he said yes to everyone, that he was permissive to everything, and this idea that Jesus would say to every person who wanted to come to Australia, “Fine”, the door is open, I just don’t think is necessarily right</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2859473.htm">From Q&amp;A 5 April 2010</a>. The statement was in response to a question &#8220;what would Jesus do&#8221; on assylum seekers, which unfortunately goaded Abbott into likening himself to Jesus. One bible&#8217;s footnote suggests Jesus drove out the temple traders because &#8220;Not only were the religious leaders robbing the people financially, but because of this they had also robbed them spiritually by stealing from them the opportunity to come to know God genuinely.&#8221; In many ways it&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.unchristian.com/pdfs/Too_Political.pdf">right wing co-opting religion that is a major factor in young generations ditching Christianity</a>.</p>

<p>On rights at work:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;If we’re honest, most of us would accept that a bad boss is a little bit like a bad father or a bad husband … you find that he tends to do more good than harm. He might be a bad boss but at least he’s employing someone while he is in fact a boss.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/am/stories/s596135.htm">From a July 2002 Industrial Relations Conference</a></p>

<p>On abortion:</p>

<blockquote><p> ‘The problem with the Australian practice of abortion is that an objectively grave matter has been reduced to a question of the mother’s convenience.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.tonyabbott.com.au/LatestNews/ArticleswrittenbyTony/tabid/87/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/3653/RATE-OF-ABORTION-HIGHLIGHTS-OUR-MORAL-FAILINGS.aspx">From a 2004 press release</a></p>

<blockquote><p> I believe that there is a vast moral gulf which separates modern Australia from Nazi Germany. But can we be so sure that, under pressure over time, we will not slide down the same slippery slope. We only have to look at the abortion situation in this country. When abortion was in effect made legal, it was supposed to happen only when the physical or mental health of the mother was threatened; yet we all know—let us not fool ourselves—that there is now abortion on demand in this country. Something that was supposed to happen only in rare circumstances is now happening to the extent of 80,000 abortions a year in Australia.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://parlinfo.aph.gov.au/parlInfo/search/display/display.w3p;adv=yes;orderBy=_fragment_number,doc_date-rev;page=0;query=abortion%20Dataset%3Ahansardr,hansardr80%20Decade%3A%221990s%22%20Year%3A%221995%22%20Month%3A%2210%22%20Day%3A%2216%22;rec=0;resCount=Default">From House Hansard, 16th October 1995</a></p>

<blockquote><p> “If half the effort were put into discouraging teenage promiscuity as goes into preventing teenage speeding, there might be fewer abortions, fewer traumatised young women and fewer dysfunctional families.”</p>

<p> “Why isn’t the fact that 100,000 women choose to end their pregnancies regarded as a national tragedy approaching the scale, say, of Aboriginal life expectancy being 20 years less than that of the general community?”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.tonyabbott.com.au/LatestNews/ArticleswrittenbyTony/tabid/87/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/3653/RATE-OF-ABORTION-HIGHLIGHTS-OUR-MORAL-FAILINGS.aspx">From an address to the Adelaide University Democratic Club in 2004</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;In Australia, as elsewhere, one of the great totems of liberation from authority has been abortion on demand. Spurred by pictures of 12-week-old unborn babies being dismembered, some women’s activists have started to question the abortion culture. Abortion may not be the precise moral equivalent of infanticide but it’s not just removing an inconvenient wart or cyst either.<br/>
Since 1996, contrary to poltical correctness, the Australian parliament has overturned right-to-kill laws and (almost) banned gay marriage. Perhaps a political constituency may even be starting to emerge to ban abortions after 20 weeks. Thoughtful feminists are starting to grieve over the downstream consequences of sexual freedom.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>From a <a href="http://www.tonyabbott.com.au/LatestNews/ArticleswrittenbyTony/tabid/87/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/3655/categoryId/4/TRADITIONAL-MORAL-VALUES-A-REVELATION.aspx">speech delivered at the CIS Consilium in Queensland, July 31 2004</a>.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p> &#8220;The problem is backyard miscarriages if unscrupulous doctors prescribe these drugs for desperate women. “</p>

<p> &#8220;If an application did come to me, I would have to satisfy myself that compelent doctors would administer the drug in safe circumstances to women who had fully considered the alternatives and understood the risks”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.tonyabbott.com.au/LatestNews/ArticleswrittenbyTony/tabid/87/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/3607/categoryId/4/PARLIAMENT-BEST-FORUM-FOR-RU486-DECISION.aspx"> On RU486 6 February 2006.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;You don’t have to be a Catholic to be troubled by the current abortion culture”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/sundayprofile/stories/s1389511.htm"> From Sunday Profile 12 June 2005.</a></p>

<p>On aid to the ‘third world’ funding abortions:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;I just think that surely there are higher priorities for Australia than funding things like that.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2514401.htm"> From Q&amp;A 19 March 2009.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Mr Speaker, we have a bizarre double standard; a bizarre double standard in this country where some-one who kills a pregnant woman’s baby is guilty of murder, but a woman who aborts an unborn baby is simply exercising choice.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.aph.gov.au/hansard/reps/dailys/dr150206.pdf">In Parliament (pdf), 15 Feb 2006.</a></p>

<p>On Bernie Banton:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;I know Bernie is very sick, but just because a person is sick doesn’t mean that he is necessarily pure of heart in all things.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.smh.com.au/news/federalelection2007news/abbott-accuses-asbestos-fighter-of-political-stunt/2007/10/30/1193618883990.html"> Said to Channel 9 reporter about asbestos sufferer and social justice campaigner Bernie Banton October 2007.</a></p>

<p>On women:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;I think it would be folly to expect that women will ever dominate or even approach equal representation in a large number of areas simply because their aptitudes, abilities and interests are different for physiological reasons”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/4corners/content/2010/s2846485.htm"> From Four Corners 15 March 2010</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;What the housewives of Australia need to understand as they do the ironing is that if they get it done commercially it’s going to go up in price and their own power bills when they switch the iron on are going to go up, every year….&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.smh.com.au/national/abbott-accused-of-being-incredibly-oldfashioned-as-he-lets-off-steam-20100209-nnqr.html"> Comments on the carbon tax in February 2010.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;[virginity] is the greatest gift that you can give someone, the ultimate gift of giving, and don&#8217;t give it to someone lightly&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2010-01-27/abbott-defends-virginity-comments/310704">Comments in Australian Women&#8217;s Weekly on what advice he would give his daughters on sex before marriage</a>. Many Christian commentators have noted that <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/frankschaeffer/2012/10/evangelical-sexy-virginity-panties-for-jesus-and-romney/">promoting virginity over chastity is counter-productive</a>.</p>

<p>On families:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;I think there does need to be give and take on both sides, and this idea that sex is kind of a woman’s right to absolutely withhold, just as the idea that sex is a man’s right to demand I think they are both they both need to be moderated, so to speak&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2514401.htm"> From Q&amp;A 19 March 2009.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;The point I make in the book is that a society… is surely capable of providing additional recognition to what might be thought of as traditional marriage…. Something akin to a Matrimonial Causes Act marriage ought to be an option for people who would like it.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2009/07/14/2625441.htm"> On the reintroduction of at fault-divorce July 2009.</a></p>

<p>On teenagers:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;The Government accepts that some 14 and 15-year-olds might prefer that their parents not know about the medical procedures they have had or the prescription drugs they are on. But children should not be presumed to be the best judges of their own long-term interests and should not have the right to go behind their parents’ backs… The real issue here is whether 14 and 15-year-olds can make informed decisions about what is right and wrong for them. And if they don’t have that capacity, should they be allowed to operate in a moral and ethical vacuum?”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.theage.com.au/news/general/mind-your-own-medicine/2004/06/12/1086749940114.html"> On Howard legislation giving parents access data about government benefits provided to their teenagers (for example, young women’s Medicare claims related to contraceptive advice), June 2004.</a></p>

<p> On whether a national celibacy campaign would be helpful to counter the rise in teen sexual activity, sexual infections and pregnancies:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;I think that it’s very important that we empower people to reject this kind of rampant sensuality.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2514401.htm"> From Q&amp;A 19 March 2009.</a></p>

<p>On Julia Gillard:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Gillard won’t lie down and die&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>On climate change:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Climate change is absolute crap&#8221;</p>

<p> &#8220;If you want to put a price on carbon why not just do it with a simple tax.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>On homosexuality:</p>

<blockquote><p> LIZ HAYES: Homosexuality? How do you feel about that?
 TONY ABBOTT: I’d probably I feel a bit threatened…</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://sixtyminutes.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=1020354"> From an interview on 60 minutes March 2010</a></p>

<blockquote><p> LEIGH SALES: What was “threatened” referring to?<br/>
 TONY ABBOTT: Well, there is no doubt that it challenges, if you like, orthodox notions of the right order of things…</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/content/2010/s2840098.htm"> From an interview on Lateline March 2010</a></p>

<p>On gay people being members of a Catholic congregation:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;If you’d asked me for advice I would have said to have – adopt a sort of “don’t ask, don’t tell” policy about all of these things…&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2514401.htm"> From Q&amp;A 19 March 2009.</a></p>

<p>On Indigenous Australia:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Now, I know that there are some Aboriginal people who aren’t happy with Australia Day. For them it remains Invasion Day. I think a better view is the view of Noel Pearson, who has said that Aboriginal people have much to celebrate in this country’s British Heritage&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2859473.htm"> From Q&amp;A 5 April 2010.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Even if dispossession is taken to mean that government has a higher responsibility to Aborigines than to other Australians, the production of beautiful art and connectedness to the land does not warrant the maintenance of a way of life also characterised by unemployment, substance abuse and domestic violence. If people choose to live in difficult to service places, that’s their business.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.tonyabbott.com.au/LatestNews/ArticleswrittenbyTony/tabid/87/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/6944/NEW-MISSION-TO-ASSIST.aspx"> From an article published in The Australian 27 June 2008.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Western civilisation came to this country in 1788 and I’m proud of that…”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/4corners/content/2010/s2846485.htm"> From Four Corners 15 March 2010</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;There may not be a great job for them but whatever there is, they just have to do it, and if it’s picking up rubbish around the community, it just has to be done&#8221;</p>

<p> TONY JONES: So are you making a case against teaching in indigenous languages? Is that what – I’m trying to get on top of the point you’re making.<br/>
 TONY ABBOTT: Well, I am making that case.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/tv/qanda/txt/s2662208.htm?show=transcript"> From Q&amp;A 27 August 2009.  </a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;Racism used to be offered as the complete explanation for Aboriginal poverty, alienation and early death. Racism hasn’t disappeared. Still, if racism caused poverty, why hasn’t poverty declined as racism diminished.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;q=cache:hinB3OrHq3cJ:parlinfo.aph.gov.au/parlInfo/download/media/pressrel/VXVE6/upload_binary/vxve66.pdf%3BfileType%3Dapplication/pdf+Racism+used+to+be+offered+as+the+complete+explanation+for+Aboriginal+poverty,+alienation+and+early+death.+Racism+hasn%E2%80%99t+disappeared.+Still,+if+racism+caused+poverty,+why+hasn%E2%80%99t+poverty+declined+as+racism+diminished.&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=au&amp;amp;pid=bl&amp;amp;srcid=ADGEESgqNBMVUJemOsBVODTFxa0wZOqz-g4I3sc_Thh7S1nkdEcSDy028GUv8lYEOCT7DRqTyZ3gfpDU3hur12CMfCcIpD0Qy5nrkcfuTBT1udBZb8Bbuy6rhVLR8Qgvn_AE51_iHz5x&amp;amp;sig=AHIEtbTSaJmxOyYRt-0xAuieaxgsXMEPjA"> From a paper presented to The Bennelong Society (pdf), September 2004.</a></p>

<p>On Nicola Roxon:</p>

<blockquote><p> Ms Roxon: &#8220;You can&#8217;t even get here on time&#8230; I&#8217;m sure had you wanted to you could.&#8221;<br/>
 Mr Abbott: &#8220;That&#8217;s bullshit. You&#8217;re being deliberately unpleasant. I suppose you can&#8217;t help yourself, can you?&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>On homelessness and poverty:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;…we just can’t stop people from being homeless if that’s their choice…”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.smh.com.au/national/abbotts-tough-love-not-their-cup-of-tea-20100215-o2vx.html"> Said to a Catholic social services conference February 2010.</a></p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;It’s the responsibility of government to try to put policies in place which over time will allow people to improve their situation. But we can’t abolish poverty because poverty in part is a function of individual behaviour.
 We can’t stop people drinking; we can’t stop people gambling; we can’t stop people having substance problems; we can’t stop people from making mistakes that cause them to be less well-off than they might otherwise be. “</p></blockquote>

<p>On the death penalty:</p>

<blockquote><p> &#8220;I’d always been against the death penalty but that contemplating the enormity of certain sort of crimes I sometimes thought that some crimes were so hideous that if the punishment were to fit maybe we were left with no alternative but the death penalty.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://sixtyminutes.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=1020354"> From an interview on 60 minutes March 2010</a></p>

<p>Paul Keating&#8217;s take, &#8220;If Abbott becomes Prime Minister, god help us&#8221;:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('4WQvtq6Hn6g');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/4WQvtq6Hn6g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('4WQvtq6Hn6g-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/4WQvtq6Hn6g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4WQvtq6Hn6g" id="4WQvtq6Hn6g" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/4WQvtq6Hn6g/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4WQvtq6Hn6g" id="4WQvtq6Hn6g-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Paul Keating &#8220;If Tony Abbott becomes PM, God help us!&#8221; - March 2010</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Paul Keating comments on Tony Abbott as a leader &#8230;.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
