<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></title>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nsewell.com//"/>
  <updated>2014-07-31T23:43:27+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://nsewell.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Sewell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coverups and Lies Over Asylum Seekers]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/07/31/asylum-lies/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T23:34:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/07/31/asylum-lies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Richard Cooke writes in The Monthly that asylum seekers are unpopular because of blue class job fears resulting from globalisation:</p>

<blockquote><p>Did Australians accept relatively high levels of immigration for so long because they’re tolerant? Australians themselves don’t think so – half think we’re a racist country. Instead, Paul Keating invented a strategy that was then expanded and perfected by John Howard: placate the business community with high levels of immigration, and crack down on asylum seekers to create the appearance of control. Kevin Rudd’s alteration of this gambit caused extreme anxiety among his colleagues.</p>

<p>“To state the obvious,” Julia Gillard wrote to him in a private email immediately before her leadership challenge in 2010, “our primary is in the mid-30s; we can’t win an election with a primary like that and the issue of asylum-seekers is an enormous reason why our primary is at that low level. It is an issue working on every level – loss of control of the borders feeding into a narrative of a government that is incompetent and out of control.”</p>

<p>The public has long been opposed to asylum seekers arriving by boat. Malcolm Fraser’s decision in the mid 1970s to take in Vietnamese boat people might be one of the most politically unpopular ever undertaken in Australia – it had less than 10% support when enacted. Even Fraser started talking about deportation once significant numbers of onshore arrivals started. The golden age of asylum policy in Australia wasn’t golden, and it was never popular.</p>

<p>But despite the heat on talkback radio, there’s some doubt about whether or not the issue of boat people is as decisive as Gillard thought it was. Around a third of people rate it as one of the most important issues, but it seems to have little effect on voter intention.</p>

<p>There’s another reason governments take to refugees with such relish: this is one of the few areas where they can demonstrate resistance to globalisation without confronting vested interests or the economically powerful.</p></blockquote>

<p>Blue collar workers who voted for the LNP, wanting asylum seeker boats &#8220;stopped&#8221; must be thrilled that unemployment benefits are being cut and apprentice tradesmen are losing government assistance to buy their first tools.</p>

<p>The fact that Julia Gillard&#8217;s &#8220;no carbon tax&#8221; statement was heavily used by her opponents is a testament to the fact that honesty is a concern for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moral_Foundations_Theory">larger sectors of the Australian community than compassion</a>.</p>

<p>Scott Morrison has routinely misdirected the media, most recently over <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-07-31/human-rights-commission-asylum-seeker-inquiry-evidence/5639440">reports of children self-harming in offshore immigration detention</a>. Sarah Ferguson <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/content/2014/s4057541.htm">put to Morrison on 7.30</a> &#8220;The Human Rights Commissioner Gillian Triggs says that virtually all of the 174 children on Christmas Island are sick. Children are self-harming, biting themselves, banging into furniture, swallowing poisons. How can this possibly be justified?&#8221;</p>

<blockquote><p>SCOTT MORRISON: Well I don&#8217;t believe that&#8217;s true, for a start&#8230;</p>

<p>SARAH FERGUSON: &#8230;You&#8217;re saying that Gillian Triggs is making up the evidence about the sickness of children?</p>

<p>SCOTT MORRISON: I don&#8217;t think there is evidence of the claim that the high - the Human Rights Commissioner has made in the way that she has made it. These are difficult environments and appropriate care is provided by our people. I think they&#8217;re quite sensational claims that have been made. <strong>She herself is not a doctor</strong> and we have medical people who are there who provide that care on a daily basis.</p></blockquote>

<p>Where have I heard that before?</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('RluGiLWkmy8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/RluGiLWkmy8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('RluGiLWkmy8-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/RluGiLWkmy8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RluGiLWkmy8" id="RluGiLWkmy8" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/RluGiLWkmy8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RluGiLWkmy8" id="RluGiLWkmy8-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Thank You for Smoking</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Thank You for Smoking</div>
</div>


<p>Crudely, the left-wing argument for same-sex marriage is that we need to be compassionate to gays, but the effective argument is we need to tolerate all people we don&#8217;t necessarily approve of, if there&#8217;s no substantiated evidence of harm.</p>

<p>Many LNP voters did vote to want the boats stopped, but they didn&#8217;t understand exactly what this would entail, both in the treatment of asylum seekers, as well as the coverups and lies to the Australian public.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Polarisation getting worse]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/07/07/polarisation/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-07T21:36:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/07/07/polarisation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Pew Forum finds that the American voting elite are becoming more polarised on the political wings, with the parties appealing more strongly to consistently progressive/conservative voters <a href="http://www.people-press.org/2014/06/12/political-polarization-in-the-american-public/">cloistered into their own media niche</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/PP-2014-06-12-polarization-0-01.png"></p>

<p>Claire Lehmann argues that opinionated political bloggers are <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-07-07/lehmann-blogged-down-in-polarities/5576412">driving a partisan divide in Australia</a></p>

<blockquote><p>The sensible middle-ground of politics is being lost in a sea of reactive, frothing debate. And what is to blame? Claire Lehmann says it is page-view journalism.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nikki Durkin opens up on startup failure]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/06/25/durkin/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T10:49:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/06/25/durkin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>90% of tech startups fail, but entrepreneurs don&#8217;t like to dwell on it.</p>

<p>Nikki Durkin was a young age, selling t-shirts on ebay in school, and pitching a fashion marketplace to her business studies class. She found girls like her had a wardrobe full of clothes but nothing to wear, so created &#8220;crack for women&#8221; by setting up a greymarket for fast fashion which quickly gained traction with a passionate user base who loved being able to trade the latest outfits. Nikki launched her business in a red ocean space where she might have beaten competitors if not for a series of setbacks from co-founder health issues, being treated as a terrorist by the US consulate and having two co-founders pull out just before closing a funding round.</p>

<p>Nikki has a long post that&#8217;s probably the most <a href="https://medium.com/@nikkidurkin99/my-startup-failed-and-this-is-what-it-feels-like-c5d64b3ae96b">honest and heartfelt</a> accounts from a founder I&#8217;ve read.</p>

<blockquote><p>I didn’t fail then. I couldn’t fail. This was my baby, and if it was going to fail it would be over my dead body&#8230; I told my mum I didn’t trust my gut when it came to this. My gut was telling me to quit. Problem was, my gut had told me that before in my darkest hours and I still pulled through. If I had trusted my gut then I would have quit years ago.</p>

<p>I knew the only way this was going to die was if we were killed. I am not a quitter. I owed it to myself, my team, my investors and the 99dresses community to see this through&#8230;</p>

<p>Once or twice I’d have an investor asking if I knew what an angel was, or if I also modelled because of my height, or some other unintentionally patronizing comment that I doubt any guy would be subjected to. I learned to take it all in my high-heeled stride.</p></blockquote>

<p>I can&#8217;t do justice to the post and the incredible frustration of dealing with angels and VCs that don&#8217;t close in time to save the business.</p>

<p>Nikki&#8217;s gone home from NYC to Callala Bay, with a population of 2,000. Everyone in the tech sector should want to back our entrepreneurs who want to make Australia more than just sells pepole rocks we dig out of the Pilbara, but we have to be honest about what the startup meat grinder can actually be like.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Moralising Effect of the Disgust Reflex]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/24/ick-factor/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T00:09:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/24/ick-factor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve written before about how [eye tracking can predict political preferences[(/blog/2014/04/05/eye-tracking). People who put more effort into actively avoiding disgusting images are more likely to be politically conservative:</p>

<div class="figure"><a href="http://m.motherjones.com/politics/2014/04/inquiring-minds-john-hibbing-physiology-ideology"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/mj-collage-pol.png" link="http://m.motherjones.com/politics/2014/04/inquiring-minds-john-hibbing-physiology-ideology" title="Tracking which images you look at can predict your disgust response, and your political preference" ><p>Tracking which images you look at can predict your disgust response, and your political preference</span></a></div>


<p>I absolutely loved reading Jonathan Haidt&#8217;s <em><a href="http://righteousmind.com/">The Righteous Mind - why good pepole are divided by religion and politics</a></em>, which makes a strong argument that our genetics influence our political leanings. David Pizarro and Jonathan Haidt have built upon earlier work on the disgust reflex to explore how the reflex to spit out impure food is triggered when we think of disgusting sex practices, or &#8220;unclean&#8221; people. Haidt ran a study where he asked Americans how they would feel if an old woman needed a rag to clean a toilet, and she <a href="http://www.commonsenseatheism.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/Haidt-Moral-Dumfounding-When-Intuition-Finds-No-Reason.pdf">ripped up an old American flag she didn&#8217;t want</a>. Conservatives were furious at the sacrilige of tearing up a flag in the privacy of her own house, while liberals argued that the community should tolerate a woman choosing how to use her own flag inside her own house. Another study asked how people would feel about a <a href="http://faculty.virginia.edu/haidtlab/articles/haidt.hersh.2001.sexual-morality.pub021.pdf">34 year old woman masturbating while cuddling her favourite teddy bear</a>. People who felt disgusted often put forward religious arguments about the design of the body. Pizarro, in a follow up, found that people were more likely to be judgemental of the unusual sex practice when standing next to a reminder to wash their hands:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('5YL3LT1ZvOM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5YL3LT1ZvOM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('5YL3LT1ZvOM-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/5YL3LT1ZvOM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YL3LT1ZvOM" id="5YL3LT1ZvOM" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/5YL3LT1ZvOM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YL3LT1ZvOM" id="5YL3LT1ZvOM-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">David Pizarro: The strange politics of disgust</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >What does a disgusting image have to do with how you vote? Equipped with surveys and experiments, psychologist David Pizarro demonstrates a correlation between sensitivity to disgusting cues &#8211; a photo of feces, an unpleasant odor &#8211; and moral and political conservatism.

TEDTalks is a daily video podcast of the best talks and performances from the TED Conference, where the world&#8217;s leading thinkers and doers give the talk of their lives in 18 minutes (or less). Look for talks on Technology, Entertainment and Design &#8211; plus science, business, global issues, the arts and much more.
Find closed captions and translated subtitles in many languages at http://www.ted.com/translate

Follow TED news on Twitter: http://www.twitter.com/tednews
Like TED on Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/TED

Subscribe to our channel: http://www.youtube.com/user/TEDtalksDirector</div>
</div>


<p>Critically, Pizarro explains how Nazi propaganda taught German children to hate Jews because they were <a href="http://www.calvin.edu/academic/cas/gpa/thumb.htm">reviled as filthy people</a>, with books teaching &#8220;Just look at these guys! The louse-infested beards! The filthy, protruding ears, those stained, fatty clothes&#8230; Jews often have an unpleasent sweetish odor. If you have a good nose, you can smell the Jews.&#8221; Disgust continues to be one of a <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/science/2012/08/anti_gay_bigotry_online_analyzing_homophobic_comments_can_disarm_the_hate_.html">range of tactics</a> put forward by those willing to limit the rights of a social group, or <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/north-carolina-pastor-calls-death-gays-lesbians-trapping-electric-fence-article-1.1082160">ostracise them completely</a>.</p>

<p>One of the clearest indicators that the Christian notion of the <em>Witness of the Holy Spirit</em> doesn&#8217;t exist is that it gets confused with personal bigotry. One Chrisitan minister in Sydney has married a former sex worker, but many Chrisitans, while they praise this action as emblematic of forgiveness and grace central to the religion, admit that the would never be able to accept a woman with an extensive past sexual history.</p>

<p>Recently Michael Sam was the first openly gay player drafted to the United States National Football League. Recently a Dallas TV panellist walked off the set when the show broadcast a kiss between Sam and his boyfriend in celebration of the draft, despite earlier showcasing <a href="http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2014/05/16/anti-gay-texas-talk-show-host-gets-her-heart-pounded-by-half-naked-male-strippers/">topless male strippers in the program</a>. Now the editor of <em>Wing Nut Daily</em> has said that pepole who feel a disgust reaction at seeing a homosexual kiss are experiencing &#8221;<a href="http://www.rightwingwatch.org/content/david-kupelian-says-revulsion-yucky-michael-sam-kiss-something-god">something from God</a>.&#8221;</p>

<p>Richard Beck has been <a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com.au/2013/02/the-psychology-of-christian-purity.html">writing on this for years</a>, and the No Shame Movement has started to <a href="http://www.relevantmagazine.com/god/church/how-not-talk-about-purity">pick up traction within mainstream evangelicalism</a>. With ongoing <a href="http://prospect.org/article/next-christian-sex-abuse-scandal">sex abuse scandals</a> all over the evangelical world, evangelical leaders can no longer drag their heels on changes that everyone knows need to happen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Our Politics Dumbing Down?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/19/dumbing-down/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T10:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/19/dumbing-down</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Macleans has great articles. American politics, like in many other OECD countries, as politicians <a href="http://www.macleans.ca/politics/america-dumbs-down/">communicate in simple soundbites while giving campaign funders and corporate lobbyists most of the power</a></p>

<blockquote><p>The trends are not encouraging. In 1978, 42 per cent of Americans reported that they had read 11 or more books in the past year. In 2014, just 28 per cent can say the same, while 23 per cent proudly admit to not having read even one, up from eight per cent in 1978. Newspaper and magazine circulation continues to decline sharply, as does viewership for cable news. The three big network supper-hour shows drew a combined average audience of 22.6 million in 2013, down from 52 million in 1980. While 82 per cent of Americans now say they seek out news digitally, the quality of the information they’re getting is suspect. Among current affairs websites, Buzzfeed logs almost as many monthly hits as the Washington Post&#8230;</p>

<p>By 2008, journalist Susan Jacoby was warning that the denseness—“a virulent mixture of anti-rationalism and low expectations”—was more of a permanent state. In her book, The Age of American Unreason, she posited that it trickled down from the top, fuelled by faux-populist politicians striving to make themselves sound approachable rather than smart. Their creeping tendency to refer to everyone—voters, experts, government officials—as “folks” is “symptomatic of a debasement of public speech inseparable from a more general erosion of American cultural standards,” she wrote</p>

<p>An aversion to complexity—at least when communicating with the public—can also be seen in the types of answers politicians now provide the media. The average length of a sound bite by a presidential candidate in 1968 was 42.3 seconds. Two decades later, it was 9.8 seconds. Today, it’s just a touch over seven seconds and well on its way to being supplanted by 140-character Twitter bursts.</p>

<p>Little wonder then that distrust—of leaders, institutions, experts, and those who report on them—is rampant. A YouGov poll conducted last December found that three-quarters of Americans agreed that science is a force for good in the world. Yet when asked if they truly believe what scientists tell them, only 36 per cent of respondents said yes. Just 12 per cent expressed strong confidence in the press to accurately report scientific findings. (Although according to a 2012 paper by Gordon Gauchat, a University of North Carolina sociologist, the erosion of trust in science over the past 40 years has been almost exclusively confined to two groups: conservatives and regular churchgoers. Counterintuitively, it is the most highly educated among them—with post-secondary education—who harbour the strongest doubts.)</p>

<p>The term “elitist” has become one of the most used, and feared, insults in American life. Even in the country’s halls of higher learning, there is now an ingrained bias that favours the accessible over the exacting.</p>

<p>The digital revolution, which has brought boundless access to information and entertainment choices, has somehow only enhanced the lowest common denominators—LOL cat videos and the Kardashians. Instead of educating themselves via the Internet, most people simply use it to validate what they already suspect, wish or believe to be true. It creates an online environment where Jenny McCarthy, a former Playboy model with a high school education, can become a worldwide leader of the anti-vaccination movement, naysaying the advice of medical professionals.</p>

<p>Most perplexing, however, is where the stupid is flowing from. As conservative pundit David Frum recently noted, where it was once the least informed who were most vulnerable to inaccuracies, it now seems to be the exact opposite. “More sophisticated news consumers turn out to use this sophistication to do a better job of filtering out what they don’t want to hear,” he blogged.</p></blockquote>

<p>Emma Teitel notes that digital media is making the problem worse, with the public experiencing information overload as society rapidly changes, as outlined in Alvin Toffler&#8217;s <strong><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Future_Shock">Future Shock</a></strong>. She <a href="http://www.macleans.ca/culture/going-viral-at-the-expense-of-our-privacy/">writes</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>60 per cent of Canadians would not change their Internet or phone behaviour if they suspected the government was spying on them. We are clearly fascinated by the secretly recorded outbursts of the morally bankrupt and grotesque—à la Rob Ford and Los Angeles Clippers owner Donald Sterling—but when it comes to the erosion of privacy among normal people at the hands of government and big corporations, we’re more or less ambivalent. It appears we’d rather share spoken-word poems on Facebook about the vacuous nature of social media than make a stink about the possibility that our government and the telecom companies that pander to it are taking advantage of us while we do.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Censorship Becoming Pointless with e-Readers]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/18/censorship/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-18T17:57:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/18/censorship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Google&#8217;s acquisition of Motorola is likely to pay off, with glowing reviews of their new $130 smartphone putting all of their competitors on notice. Last year Nokia announced a <a href="http://www.cnet.com/products/nokia-lumia-520/">$100 Lumia 520 smartphone</a> running Windows phone, and Google and Microsoft are going to continue to try to undercut each other to vie for dominance of the developing market. IDC data indicate that in 2013, the average worldwide <a href="http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS24461213">price of a smartphone was $337</a>, down from $387 in 2012. With Google using Motorola to dramatically undercut the market prices are likely to fall faster than anticipated, in a move that will be a major win for consumers in developing markets. IDC predicted that the average worldwide smartphone price would fall to $265 by 2017, while the North American average of $531 would rise to $567, but with Google and Microsoft pushing entry level phones I predict it will go down significantly.</p>

<p>Recently, it&#8217;s hit the news that parents in an Idaho school district successfully campaigned to remove Sherman Alexie&#8217;s acclaimed Young Adult novel, The Absolutely True Diary of a Part-Time Indian. The multi award winning book was pulled from the shelves after parents objected to its coarse language, references to masturbation, and political criticism of Christian conservatives. Parents called <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20140428/11320827052/censorious-parent-calls-cops-teen-giving-away-books-local-park.shtml">the cops on a student at the high school</a> giving out free copies of the book to peers after the school pulled the book.</p>

<p>The American Library Association has pointed out how farcical censorship is when the #1 most banned book, <strong>Captain Underpants</strong>, <a href="http://ncac.org/censorship-article/state-of-censorship-unabridged-contributions-from-our-participants/">is read by parents to children</a>. The potty humour in the book is designed to make young children giggle and parents roll their eyes. Challenges to the book highlight the absurdity of one group of parents deciding on behalf of every other family in a library district what morals the children are to be raised with.</p>

<p>The National Coalition Against Censorship highlights in their Kids Rights to Read Project that the majority of the most influential books of all time were at one time censored:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/ncac-banned.png" title="&#34;70% of 'Books that shaped America' have been banned&#34;" alt="&#34;70% of 'Books that shaped America' have been banned&#34;"></p>

<p>The actions of the student in distributing the book, which they love, to younger students in year 10 shows that an intergeneration values disconnect is not going to be solved with parental censorship of the media or libraries, and ultimately highlight why teenagers are justified in abandoning the values of their parents.</p>

<p>Attempts at book censorship are going to become increasingly farcical when technology allows individual consumers to buy books that aren&#8217;t stocked in their local library or their local state. <a href="http://www.marketingcharts.com/wp/online/87-of-american-adults-now-access-the-internet-41043/">97% of 18-29</a> year olds use the internet.</p>

<p>2014 figures show that tablet ownership in the US is up to <a href="http://www.marketingcharts.com/wp/online/us-tablet-ownership-update-january-2014-39508/">44% of the adult population</a>, and <a href="http://www.pewinternet.org/files/old-media//Files/Reports/2014/PIP_E-reading_011614.pdf">50% of adults have either a tablet or an e-reader</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/tablet-ereader.png" title="&#34;50% of adults in the United States how have either a tablet or an e-reader&#34;" alt="&#34;50% of adults in the United States how have either a tablet or an e-reader&#34;"></p>

<p>Nielsen has slightly higher estimates of Smartphone ownership among teens, estimating that 70 percent of teens aged 13-17 <a href="http://www.nielsen.com/us/en/newswire/2013/ring-the-bells-more-smartphones-in-students-hands-ahead-of-back.html">own smartphones</a>, while 79% of young adults aged 18-24 do.</p>

<p>Figures from September 2013 show that <a href="http://www.pewinternet.org/files/old-media//Files/Reports/2013/PIP_Tablets%20and%20e-readers%20update_101813.pdf">46% of 16-17 year olds have tablets</a>, while 24% have e-book readers. 91% of them have cell phones, while 68% have smartphones.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/pew-smartphone-household.png" title="Pew Household income vs Smartphone ownership rates" ></p>

<p>Smartphones are owned by only 41% of people in with a household income under $30,000 US, rising to 84% of those with household incomes over $150,000. Hopefully with entry level smartphones offering decent performance at US $100, cellphone customers in low income households will move to smartphones in a few years.</p>

<p>One of the other major areas where censorship has played out is in sex education, where conservative states have passed laws banning factual sex education and enforcing ineffectual abstinence-only curricula. With smartphone access to apps by <a href="https://healthcenter.uoregon.edu/Home/SexPositive.aspx">Oregon university</a> and other providers these laws will quickly become redundant, as teens seek out factual, unbiased information online.</p>

<p>Any ideology, political or religious, that requires the censorship of every family within a school district is not going to survive the age of the internet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ultra-leftists]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/06/ultra-leftists/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T08:20:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/06/ultra-leftists</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In June 2011 <a href="http://chipberlet.blogspot.com.au/">Chip Berlet</a> saw Occupy Wall Street facing a takeover by parasitic sectarian groups, and republished his 1999 essay on <a href="http://chipberlet.blogspot.com.au/2011/06/abstaining-from-bad-sects.html">cadre ultra-leftist sects</a>. The entire essay is worth a read, here are some highlights:</p>

<blockquote><p>To describe cadre-based sectarian ultra-leftists as tedious and disruptive is a charitable understatement</p></blockquote>

<p>Noting the similarity of leftist political division to religious sectarianism:</p>

<blockquote><p>When a sect tries to enforce these views on everyone, member and non-member alike, the sect [embraces] an inappropriate demand for a mass group to accept uncritically the ideological precepts of a specific group or individual.</p></blockquote>

<p>On the requirement to toe the party line, ostensibly reached though consultation</p>

<blockquote><p>Once a specific position is arrived at, cadre are expected to support the decision, and refrain from any disagreement with or criticisms of the &#8220;line&#8221; with persons or groups outside of the cadre organization. When people talk about &#8220;The Party Line,&#8221; they mean the line the cadre group members are bound to uphold in public.</p>

<p>Ultra-leftism is an egocentric form of mythopoetic martyrdom whereby practitioners anoint themselves as the beleaguered guardians of the one true political line. They read long impenetrable manifestos at public meetings. They show up at mass demonstrations with helmets and hockey sticks for a game of self-fulfilling prophecy that often results in violence as they hurl themselves at police. They inevitably urge a course of action that is hopelessly out of touch with reality. Even Lenin called this an &#8220;infantile disorder.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>The fragmentation of the media environment has attenuated the failure of ultra-leftists to appeal to centrist and soft left voters. Currently the brain drain on twitter is going into overdrive with pepole defending pointless <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-05-05/q-and-a-protesters-target-pyne/5432200">interruption of the ABC&#8217;s QandA program</a></p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('ND290z2kr2o');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ND290z2kr2o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('ND290z2kr2o-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ND290z2kr2o/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ND290z2kr2o" id="ND290z2kr2o" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ND290z2kr2o/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ND290z2kr2o" id="ND290z2kr2o-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Student protesters interrupt Q&A</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >A group of rowdy protesters brings the ABC&#8217;s Q&A program to an abrupt halt as they chant to interrupt a debate about university funding. Read more: http://ab.co/1kOqUFe</div>
</div>


<p>Berlet quotes Andrew Freenberg on how leftist groups prioritise an identity of revolution over effective campaigning:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sectarianism in the movement was based on a sense of moral superiority that was effective in motivating an in-group but incompatible with its expansion among those sympathetic to its program. Moral heroism mobilized the troops, but it was accompanied by a characteristic romantic elitism rooted in a sense of differentness, of sacrifice and oppression&#8230; Many new left groups preferred to substitute individual morality for politics and became obsessively concerned with establishing the revolutionary personal identity of their members at the expense of effective action on the real world.</p></blockquote>

<p>Some of the social psychologists who&#8217;ve studied inter-group conflict and how it applies to politics recommend that people try to reach <a href="http://www.civilpolitics.org/content/tom-edsalls-guide-what-each-side-gets-right/">across party lines to find comonality on key issues</a>, and recognise what their opponents get right. If an asteroid were heading towards earth and was going to destroy the planet, people would instinctively reach across party lines to solve the problem as quickly as possible, rather than trying to boost their poll numbers with divisive rhetoric over the failings of the other side. Jonathan Haidt&#8217;s research suggests that Progressives have more work to do than Conservatives in trying to understand the perspective of voters they disagree with.</p>

<p>Bonus - Keating telling whiny protestors to get a job.</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('ghaU7KMJAks');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ghaU7KMJAks&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('ghaU7KMJAks-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ghaU7KMJAks/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ghaU7KMJAks" id="ghaU7KMJAks" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ghaU7KMJAks/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ghaU7KMJAks" id="ghaU7KMJAks-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">&#8216;Go and get a job&#8217; (1995)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Paul Keating is not a fan of student protesters, who should apparently &#8216;get a job&#8217; and do some work &#8216;like the rest of us&#8217;. More: http://ab.co/keatinginsults</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sarah Palin, Anti-Christian]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/01/palin/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-01T12:07:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/05/01/palin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sarah Palin has joked at an NRA convention that if she was running the country, waterboarding is how she would baptise terrorists. The whole crowd cheered and jeered:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('A7vdAlzh-jo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/A7vdAlzh-jo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('A7vdAlzh-jo-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/A7vdAlzh-jo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A7vdAlzh-jo" id="A7vdAlzh-jo" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/A7vdAlzh-jo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A7vdAlzh-jo" id="A7vdAlzh-jo-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Sarah Palin: If I Were President &#8216;Waterboarding Is How We&#8217;d Baptize Terrorists&#8217;</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Sarah Palin, former Vice Presidential candidate announced at the National Rifle Association&#8217;s &#8220;Stand and Fight Rally&#8221; on Sunday 4/27/2014
&#8220;If I were in charge, they would know that waterboarding is how we baptize terrorists.&#8221;</div>
</div>


<p>Andrew Sullivan is one of few critics who is willing to stand up and <a href="http://dish.andrewsullivan.com/2014/04/28/the-pernicious-poison-of-palin-ctd/">criticise her with the full force she deserves</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Now look how far we have come from the original notion – pioneered by Charles Krauthammer and popularized by “24″ – that torture should only be used in the hypothetical ticking time-bomb case. That argument – only ever hypothetical – nonetheless assumes that torture is evil and should only be used in extremis to prevent imminent catastrophe. Palin, in contrast, like her party, has long since blown past such niceties. She believes that torture should be the first resort – a sign of how America treats its foes, a badge of honor.</p>

<p>What can one say but that this is a bona fide fascistic sentiment. It revels in violence against individuals tied down by their hands and feet and strapped to a terrifying board in order to be suffocated hundreds of times to near-death&#8230; Even totalitarian regimes have publicly denied their torture. Their reticence and lies are some small concession of vice to the appearance of virtue. Not Palin – who wants to celebrate brutal torture as the American way.</p></blockquote>

<p>Sullivan notes that in <a href="http://www.pewforum.org/2009/04/29/the-religious-dimensions-of-the-torture-debate/">recent polling</a> on the issue, 62% of White evangelical Christians support torture, while only 40% of religiously unaffiliated Americans do. Support for torture is highest among those who attend church weekly. Torture has become a <em>Christian</em> value in America:</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/pew-torture.png" width="2009" title="Pew polling on torture against suspected terrorists" ></p>

<blockquote><p>It seems to me, moreover, that torture is a far graver evil, even for orthodox theologians, than non-procreative or non-marital sex. And yet today’s Christianists are obsessed about the latter and not just indifferent to the former, but actually in favor of it. It’s this twisted set of priorities, this exquisitely misplaced set of fears, and this utter ignorance of even basic Christian teaching that reveals all that’s so terribly wrong with American Christianity. It has become its own nemesis.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marketing of euthenasia]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/30/euthenasia/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-30T12:09:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/30/euthenasia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many driving safety advertising campaigns use shocking images of death and disfigurement to drive safely, obey the road rules and put on a seat belt. The &#8216;embrace life&#8217; campaign has avoided shock and horror and instead opted for a positive message about seatbelts:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('h-8PBx7isoM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/h-8PBx7isoM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('h-8PBx7isoM-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/h-8PBx7isoM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h-8PBx7isoM" id="h-8PBx7isoM" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/h-8PBx7isoM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h-8PBx7isoM" id="h-8PBx7isoM-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Embrace Life - always wear your seat belt</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >For all licensing and broadcast information visit: http://www.alexandercommercials.co.uk

All material © 2010 Sarah Alexander/Daniel Cox/Sussex Safer Roads Partnership. WARNING: All rights of the producer and of the owner of the work reserved. Unauthorised copying, public performance, radio or tv broadcasting of this material is prohibited.

Music by Siddhartha Barnhoorn - http://www.sidbarnhoorn.com
An original approach to road safety advertising from the Sussex Safer Roads Partnership. 
http://www.sussexsaferroads.gov.uk
Join the Facebook group for Embrace Life at http://www.tinyurl.com/embracetv</div>
</div>


<p>People often try to put thoughts of death and suffering out of their minds, as they cause anguish and consternation. Positive messages are more likely to be talked about among families and peer-groups.</p>

<p>The voluntary euthanasia campaign has had <a href="http://www.hootville.com/marketingeuthanasia">verry little success</a> in getting their message across.</p>

<blockquote><p>Here’s a list of some groups / issues currently out-performing [voluntary euthanasia]:</p>

<ul>
<li>live cattle;</li>
<li>puppies born in puppy farms;</li>
<li>asylum seekers;</li>
<li>transgendered people;</li>
<li>homosexuals;</li>
<li>the disabled;</li>
<li>victims of domestic violence;</li>
<li>the corral in the barrier reef;</li>
<li>farmers affected by fracking;</li>
<li>victims of sexual abuse at the hands of clergy.</li>
</ul>


<p>These groups are a laundry list of disenfranchised, under-resourced, abused, neglected and unorganised – yet each of them outperform [voluntary euthanasia] week-in, week-out in the battle for media space, barbeque discussions and political response.</p></blockquote>

<p>The &#8216;pro-choice&#8217; movement that advocates for a woman&#8217;s right to choose abortion (or not) is careful to state that they are not &#8216;pro-abortion&#8217;. They don&#8217;t prescribe the circumstances under which they believe a woman should seek an abortion, they leave the choice to the individual. The label &#8216;Dying with Dignity&#8217; may not be a good name for the voluntary euthanasia movement, and the group &#8217;<a href="https://www.mja.com.au/journal/2013/198/4/doctors-support-law-reform-voluntary-euthanasia">Doctors for Voluntary Euthanasia Choice</a>&#8217;, are approaching a better label.</p>

<p>Death and suffering are taboo because the thought of them cuases distress, so the voluntary euthanasia movement needs to find positive ways to communicate their message. Additionally, the voluntary euthanasia movement has focussed on ultra-leftist audiences to the detriment of broad community outreach.</p>

<p>In 2010 a study of Australian attitudes to abortion, <a href="https://www.mja.com.au/journal/2010/193/1/australian-attitudes-early-and-late-abortion">published in the MJA</a> found that contextual details about specific scenarios made people more permissive in their approach to laws:</p>

<blockquote><p>The sensitivity of Australians’ views on abortion to contextual details may have implications for other debates about ethics. The more permissive attitude elicited when context was provided in our study may, for example, carry over to debates about euthanasia, the use of medicine or technology for human enhancement, organ donation, and embryonic stem cell research. It is an open question whether policy formation should be informed by views about abstract propositions or about cases containing contextual details.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Trolley Problem - Would You Push The Fat Man?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/14/trolley-problem/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T21:11:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/14/trolley-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The New York Times has a good discussion of the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/11/24/books/review/would-you-kill-the-fat-man-and-the-trolley-problem.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=1&amp;">Trolley Problem</a></p>

<blockquote><p>You are walking near a trolley-car track when you notice five people tied to it in a row. The next instant, you see a trolley hurtling toward them, out of control. A signal lever is within your reach; if you pull it, you can divert the runaway trolley down a side track, saving the five — but killing another person, who is tied to that spur. What do you do? Most people say they would pull the lever: Better that one person should die instead of five.</p>

<p>Now, a different scenario. You are on a footbridge overlooking the track, where five people are tied down and the trolley is rushing toward them. There is no spur this time, but near you on the bridge is a chubby man. If you heave him over the side, he will fall on the track and his bulk will stop the trolley. He will die in the process. What do you do? (We presume your own body is too svelte to stop the trolley, should you be considering noble self-sacrifice.)</p></blockquote>

<p>I loved Jonathan Haidt&#8217;s reconciliation of moral psychology with the old philosophical question, and this is an area where a lot of people are turning to hard science to understand ethical reasoning.</p>

<p>Fun facts:</p>

<blockquote><p>In 1944, new German V-1 rockets started pounding the southern suburbs of London, though they were clearly aimed at more central areas. The British not only let the Germans think the rockets were on target, but used double agents to feed them information suggesting they should adjust their aim even farther south. The government deliberately placed southern suburbanites in danger, but one scientific adviser, whose own family lived in South London, estimated that some 10,000 lives were saved as a result. A still more momentous decision occurred the following year when America dropped atom bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki on the argument that a quick end to the war would save lives — and by macabre coincidence, the Nagasaki bomb was nicknamed Fat Man. Similar calculations are being made right now. One has only to think of collateral damage in military strikes, or of the justifications offered for torturing terrorism suspects. At their best, such reasonings are valid; at their worst, they are a writhing nest of weasels.</p></blockquote>

<p>If it is considered ethical to select which civilians die in enemy bombings, is it ethical to subject your own soldiers to <a href="http://www.nyam.org/news/press-releases/2008/3096.html">chemical weapons</a> during tests?</p>

<blockquote><p>In the early 1940s, medical scientists funded by the U.S. Chemical Warfare Service conducted painful mustard gas experiments on at least 60,000 American soldiers. The Allies, including the governments of Canada, Britain, Australia, and the United States, conducted these experiments on their own soldiers in order to identify the impact of chemical weapons on the health of soldiers.</p></blockquote>

<p>Many people see this as one of the cases of the long history of morally dubious, and often downright criminal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_experimentation_in_the_United_States">human experiments carried out without informed consent</a>. Nazi scientists during the Nuremberg trials cited American human experiments carried out without the knowledge of prison inmates.</p>

<p>In some areas it&#8217;s hard to tell whether the history of abuses of human experimentation is worse in the US or in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi_human_experimentation">Nazi Germany</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_human_experimentation">Japan</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poison_laboratory_of_the_Soviet_secret_services">Russia</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp_22">North Korea</a>.</p>

<p>Many international critics successfully argue against human rights abuses in other countries, but freqently do so while <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/And_you_are_lynching_Negroes">covering up their own</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why are Australians so Down on Refugees?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/14/refugee/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T18:30:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/14/refugee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Barney Zwartz, retired religion columnist for the Age, has a good piece on the <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-04-14/zwartz-sparking-the-moral-imagination-of-the-masses/5388414">messaging of refugee advocates</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The message was that [refugee advocates] were the compassionate ones, the moral ones, the real Australians. The implication, well-understood and resented by opponents, is that those who disagree with the protesters are selfish, uncaring and/or racist and/or morally torpid&#8230;</p>

<p>Stigmatising half the population is no way to persuade people; it is no way to change refugee policy. Nor do I believe it is accurate. How such a large proportion of Australians came to see people fleeing persecution as illegals, queue jumpers, economic migrants, and a threat to our national economy and security is too big a subject to tackle here, but it is the successful result of malign policy and media slanting.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is quite a complex issue indeed. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moral_Foundations_Theory">Moral Foundations Theory</a> shows that most political arguments touch on six core values:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Care</strong>/<strong>harm</strong> for others, protecting them from harm.<br/>
<strong>Fairness</strong>/<strong>cheating</strong>, Justice, treating others in proportion to their actions
<strong>Liberty</strong>/<strong>oppression</strong>, characterizes judgments in terms of whether subjects are tyrannized.<br/>
<strong>Loyalty</strong>/<strong>betrayal</strong> to your group, family, nation.
<strong>Authority</strong>/<strong>subversion</strong> for tradition and legitimate authority.
<strong>Sanctity</strong>/<strong>degradation</strong>, avoiding disgusting things, foods, actions.</p></blockquote>

<p>Jonathan Haidt, the theory&#8217;s author has found that people have strange ideas about the notion of Sanctity. When asked if it&#8217;s OK for an old lady to tear up an unwanted national flag to wipe down her toilet bowl, many people are disgusted and outraged, but struggle to say why it&#8217;s wrong to use her own property in the privacy of her own home in the way she wishes. The majority of people believe that the flag is a sacred symbol, and indeed the Union Jack is made up of three crucifixes. Many Australians feel a sense of social identity from their belonging to the nation state, and John Howard would not have mandated that every public school must have a national flag in 2004 if it didn&#8217;t make for powerful propaganda. When Amanda Bishop and Phil Lloyd satirised the prime minister having sex wrapped in an Australian flag liberals were amused while conservatives <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2011-09-20/mps-angered-over-gillard-satire-sex-scene/2908158">were out for blood</a></p>

<div class="figure"><a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2011-09-20/mps-angered-over-gillard-satire-sex-scene/2908158"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/kerr-flag.png" link="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2011-09-20/mps-angered-over-gillard-satire-sex-scene/2908158" title="Miranda Kerr's bum received a much warmer reception from conservatives than Amanda Bishop's" ><p>Miranda Kerr&#8217;s bum received a much warmer reception from conservatives than Amanda Bishop&#8217;s</span></a></div>


<p>Many racists express a concern that the country is being &#8220;polluted&#8221; by migrants and their cultural values and religious beleifs. But the vast majority of people do <a href="http://www.themonthly.com.au/blog/richard-cooke/2013/07/25/1374721635/bogans-and-boat-people-pt1">not hold racist sentiments towards immigrants</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>More than 60% of us said we wanted immigration to increase or stay the same. In Germany that figure was 22%&#8230; For a bunch of racists, we are unusually tolerant.</p>

<p>In 2009 Australia had the highest level of immigration per capita in the OECD, eclipsing influxes that have caused tabloid pandemonium elsewhere. A quarter of us were born overseas, almost half have at least one overseas born parent. Interracial marriage, often identified by demographers as a truer indicator of racism than expressed attitudes, is the norm here. A majority of third generation non-English speaking immigrants intermarry, most to Anglo-Celtic Australians. Our treatment of boat people isn&#8217;t just different to how other countries treat refugees. It&#8217;s different to how Australians themselves treat immigrants of every other kind.</p></blockquote>

<p>One of the real issues in modern Australia, however, is that while inner city white collar voters enjoy the benefits of globalisation, outer suburban blue collar workers feel deeply concerned about their jobs going offshore. It&#8217;s easier to sell a carbon tax to inner city architects and engineers that design solar panels than to outer suburbs steelworkers and bricklayers that see solar panels manufactured in China and shipped in. Similarly the divide over refugees may not be as much about racism as about class inequality and <a href="http://www.themonthly.com.au/blog/richard-cooke/2013/07/30/1375142271/bogans-and-boat-people-pt-2">job security concerns</a>.</p>

<p>So the Moral Foundation of Sanctity can explain racist opposition to immigration, but anyone that doesn&#8217;t want the country &#8220;polluted&#8221; by refugees would feel the same way about migrants. With the opposition to refugees greater than to migrants, there are other issues at play. Security is frequently portrayed as a major issue, and the claim that Australia&#8217;s borders and soveringnty must be &#8220;protected&#8221; is an effective argument about how people don&#8217;t want their respect for authority to be subverted by people smugglers.</p>

<p>The fact that Howard used military vessels to intercept the Tampa in the same way that customs vessels would target drug smugglers powerfully shaped Australian perceptions of the &#8220;security risk&#8221; of asylum seekers. After the September 11th attacks and 2002 Bali Bombings it became harder for liberals to criticise the use of the Australian military to repel the Tampa. Explaining that Hazara muslims are persecuted by Al-Queda, and that Iranians are mostly secularists repressed by a theocratic government has become harder ever since. The claim that asylum seekers are &#8220;illegals,&#8221; while a blatant lie that has been debunked endlessly, continues to be a powerful tool to elicit the feeling that asylum seekers and people smugglers are subverting Australia&#8217;s rules.</p>

<p>Haidt&#8217;s analysis shows that Sanctity, Authority and Loyalty are moral foundations that social conservatives prioritise, while Compassion, Fairness and Liberty are principles that liberals prioritise. Libertarian care deeply about limiting the size of government because they prioritise freedom from opression above all other moral foundations. Strongly progressive voters base their moral intuitions on compassion far more than any other moral foundation. Critically, social conservatives do not lack compassion, they just base their moral intuitions on compassion in equal proportion to other foundations.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s been well established that compassion is the <a href="http://www.crikey.com.au/2013/07/29/let-them-all-come-is-stop-the-boats-for-unthinking-progressives/">only moral foundation</a> being advocated by some progressives. Unfortunately, progressive voices articulate a desire for compassion but don&#8217;t don&#8217;t seem to speak out effectively on how the Australian notion of fairness and egalitarianism is effectively manipulated.</p>

<p>Australia is one of the only countries that links our humanitarian refugee intake to the number of irregular arrivals. The notion that refugees should join a &#8220;queue&#8221; is a powerful appeal to Australia&#8217;s sense of fairness that doesn&#8217;t have simple three word slogan answers. In reality, the UNHCR had 7.1 million refugees in 2011 while <a href="http://theconversation.com/what-role-does-australia-play-in-accepting-the-worlds-refugees-8328">only 79,800 were resettled</a>, meaning that the UNHCR &#8220;queue&#8221; may not clear for any one refugee in their lifetime.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s so much more to write on when it comes to refugees, but the progressive narrative needs to move away from overrepresenting racism in the Australian community. Malcom Fraser prevented Vietnamese from making risky voyages to Australia by boat by setting up a processing centre in Indonesia that quickly processed asylum seekers and put genuine refugees on a plane to the mainland. With conflicts like <a href="http://data.unhcr.org/syrianrefugees/regional.php">Syria</a>, global refugee numbers are not going down, so the issue is going to need more than three word slogans focussed on the current electoral cycle. That will mean having regional resettlement agreements, which can&#8217;t effectively be negotiated without bipartisanship, which can&#8217;t be achieved without swinging voters on side, which can&#8217;t be achieved unless progressive rhetoric changes to inform, rather than castigate political moderates that currently buy into media misrepresentation of the issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2013 NSW Crime Figures Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/13/bocsar/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T13:43:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/13/bocsar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The NSW Bureau of Crime Statistics And Reporting has <a href="http://apo.org.au/research/nsw-recorded-crime-statistics-2013">released figures from 2013</a> showing the trends in crime reporting.</p>

<blockquote><p>This report presents data on crime reported to, or detected by, the NSW Police Force from January 1995 to December 2013, with a focus on the statistical trends for the 24 months ending December 2013. The data were extracted from the Computerised Operational Policing System (COPS) of the NSW Police Force in February 2014.</p>

<p>The report includes an overview of trends in the most recent two-year period for major offence categories, firstly for NSW and then across NSW regions broken down to the Local Government Area (LGA) level. At the State level, for the 24-month period to the end of December 2013 two major offence categories have been trending upwards: indecent assault, act of indecency and other sexual offences (up 7.8%) and fraud (up 13.2%). Seven of the 17 major offence categories were trending downwards: robbery without a weapon (down 11.2%), break and enter dwelling (down 13.3%), break and enter non-dwelling (down 10.5%), motor vehicle theft (down 12.9%), steal from motor vehicle (down 5.0%), steal from person (down 11.8%) and malicious damage to property (down 8.1%).</p>

<p>The NSW graphs for rates of violent and property offences are on page 7 of the report. For violent offences using the 12-month moving average (light grey line) we can see a downward path over the past five years and this can also be seen in the trend tests for the levels of reported offences in Table 1.1. The property offences graph using the 6-month moving average (light grey line) indicates a strong downward path since about 2000 to 2010, after which it stablised before dropping again more recently. Table 1.1 for trend tests on the levels of property offences indicates a stable trend over the last five years, however a significant decrease over the two most recent years.</p></blockquote>

<p>Interestingly, the largest increase in any crime was in &#8220;traffic regulatory offences&#8221;, meaning that the NSW government is using mobile speed cameras to issue more tickets to fill state coffers.</p>

<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/bocsar2013.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eye Tracking Can Predict Political Preferences]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/05/eye-tracking/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-05T10:08:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/04/05/eye-tracking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jefferson wrote that &#8220;The same political parties which now agitate the United States, have existed through all time.&#8221;</p>

<p>Researchers using eye tracking technology have evaluated how much time people look at images within a <a href="http://m.motherjones.com/politics/2014/04/inquiring-minds-john-hibbing-physiology-ideology">collage like this one</a>:</p>

<div class="figure"><a href="http://m.motherjones.com/politics/2014/04/inquiring-minds-john-hibbing-physiology-ideology"><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/mj-collage-pol.png" link="http://m.motherjones.com/politics/2014/04/inquiring-minds-john-hibbing-physiology-ideology" title="Tracking which images you look at can predict your disgust response, and your political preference" ><p>Tracking which images you look at can predict your disgust response, and your political preference</span></a></div>


<p>Researchers found that the eye tracking predicted the political preferences of the individuals. This suggests that the disgust response is genetically innate to the individual, meaning that political preferences may result from genes. Thus, there will always be liberals and conservatives. Chris Mooney interviewed the main researcher on his results on the <em>Inquiring Minds</em> podcast:</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="http://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F142960723&amp;"></iframe>


<p>David Pizarro has researched the disgust responses of liberals and conservatives, and evaluated how they relate to views on sexuality:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('5YL3LT1ZvOM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5YL3LT1ZvOM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('5YL3LT1ZvOM-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/5YL3LT1ZvOM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YL3LT1ZvOM" id="5YL3LT1ZvOM" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/5YL3LT1ZvOM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5YL3LT1ZvOM" id="5YL3LT1ZvOM-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">David Pizarro: The strange politics of disgust</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >What does a disgusting image have to do with how you vote? Equipped with surveys and experiments, psychologist David Pizarro demonstrates a correlation between sensitivity to disgusting cues &#8211; a photo of feces, an unpleasant odor &#8211; and moral and political conservatism.

TEDTalks is a daily video podcast of the best talks and performances from the TED Conference, where the world&#8217;s leading thinkers and doers give the talk of their lives in 18 minutes (or less). Look for talks on Technology, Entertainment and Design &#8211; plus science, business, global issues, the arts and much more.
Find closed captions and translated subtitles in many languages at http://www.ted.com/translate

Follow TED news on Twitter: http://www.twitter.com/tednews
Like TED on Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/TED

Subscribe to our channel: http://www.youtube.com/user/TEDtalksDirector</div>
</div>


<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mHhSYyvI-5k&amp;list=PLB4uoi02B2hPwxZsIP3yPmBGKxwHZ3USu&amp;index=1">Sex, Death and the Meaning of Life</a></p>

<p>Jonathan Haidt gave <a href="http://reason.com/reasontv/2013/02/26/sex-and-the-culture-war-your-body-may-be">an interesting talk to libertarians on how libertarians are low on the disgust scale</a></p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('Pmz10uQsTYE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Pmz10uQsTYE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('Pmz10uQsTYE-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Pmz10uQsTYE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pmz10uQsTYE" id="Pmz10uQsTYE" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Pmz10uQsTYE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pmz10uQsTYE" id="Pmz10uQsTYE-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">It&#8217;s Hard to Gross Out a Libertarian: Jonathan Haidt on Sex, Politics, and Disgust</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >&#8220;Morality isn&#8217;t just about stealing and killing and honesty, it&#8217;s often about menstruation, and food, and who you are having sex with, and how you handle corpses,&#8221; says NYU social psychologist Jonathan Haidt, who is author of THE RIGHTEOUS MIND: WHY GOOD PEOPLE ARE DIVIDED BY POLITICS.

Haidt argues that our concern over these victimless behaviors is rooted in our biology. Humans evolved to feel disgusted by anything that when consumed makes us sick. That sense of disgust then expanded &#8220;to become a guardian of the social order.&#8221;

This impulse is at the core of the culture war. Those who have a low sensitivity to disgust tend to be liberals or libertarians; those who are easily disgusted tend to be conservative.

Haidt discussed his views on morality and politics at an event hosted by the Reason Foundation, which was held on February 19, 2013 at the Museum of Sex. Haidt&#8217;s lecture was followed by a Q&A with New York Times Science Columnist John Tierney.

Approximately 35 minutes. Camera by Jim Epstein and Naomi Brockwell. Edited by Epstein.

Go to http://Reason.com/Reason.tv for downloadable versions of this video and subscribe to Reason TV&#8217;s YouTube Channel to receive automatic notifications when new material goes live.</div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Need for Public Intellectuals]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/22/public-intellectuals/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-22T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/22/public-intellectuals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Chompers <a href="http://rationallyspeaking.blogspot.com.au/2014/03/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-fish.html">noted</a></p>

<blockquote><p>“Citizens of the democratic societies should undertake a course of intellectual self defense to protect themselves from manipulation and control, and to lay the basis for meaningful democracy”</p></blockquote>

<p>Robin <a href="http://america.aljazeera.com/opinions/2014/3/kristof-academicswritingpublicintellectuals.html">writes</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Academics used to face a hard choice between writing for sequestered journals that few people read and newspapers and magazines that are hard to break into. Now we have a third option: the blogs and Tumblr, Twitter and Facebook accounts of the social media world.</p>

<p>In my first year out of graduate school, I wrote an article in The American Political Science Review about the politics of fear. I can count on my hand the number of people outside academia who have read it. Not because it’s abstruse or irrelevant but because it’s cloistered behind journal paywalls that only academics can easily scale.</p>

<p>Now I have a blog, where I write about political theory, McCarthyism and bathroom breaks. As many as 20,000 people read my posts — in a single day. Thousands of my colleagues are doing the same thing, many with even bigger readerships. Group blogs such as Crooked Timber and Lawyers, Guns and Money offer platforms to political scientists, economists, sociologists, literary critics, historians and philosophers, and judging by the comments they attract, they are read by a great many nonacademics.</p>

<p>&#8230;At their best, intellectuals do more than package their research into digestible bits for policymakers or the public. They force us to think beyond the limits of the day, to ask the questions no one is asking. They are an invitation to imaginative excess and political trespass. Academic experts in the mainstream media reassure us with their authority; young intellectuals in the little magazines arrest us with their divinations.</p>

<p>&#8230;Writers and academics who fret over the fate of public intellectuals may think they are debating vital questions of the culture. But their discussions are myopically focused on the writing habits of a rapidly disappearing elite.</p></blockquote>

<p>Pigliucci has launched <a href="http://scientiasalon.org/">Scientia Salon</a> to stimulate discussions among a general audience, noting that pursuit of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eudaimonia">eudaimonic</a> life involves reasoned discourse.</p>

<blockquote><p>3) We acknowledge — as is clear from research in the cognitive sciences — that human beings navigate the world by deploying a complex mixture of reason and emotion, and that they often engage in rationalization more than rationality.</p>

<p>4) Indeed, we think with David Hume that this is a crucial part of human nature, since emotions are necessary in order to actually care about anything in the first place.</p>

<p>5) But we also think that open and reasoned discourse is fundamental for the pursuit of a eudaimonic life on the part of the individual, as well as for the development of a just and democratic society.</p>

<p>6) Scientia, understood as the broadest range of scientific and humanistic disciplines that positively contribute to human understanding, is an essential tool for pursuing that eudaimonic life and achieving that just society.</p>

<p>7) In order to make an impact, we think that writers concerned with these matters ought to aim at a wide audience, avoid unnecessary jargon, and write clearly and engagingly, even humorously when appropriate.</p>

<p>8) We therefore welcome authors and readers who are willing to contribute honestly and substantively to an open dialogue on all matters of the intellect, especially those of general interest to fellow human beings.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Your Self-Identity Holding You Back?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/21/identity/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T22:31:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/21/identity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Paul Graham in 2009 <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/identity.html">noted that many discussions about religion and politics quickly stir up emotion in people</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>As a rule, any mention of religion on an online forum degenerates into a religious argument. Why? Why does this happen with religion and not with Javascript or baking or other topics people talk about on forums?</p>

<p>&#8230;Then it struck me: this is the problem with politics too. Politics, like religion, is a topic where there&#8217;s no threshold of expertise for expressing an opinion. All you need is strong convictions.</p></blockquote>

<p>Graham notes that discussions about a Bronze age war rarely devolve to political arguments, whereas modern conflicts that involve citizens of one&#8217;s country often do. He concludes:</p>

<blockquote><p>If people can&#8217;t think clearly about anything that has become part of their identity, then all other things being equal, the best plan is to let as few things into your identity as possible.</p></blockquote>

<p>One of the greatest reasons that humans have dominated the entire planet is our ability to collaborate with non-kin groups. Many people refer to others in the same religion, nationality or political group as their brothers and sisters.</p>

<p>Psychologists have demonstrated cultural polarisation based on the affiliation with social institutions. Kahan writes in <strong><a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1630002">Fixing the communications failure</a></strong>:</p>

<blockquote><p>In a famous 1950s psychology experiment, researchers showed students from two Ivy League colleges a film of an American football game between their schools in which officials made a series of controversial decisions against one side. Asked to make their own assessments, students who attended the offending team&#8217;s college reported seeing half as many illegal plays as did students from the opposing institution. Group ties, the researchers concluded, had unconsciously motivated students from both colleges to view the tape in a manner that favoured their own school.</p>

<p>Since then, a growing body of work has suggested that ordinary citizens react to scientific evidence on societal risks in much the same way. People endorse whichever position reinforces their connection to others with whom they share important commitments. As a result, public debate about science is strikingly polarized. The same groups who disagree on &#8216;cultural issues&#8217; — abortion, same-sex marriage and school prayer — also disagree on whether climate change is real and on whether underground disposal of nuclear waste is safe.</p></blockquote>

<p>Kahan and his colleagues have identified <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_cognition">a range of issues where perceived clashes with cultural values of a particular group polarise opinion</a>.</p>

<p>Some people that retire after working in a job for decades, say as an accountant, will volunteer one day a week for a charity because the question &#8220;what do you do?&#8221; is often the second thing that people are asked.</p>

<p>Personally, I think that the strength of social identity is a strong reason why the <strong>No True Scotsman</strong> fallacy frequently comes up in political and religious arguments. It goes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_true_Scotsman">like this</a></p>

<blockquote><p> Person A: No democracy ever starts a war<br/>
 Person B: Well country X is a democracy and they started a war<br/>
 Person A: Well, no <strong>true</strong> democracy ever starts a war</p></blockquote>

<p>LessWrong has an article about <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/jsh/strategic_choice_of_identity/">choosing a small identity</a> to bootstrap a larger worldview. Identities like &#8220;growth mindset&#8221; or &#8220;someone who tries new things&#8221; or a &#8220;jack of all trades.&#8221; Perhaps the best one is &#8220;truth-seeker,&#8221; which is a more useful mindset to have than any religious or political identity that can lead someone to become closed minded when they perceive a threat to their group&#8217;s values.</p>

<p>Studies have found that when a sports fan&#8217;s team loses, <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/thesalt/2013/09/20/224148230/diet-of-defeat-why-football-fans-mourn-with-high-fat-food">junk food sales go up</a>. Jonathan Haidt has written about how non-violent sport is probably an outlet for the tribalism we previously needed to survive.</p>

<p>A recent Pew Social Trends study has found that millenials are the generation <a href="http://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2014/03/07/millennials-in-adulthood/">least inclined to identify with political and religious institutions</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Pew Research Center surveys show that half of Millennials (50%) now describe themselves as political independents and about three-in-ten (29%) say they are not affiliated with any religion. These are at or near the highest levels of political and religious disaffiliation recorded for any generation in the quarter-century that the Pew Research Center has been polling on these topics.</p></blockquote>

<p>If you identify as a Democrat then you will probably be personally offended when Obama does something that goes against your values (every president will dissapoint their supporter base on some issues), and you&#8217;ll probably feel your blood pressure go up every time you see a clip of FOX news. Making matters worse these days, search engines are increasingly using algorithms to return results that are relevant based on previous searches. This means that someone who has spent time searching for political content will get more political content in future internet searches, and someone that reads conservative websites often will find conservative websites in their search results more often.</p>

<p>Bill Maher has explained how people have less in common than they used to, now that people all get customised stories based on what they&#8217;ve clicked on in the past:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('VZbH_2feBPI');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VZbH_2feBPI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('VZbH_2feBPI-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VZbH_2feBPI/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZbH_2feBPI" id="VZbH_2feBPI" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VZbH_2feBPI/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZbH_2feBPI" id="VZbH_2feBPI-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Bill Maher discovers &#8220;The Filter Bubble&#8221;</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >February 21, 2014
Episode 308

Eli Pariser: Beware online &#8220;filter bubbles&#8221;
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B8ofWFx525s

The Filter Bubble: How the hidden web is shaping lives
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6_sim_Wc3mY

Additional information:
http://www.thefilterbubble.com
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filter_bubble

&#8212;&#8211;
Transcript

New Rule: The Sparkletts guy must tell me why nobody talks around the water cooler anymore. But, wait, I think I know why. It&#8217;s because as a culture we don&#8217;t have enough in common anymore.

And that&#8217;s because the Internet, which was supposed to unite the world, has become too adept at serving us personalized content. Do you know what I saw on Yahoo&#8217;s front page this morning? No, you don&#8217;t, because mine isn&#8217;t the same as yours. People get newsfeeds now that just spit back customized stories based on what we&#8217;ve clicked on in the past.

So, I, for example, might see a lot of stories about pot, American history, and, of course &#8220;Christian Mingle.&#8221;

Whereas, Ted Nugent just gets ads for Prozac and bullets. 

So, yes, welcome to the brave new world of micro-targeting which &#8211; look, admittedly is often harmless. No one gets hurt if my computer tells me, &#8220;You bought &#8216;James Taylor&#8217;s Greatest Hits.&#8217; You might also enjoy this pillow and these sleeping pills.&#8221; 

Or, &#8220;You&#8217;ve shown an interest in &#8216;nipple slips.&#8217; Here&#8217;s every picture ever of Tara Reid.&#8221; [slide of Tara Reid] 

&#8220;And here&#8217;s an article about another slippery boob.&#8221; [slide of Ted Cruz]

But, consider this: back in the olden days, this is how people spent their time on the subway. [older slide of crowded subway] Amazing, isn&#8217;t it? Everyone is reading a newspaper and no one is masturbating. 

Here&#8217;s a subway car today. [three people sit staring at hand-held devices] Everyone is playing &#8220;Angry Birds,&#8221; and no one is getting news. Or, if they are, it&#8217;s their Facebook newsfeed, which is now how a third of their &#8211; of adults get their news.

And this month, Facebook unveiled an app called &#8220;Paper,&#8221; which Mark Zuckerberg calls &#8211; quote &#8211; &#8220;the best personalized newspaper in the world.&#8221;

Yeah, I suppose the Washington Post is okay, like when it uncovered Watergate, but Facebook lets you share pictures of your lunch and do this? [he gestures and makes goofy face] 

But&#8230;but, hey, if one of the richest companies in America can get richer by making you a little stupider every time you look at your phone, small price to pay. 

And, boy, does it make you stupider. &#8220;Paper&#8221; tracks the news you&#8217;re interested in and gives you more of that and less of everything else, never burdening you with contradictory information or telling you anything new. That&#8217;s what makes it news. 

But, only seeing the stuff that confirms the opinions you already have isn&#8217;t news. It&#8217;s Fox News.

The reason so many Americans, for example, think climate change is a hoax, is that their only source for science news is Glenn Beck, Fox and  Matt Drudge, the &#8220;cracker trifecta.&#8221; 

Newspapers may be old-fashioned, but here&#8217;s what we&#8217;re losing if you never see one: they are trying to tell you what&#8217;s actually important, not just what&#8217;s important to you. You may not read the whole paper, but you at least see headlines making you aware that something&#8217;s going on outside of your micro-targeted world of fashion or music or wiccans or zombies or whatever you&#8217;re into. 

I don&#8217;t enjoy reading about climate change. It&#8217;s depressing. But, for example, I recently saw a headline that said jellyfish are taking over the ocean. Which I found alarming.

So, I read the article. And, apparently, yes, jellyfish are the cockroaches of the sea and will happily eat all the toxic shit we&#8217;re putting in the ocean which is killing everything else down there. But, the jellyfish are, like, &#8220;Oil? Fuckin&#8217; love it!&#8221; &#8220;Plastic? I had some for lunch.&#8221;

Yes, jellyfish: 500 million years of yechhh&#8230;and now their time has come. [laughter] 

And, no one is going to hear about it unless a jellyfish washes up on a beach and exposes its nipple.

Additional information:
http://www.hbo.com/real-time-with-bill-maher#/real-time-with-bill-maher/episodes/12/308-episode/index.html

&#8212;&#8211;
Fair Use Notice
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_use

The use of the following media materials is protected by the Fair Use Clause of the U.S. Copyright Act of 1976, which allows for the rebroadcast of copyrighted materials for the purpose of commentary, criticism, and education.</div>
</div>


<p>Mark Scott, managing director of the ABC, has warned Christians not to get <a href="http://www.biblesociety.org.au/news/mark-scott-christians-beware-christian-bubble">trapped in a bubble</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“The new media environment presents a great risk for Christians to retreat. There will be in a media sense, a massive global market for Christians to listen to Christian music, to read Christian books, to see Christian films, to partake in Christian blogs, to comment on each other’s Christian Facebook pages and to live in that Christian world.</p></blockquote>

<p>The same can be true for atheists, Democrats, Republicans, Libertarians and everyone else who reads only information that agrees with their preferred label. If a Democrat spends 90% of their time reading websites that have a liberal perspective, then it might be harder for them to empathise with someone who disagrees with their political philosophy, and we see that all the time in snarky comments that seek to dogpile critics rather than address their concerns.</p>

<p>Hume said that truth emerges from arguments between friends, and if you want to find the truth you need to be prepared to listen to people that disagree, and start from the position that you could be wrong. Especially in this day and age of filter bubbles and personalised news feeds, we must be vigilant about how much time we spend cloistered inside media that reflect our own viewpoints, and not be afraid to find dissenting voices. If people constrain themselves to only engaging in discussion with groups of people with the same interests, social capital could go down as we lose the water cooler.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Frozen Promote Lesbianism and Bestiality?]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/16/frozen/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T09:39:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/16/frozen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>News outlets all around the world are making fun of a Christian radio host that suggested that the academy award winning film <em>Frozen</em> was inspired by Satan to teach children to embrace lesbianism and bestiality. All while maintaining that he&#8217;s not a conspiracy theorist:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('fGefLMWcZOU');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/fGefLMWcZOU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('fGefLMWcZOU-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/fGefLMWcZOU/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fGefLMWcZOU" id="fGefLMWcZOU" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/fGefLMWcZOU/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fGefLMWcZOU" id="fGefLMWcZOU-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">TGIF - Frozen promotes lesbianism and bestiality?</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >The ABC&#8217;s TGIF program takes down Swanson&#8217;s stupidity.</div>
</div>


<p>Does Frozen promote lesbianism and bestiality? No. What it does do is promote that self respect and the resilience to overcome adversity and criticism is a strength in girls. Look at the lyrics for <strong>Let it Go</strong>:</p>

<blockquote><p> I don’t care what they’re going to say&#8230;<br/>
 It’s funny how some distance makes everything seem small<br/>
 And <strong>the fears that once controlled me can’t get to me at all</strong><br/>
 It’s time to see what I can do<br/>
 To test the limits and break through<br/>
 <strong>No right, no wrong, no rules for me</strong><br/>
 I’m free&#8230;<br/>
 You’ll never see me cry&#8230;</p>

<p> I’m never going back, the past is in the past<br/>
 Let it go, let it go<br/>
 And I’ll rise like the break of dawn<br/>
 Let it go, let it go<br/>
 That perfect girl is gone<br/>
 Here I stand in the light of day</p></blockquote>

<p>The producer noted how they&#8217;d departed from the original story to humanise Elsa by making her a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frozen_(2013_film">sibling of the protagonist</a>):</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Hans Christian Andersen’s original version of The Snow Queen is a pretty dark tale and it doesn&#8217;t translate easily into a film. For us the breakthrough came when we tried to give really human qualities to the Snow Queen. When we decided to make the Snow Queen Elsa and our protagonist Anna sisters, that gave a way to relate to the characters in a way that conveyed what each was going through and that would relate for today&#8217;s audiences. This film has a lot of complicated characters and complicated relationships in it. There are times when Elsa does villainous things but because you understand where it comes from, from this desire to defend herself, you can always relate to her. &#8216;Inspired by&#8217; means exactly that. There is snow and there is ice and there is a Queen, but other than that, we depart from it quite a bit. We do try to bring scope and the scale that you would expect but do it in a way that we can understand the characters and relate to them.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Most critics have hailed the film as promoting self-acceptance and the resilience to overcome bullying and abusive relationships, especially for girls. If hardline radio hosts think that promotes lesbianism, I&#8217;d love to see the kind of script that he&#8217;d put forward to directors.</p>

<p>Rachel Marie Stone notes how Frozen will <a href="http://rachelmariestone.religionnews.com/2014/03/20/frozen-evangelical-purity-culture-like-girl/">help girls overcome purity culture</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I read halfway though this article and literally couldn't believe what I was reading... amazing!]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/15/fake-quote/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-15T17:58:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/15/fake-quote</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As Voltaire once said “The secret of being a bore is to tell everything,” and the secret to a good story is to get the listener to care about the exposition before you reveal the conclusion. Many of the videos that go viral online are professionally produced pieces that fool the viewers into sharing the video with friends without realising that it&#8217;s an ad. Recently millions of people shared an artsy black and white video where actors pretended to kiss people for the first time, which was really an ad for a boring clothing company.</p>

<p>Last year Saatchi came up with this piece of slo-mo genius:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('7PVVT9V2CM0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/7PVVT9V2CM0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('7PVVT9V2CM0-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/7PVVT9V2CM0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7PVVT9V2CM0" id="7PVVT9V2CM0" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/7PVVT9V2CM0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7PVVT9V2CM0" id="7PVVT9V2CM0-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">First Taste</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Tasty video bit at #TEDxSydney 2013.

Video by Saatchi & Heckler</div>
</div>


<p>Ads that go viral commonly focus on universal human truths that work in any language, on any continent. Many of the popular &#8220;best of web&#8221; videos focus on stunning nature scenes, slo-mo extreme sports and people with weird dance moves.</p>

<p>The parodies of the first kiss video are many and varied, this one with dogs is one of the stranger ones:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('026IsHhSupE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/026IsHhSupE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('026IsHhSupE-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/026IsHhSupE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=026IsHhSupE" id="026IsHhSupE" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/026IsHhSupE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=026IsHhSupE" id="026IsHhSupE-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">FIRST SNIFF (First Kiss Parody)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >We asked some dogs to kiss for the first time&#8230;</div>
</div>


<p>Vice created a more realistically awkward video by getting <a href="http://www.vice.com/shorties/we-got-twenty-british-strangers-who-arent-models-to-kiss-each-other">20 strangers who aren&#8217;t models to kiss each other</a>. As Vice notes, a growing number of websites are getting better at <a href="http://www.vice.com/read/the-internet-is-a-giant-lie-factory">tweaking algorithms to pump traffic-magnet content</a> like “Half Way Through These Photos, I Could Barely Handle It. But I’m Glad I Made It to the End… Amazing.” As each new meme website tries to game social algorithms by running other people&#8217;s content under misleading headlines, more and more stories are just beat-ups created for the online outrage factory. One of the most egregious examples of race baiting is the bogus story that Chinese people are grinding up babies into soup to increase their sexual potency. In the race to reach the lowest common denominator, no barrier is too low for a quick buck.</p>

<p>Vice notes that there was a time when <a href="http://www.vice.com/read/why-are-so-many-social-media-managers-dipshits">ad agencies veered on the side of overestimating the intelligence of their customer base</a>, which was before the days of social media marketing managers. Just see <a href="https://www.facebook.com/corporatebollocks">Corporate Brand(R)</a> on Facebook for <strong><em>fantastic</em></strong> ideas about user engagement. For every retweet that the douchebags get, they&#8217;ll even donate up to the fixed amount that they already decided to donate.</p>

<p>Sometimes people make <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2011/05/anatomy-of-a-fake-quotation/238257/">honest mistakes by repeating accidental misquotes</a>, and indeed one of the most famous Voltaire quotes <a href="http://listverse.com/2008/05/15/top-10-famous-historic-misquotes/">wasn&#8217;t his</a>. Others are trying to make money using the internet to peddle bunk that&#8217;s been around for centuries:</p>

<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onmouseover="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('QQ5ump8ZAn8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;z-height:0.5;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QQ5ump8ZAn8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, document.getElementById('QQ5ump8ZAn8-rep'));myAnchor.parentNode.onmouseover = null;myAnchor.classList.remove('youtube-over');return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link youtube-over" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/QQ5ump8ZAn8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QQ5ump8ZAn8" id="QQ5ump8ZAn8" onclick="return false;">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/QQ5ump8ZAn8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QQ5ump8ZAn8" id="QQ5ump8ZAn8-rep" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Derren Brown - Science Of Scams | Brick Breaking</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Derren Brown shows us a paranormal trick.
SUBSCRIBE. AND LIKE</div>
</div>


<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLE4B268704A5460AD">full series of the Science of Scams is worth a watch</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tech in Education - Khan Academy to offer SAT prep]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/07/ed-tech/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T04:14:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/07/ed-tech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The New York Times has some interesting coverage of recent developments in Ed-Tech. One of the big ones is that the US&#8217;s SAT system is going to <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/06/education/major-changes-in-sat-announced-by-college-board.html?_r=0">partner with Khan Academy</a> to deliver a classroom-focussed college admissions system, and provide preparation to everyone, rather than just the rich that can afford test prep classes. Free preparation for one of the most important US college admissions tests is a <a href="http://khanacademy.com/sat">major coup for the organisation</a> that Bill Gates and others have backed to improve the learning quality of students around the world.</p>

<p>Related news:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/03/education/new-all-digital-curriculums-hope-to-ride-high-tech-push-in-schoolrooms.html?rref=education">New All-Digital Curriculums Hope to Ride High-Tech Push in Schoolrooms</a></p>

<blockquote><p>English language curriculums built entirely on a digital platform — replacing written textbooks, worksheets or printed study guides — are about to enter the market from several companies, with promises that they will change the nature of classroom learning across the country.</p>

<p>The Obama administration has pledged to provide high-speed Internet connections to 15,000 schools over the next two years, districts are purchasing tablets and laptops for students, and on Friday, President Obama announced $400 million in corporate commitments from the software companies Adobe and Prezi, which will donate software to teachers. Meanwhile, other companies are rushing in.</p>

<p>On Monday at an education conference in Austin, Tex., Joel Klein, the former chancellor of New York City public schools and the current chief executive of Amplify, the education unit of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation, will introduce a digital English language arts curriculum for middle school.</p>

<p>Mr. Klein said the new software, which will run on a variety of devices and is priced at $45 per student a year, includes videos, games and vocabulary apps and allows teachers to track student writing and give feedback directly online. “This is not a bunch of souped-up PDFs,” Mr. Klein said, referring to digital versions of print documents.</p>

<p>McGraw Hill, the textbook publisher, will also announce this week that it has signed a partnership with StudySync, a company that creates digital English curriculum tools that have been deployed in 22,000 classrooms and are priced at about a third of Amplify’s rate.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/15/magazine/no-child-left-untableted.html?pagewanted=all">No Child Left Untableted</a></p>

<blockquote><p>The key, he said, is personalized learning — breaking free of the mass-production model, tailoring the curriculum to the student and redesigning it around proven competence rather than accrued face time, so that each student can go at his own pace. “Now your job is not to dispense knowledge,” Britt told the trainees. “It’s to facilitate learning. No longer is the teacher the bottleneck between students and knowledge. Rather, the teacher architects the environment — in the classroom, on the tablet, online, everywhere.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Textbook efficiency:</p>

<blockquote><p>When I asked Arne Duncan, the U. S. secretary of education, about the increasing amounts of money being spent by school systems on educational technology, he said: “We spend precious taxpayer money now on textbooks, buses, milk, all kinds of things. The real question is, ‘How do you spend more effectively?’ ” Electronic readers could make textbooks better and cheaper, he said. “As a country we spend $7 billion to $8 billion a year on textbooks. My simple question is, ‘Why?’ ” Referring to the six-year textbook-adoption cycle some states still use, Duncan said, “That’s a Neanderthal system.”</p></blockquote>

<p>GigaOm has a good <a href="http://gigaom.com/2014/02/25/how-khan-academy-is-using-design-to-pave-the-way-for-the-future-of-education/">take on the design of Khan Academy</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Since its founding in 2008 by former hedge fund analyst Salman Khan — who was making math videos in his spare time to tutor his cousins — Khan Academy has emerged as a new way to learn; one that is self paced, approachable, conversational and tries to help students master individual subjects before moving onto the next. Bill Gates is a big fan, as is Google and its chairman Eric Schmidt as well as Netflix CEO Reed Hastings — all of these big names invested in the company.</p>

<p>While millions of users access the site and watch its content, 30,000 classrooms also use the videos for in-school teaching and teachers (they call them coaches) can also use the software to track student progress. All of these moving parts are tied together by an understated design ethos that highlights simplicity, puts the content first, and tries remove frustration and friction from learning.</p></blockquote>

<p>Audrey Watters has a good roundup of the politics of the &#8220;Open&#8221; label being applied beyond open source tech, especially in Ed-Tech where &#8220;open&#8221; online courses <a href="http://hackeducation.com/2013/12/16/top-ed-tech-trends-2013-open/">more commonly means &#8221;<strong>open for business</strong>&#8221;</a>. She has an extensive discussion of MOOC hype <a href="http://hackeducation.com/blog/tag.php?Search_Tag=ed-tech%20trends%202013">in a 2013 rundown</a> that is well worth a read.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anglican church heading for fracture]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/06/anglican-fracture/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T21:49:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/06/anglican-fracture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently a London vicar <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/friendlyatheist/2014/03/04/london-vicar-to-defy-church-leaders-by-marrying-atheist-same-sex-partner/">publicly committed to marrying his same sex partner</a> despite church rules forbidding it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Evidence of Alarming Vaccine Side Effects]]></title>
    <link href="http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/05/vaccine-side-effects/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T22:52:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nsewell.com//blog/2014/03/05/vaccine-side-effects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://nsewell.com//images/vaccine-side-effects.jpg" alt="Alarming Vaccine Side Effects" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
